<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<algorithms version="110505">
<algorithm name="SectLabel" version="110505">
<variant no="0" confidence="0.000000">
<title confidence="0.9984225">
Learning to Predict Problematic Situations in a Spoken Dialogue
System: Experiments with How May I Help You?
</title>
<author confidence="0.980695">
Marilyn Walker, Irene Langkilde, Jerry Wright, Allen Gorin, Diane Litman
</author>
<affiliation confidence="0.853401">
AT&amp;T Labs—Research
</affiliation>
<address confidence="0.9605895">
180 Park Avenue
Florham Park, NJ 07932-0971 USA
</address>
<email confidence="0.999429">
walker,jwright,algor,diane@research.att.corn, ilangkil@isi.edu
</email>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.993915" genericHeader="abstract">
Abstract
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9997282">
Current spoken dialogue systems are deficient in
their strategies for preventing, identifying and re-
pairing problems that arise in the conversation. This
paper reports results on learning to automatically
identify and predict problematic human-computer
dialogues in a corpus of 4774 dialogues collected with
the How May I Help You spoken dialogue system.
Our expectation is that the ability to predict prob-
lematic dialogues will allow the system&apos;s dialogue
manager to modify its behavior to repair problems,
and even perhaps, to prevent them. We train a
problematic dialogue classifier using automatically-
obtainable features that can identify problematic
dialogues significantly better (23%) than the base-
line. A classifier trained with only automatic fea-
tures from the first exchange in the dialogue can
predict problematic dialogues 7% more accurately
than the baseline, and one trained with automatic
features from the first two exchanges can perform
14% better than the baseline.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.998992" genericHeader="introduction">
1 Introduction
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999977377777778">
Spoken dialogue systems promise efficient and nat-
ural access to a large variety of information sources
and services from any phone. Systems that sup-
port short utterances to select a particular function
(through a statement such as &amp;quot;Say credit card, col-
lect or person-to-person&amp;quot;) are saving companies mil-
lions of dollars. Research prototypes exist for appli-
cations such as personal email and calendars, travel
and restaurant information, and personal banking
(Baggia et al., 1998; Walker et al., 1998; Seneff et
al., 1995; Sanderman et al., 1998; Chu-Carroll and
Carpenter, 1999) inter a/ia. Yet there are still many
research challenges: current systems are limited in
the interaction they support and brittle in many re-
spects. We show how spoken dialogue systems can
learn to support more natural interaction on the ba-
sis of their previous experience.
One way that current spoken dialogue systems are
quite limited is in their strategies for detecting and
repairing problems that arise in conversation. If
a problem can be detected, the system can either
transfer the call to a human operator or modify its
dialogue strategy in an attempt to repair the prob-
lem. We can train systems to improve their ability to
detect problems by exploiting dialogues collected in
interactions with human users. The initial segments
of these dialogues can be used to predict that a prob-
lem is likely to occur. We expect that the ability to
predict that a dialogue is likely to be problematic
will allow the system&apos;s dialogue manager to apply
more sophisticated strategies to repairing problems,
and even perhaps, to prevent them.
This paper reports experiments on predicting
problems in spoken dialogue interaction by train-
ing a problematic dialogue predictor on a corpus of
4774 dialogues collected in an experimental trial of
AT&amp;T&apos;s How May I Help You (HMIHY) spoken dia-
logue system (Gorin et al., 1997; Riccardi and Gorin,
to appear; E. Ammicht and Alonso, 1999). In this
trial, the HMIHY system was installed at an AT&amp;T
customer care center. HMIHY answered calls from
live customer traffic and successfully automated a
large number of customer requests. An example of
a dialogue that HMIHY completed successfully is
shown in Figure 1.1
</bodyText>
<note confidence="0.434914">
SI: AT&amp;T How may I help you?
</note>
<table confidence="0.795349375">
UI: I need to [ uh ] put a call on my calling card please
S2: May I have your card number, please?
U2: 7 6 5 4 3 2 1 0 9 8 7 6 5 4
S3: What number would you like to call?
U3: 8 1 4 7 7 7 6 6 6 6 (rnisrecognized)
S4: May I have that number again?
U4: 8 1 4 7 7 7 6 6 6 6
S5: Thank you.
</table>
<figureCaption confidence="0.997803">
Figure 1: Sample TASKSUCCESS Dialogue
</figureCaption>
<bodyText confidence="0.97563575">
We shall refer to the dialogues with a TASKSUC-
CESS outcome, in which HMIHY successfully auto-
mates the customer&apos;s call, as the TASKSUCCESS dia-
logues. In addition to the TASKSUCCESS dialogues,
there are several other call outcomes, to be described
in detail below, which we consider problematic.
I The phone numbers, card numbers, and pin numbers in
the sample dialogues are artificial.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.996863">
210
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.9999873">
This paper reports results from a set of experi-
ments that test whether we can learn to automat-
ically predict that a dialogue will be problematic
on the basis of information the system has: (1)
early on in the dialogue; and (2) in real time. We
train an automatic classifer for predicting problem-
atic dialogues from features that can be automat-
ically extracted from the HMIHY corpus. The re-
sults show that we can learn to predict problematic
dialogues using fully automatic features with an ac-
curacy ranging from 72% to 87%, depending on how
much of the dialogue the system has seen so far.
Section 2 describes HMIHY and the dialogue corpus
which the experiments are based on. Section 3 de-
tails the encoding of the dialogues and the methods
used for utilizing the machine learning program RIP-
PER to train an automatic problematic dialogue pre-
dictor (Cohen, 1996). Section 4 presents the results
and section 5 summarizes the paper and describes
future work.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.890623" genericHeader="method">
2 Experimental System and Data
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999742242424243">
HMIHY is a spoken dialogue system based on the no-
tion of call routing (Gorin et al., 1997; Chu-Carroll
and Carpenter, 1999). In the HMIHY call rout-
ing system, services that the user can access are
classified into 14 categories, plus a category called
other for calls that cannot be automated and must
be transferred to a human operator (Gorin et al.,
1997).2 Each category describes a different task,
such as person-to-person dialing, or receiving credit
for a misdialed number. The system determines
which task the caller is requesting on the basis of
its understanding of the caller&apos;s response to the
open-ended system greeting AT&amp;T, How May I Help
You?. Once the task has been determined, the infor-
mation needed for completing the caller&apos;s request is
obtained using dialogue submodules that are specific
for each task (Abella and Gorin, 1999).
In addition to the TASKSUCCESS dialogues in
which HMIHY successfully automates the cus-
tomer&apos;s call, illustrated in Figure 1, and the calls
that are transferred to a human operator, there are
three other possible outcomes for a call, all of which
are problematic. The first category, which we call
HANGUP, results from a customer&apos;s decision to hang
up on the system. A sample HANGUP dialogue is
in Figure 2. A caller may hang up because s/he is
frustrated with the system; our goal is to learn from
the corpus which system behaviors led to the caller&apos;s
frustration.
The second problematic category (wizARD), re-
sults from a human customer care agent&apos;s decision to
take over the call from the system. Because HMIHY
is experimental, each call was monitored by a human
</bodyText>
<footnote confidence="0.867446">
2 One potential use of our results is to provide better rules
for making the transfer decision.
</footnote>
<note confidence="0.5038235">
Si: AT&amp;T How may I help you?
U1: I need credit please.
S2: Okay. What is the reason for the credit?
U2: Miss, uh, Miss, different area code than I needed.
</note>
<footnote confidence="0.679422333333333">
S3: Sorry. I need to know whether you need credit for
a wrong number, bad connection or a call that was cut
off.
U3: It is a wrong number. (impatient humming)
S4: What was the number that you dialed?
USER HANGS UP
</footnote>
<figureCaption confidence="0.998522">
Figure 2: Sample HANGUP Dialogue
</figureCaption>
<bodyText confidence="0.9999816">
agent serving as a wizard who could override the
system. There were a number of agents who partici-
pated as wizards during the trial of HMIHY and each
wizard was simply told to take over the call if s/he
perceived problems with the system&apos;s performance.
The wizard&apos;s decision was logged by the experimen-
tal setup, resulting in labelling the call as one that
the wizard took over.3 A dialogue where the wizard
decided that the dialogue was problematic and took
over the call is shown in Figure 3.
</bodyText>
<listItem confidence="0.849006363636364">
Si: AT&amp;T How may I help you?
UI: (silence)
52: Sorry. Please briefly tell me how I may help you?
U2: I&apos;m trying to call 1 8 hundred call A T T.
S3: Do you want to place a call?
U3: Through my calling card.
54: May I have your card number, please?
U4: It&apos;s 8 7 6 5 4 3 2 1 0 and then my pin number is 8
7 6 5. (misreeognized)
S5: Sorry. Please enter or say your card number again.
WIZARD STEPS IN
</listItem>
<figureCaption confidence="0.997995">
Figure 3: Sample WIZARD Dialogue
</figureCaption>
<bodyText confidence="0.931269363636364">
The third problematic category, the TASKFAILURE
dialogues, are cases where the system completed the
call, but carried out a task that was not the task
that the customer was actually requesting. An ex-
ample TASKFAILURE dialogue is given in Figure 4:
HMIHY interpreted utterance U2 as a request to
make a third-party call e.g. to bill it to my home
phone. HMIHY then asked the caller for the infor-
mation it needed to carry out this task, the caller
complied, and the system completed the call.
The corpus of 4774 dialogues used in our exper-
iments was collected in several experimental trials
of HMIHY on live customer traffic (Riccardi and
Gorin, to appear; E. Ammicht and Alonso, 1999),
and is referred to as HM2 in (Riccardi and Gorin, to
appear)). During the trial, all of the system behav-
iors were automatically recorded in a log file, and
later the dialogues were transcribed by humans and
labelled with a semantic category representing the
30f course we can only infer what might have motivated
the wizard to take over the call, but we assume that the wizard
had good reason for doing so.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.996852">
211
</page>
<figure confidence="0.609056583333333">
Si: AT&amp;T How may I help you?
Ul: (silence)
S2: Sorry. Please briefly tell me how I may help you?
U2: I wanta find out how much my bill&apos;s worth.
S3: What phone number would you like the call billed
to?
U3: Urn the access number.
S4: Sorry. Could I have that phone number again?
U4: 1 8 hundred 2 2 5 5 2 8 8.
55: What number would you like to call?
U5: 800 225 5288 (touchtone input)
S6: Thank you.
</figure>
<figureCaption confidence="0.99902">
Figure 4: Sample TAsKFAILuRE Dialogue
</figureCaption>
<bodyText confidence="0.99992675">
task that the caller was asking HMIHY to perform,
on a per utterance basis. The logfiles also included
labels indicating whether the wizard had taken over
the call or the user had hung up.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.990687" genericHeader="method">
3 Training an Automatic
</sectionHeader>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.98481">
Problematic Dialogue Predictor
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9976742">
Our experiments apply the machine learning pro-
gram RIPPER (Cohen, 1996) to automatically induce
a &amp;quot;problematic dialogue&amp;quot; classification model. RIP-
PER takes as input the names of a set of classes to
be learned, the names and ranges of values of a fixed
set of features, and training data specifying the class
and feature values for each example in a training set.
Its output is a classification model for predicting the
class of future examples. In RIPPER, the classifica-
tion model is learned using greedy search guided by
an information gain metric, and is expressed as an
ordered set of if-then rules.
To apply RIPPER, the dialogues in the corpus must
be encoded in terms of a set of classes (the output
classification) and a set of input features that are
used as predictors for the classes. We start with the
dialogue categories described above, but since our
goal is to develop algorithms that predict/identify
problematic dialogues, we treat HANGUP, WIZARD
and TASKFAILURE as equivalently problematic. Thus
we train the classifier to distinguish between two
classes: TASKSUCCESS and PROBLEMATIC. Note that
our categorization is inherently noisy because we do
not know the real reasons why a caller hangs up or a
wizard takes over the call. The caller may hang up
because she is frustrated with the system, or she may
simply dislike automation, or her child may have
started crying. Similarly, one wizard may have low
confidence in the system&apos;s ability to recover from er-
rors and use a conservative approach that results in
taking over many calls, while another wizard may be
more willing to let the system try to recover. Nev-
ertheless we take these human actions as a human
labelling of these calls as problematic. Given this
classification, approximately 36% of the calls in the
corpus of 4774 dialogues are PROBLEMATIC and 64%
are TASKSUCCESS.
Next, we encoded each dialogue in terms of a set
of 196 features that were either automatically logged
by one of the system modules, hand-labelled by hu-
mans, or derived from raw features. We use the
hand-labelled features to produce a TOPLINE, an es-
timation of how well a classifier could do that had
access to perfect information. The entire feature set
is summarized in Figure 5.
</bodyText>
<listItem confidence="0.9979065">
• Acoustic/ASR Features
— recog, recog-numwords, ASR-duration, dtmf-
flag, rg-modality, rg-grammar
• NLU Features
— a confidence measure for all of the possible
tasks that the user could be trying to do
— salience-coverage, inconsistency, context-shift,
top-task, nexttop-task, top-confidence, diff-
confidence
• Dialogue Manager Features
</listItem>
<bodyText confidence="0.6415996">
— sys-label, utt-id, prompt, reprompt, confirma-
tion, subdial
— running tallies: num-reprompts, num-
confirms, num-subdials, reprompt%, confir-
mation%, subdialogue%
</bodyText>
<listItem confidence="0.9932544">
• Hand-Labelled Features
— tscript, human-label, age, gender, user-
modality, clean-tscript, cltscript-numwords,
rsuccess
• Whole-Dialogue Features
</listItem>
<bodyText confidence="0.62437225">
— num-utts, num-reprompts, percent-reprompts,
num-confirms, percent-confirms,
num-
subdials, percent-subdials, dial-duration.
</bodyText>
<figureCaption confidence="0.988007">
Figure 5: Features for spoken dialogues.
</figureCaption>
<bodyText confidence="0.999998823529412">
There are 8 features that describe the whole dia-
logue, and 47 features for each of the first four ex-
changes. We encode features for the first four ex-
changes because we want to predict failures before
they happen. Since 97% of the dialogues in our cor-
pus are five exchanges or less, in most cases, any
potential problematic outcome will have occurred
by the time the system has participated in five ex-
changes. Because the system needs to be able to
predict whether the dialogue will be problematic us-
ing information it has available in the initial part of
the dialogue, we train classifiers that only have ac-
cess to input features from exchange 1, or only the
features from exchange 1 and exchange 2. To see
whether our results generalize, we also experiment
with a subset of features that are task-independent.
We compare results for predicting problematic dia-
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.989587">
212
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.99996852631579">
logues, with results for identifying problematic di-
alogues, when the classifier has access to features
representing the whole dialogue.
We utilized features logged by the system because
they are produced automatically, and thus could be
used during runtime to alter the course of the dia-
logue. The system modules that we collected infor-
mation from were the acoustic processer/automatic
speech recognizer (ASR) (Riccardi and Gorin, to ap-
pear), the natural language understanding (NLU)
module (Gorin et al., 1997), and the dialogue man-
ager (DM) (Abella and Gorin, 1999). Below we de-
scribe each module and the features obtained from
it.
ASR takes as input the acoustic signal and
outputs a potentially errorful transcription of what
it believes the caller said. The ASR features for
each of the first four exchanges were the output
of the speech recognizer (recog), the number of
words in the recognizer output (recog-numwords),
the duration in seconds of the input to the
recognizer (asr-duration), a flag for touchtone
input (dtmf-flag), the input modality expected
by the recognizer (rg-modality) (one of: none,
speech, touchtone, speech+touchtone, touchtone-
card, speech+touchtone-card, touchtone-date,
speech+touchtone-date, or none-final-prompt), and
the grammar used by the recognizer (rg-grammar).
The motivation for the ASR features is that any
one of them may have impacted performance. For
example, it is well known that longer utterances
are less likely to be recognized correctly, thus asr-
duration could be a clue to incorrect recognition re-
sults. In addition, the larger the grammar is, the
more likely an ASR error is, so the name of the
grammar rg-grammar could be a predictor of incor-
rect recognition.
The natural language understanding (NLU) mod-
ule takes as input a transcription of the user&apos;s utter-
ance from ASR and produces 15 confidence scores
representing the likelihood that the caller&apos;s task is
one of the 15 task types. It also extracts other
relevant information, such as phone or credit card
numbers. Thus 15 of the NLU features for each ex-
change represent the 15 confidence scores. There
are also features that the NLU module calculates
based on processing the utterance. These include
an intra-utterance measure of the inconsistency be-
tween tasks that the user appears to be requesting
(inconsistency), a measure of the coverage of the
utterance by salient grammar fragments (salience-
coverage), a measure of the shift in context between
utterances (context-shift), the task with the highest
confidence score (top-task), the task with the second
highest confidence score (nexttop-task), the value of
the highest confidence score (top-confidence), and
the difference in values between the top and next-
to-top confidence scores (duff-confidence).
The motivation for these NLU features is to make
use of information that the NLU module has based
on processing the output of ASR and the current dis-
course context. For example, for utterances that fol-
low the first utterance, the NLU module knows what
task it believes the caller is trying to complete. If it
appears that the caller has changed her mind, then
the NLU module may have misunderstood a previ-
ous utterance. The context-shift feature indicates
the NLU module&apos;s belief that it may have made an
error (or be making one now).
The dialogue manager (DM) takes the output of
NLU and the dialogue history and decides what it
should say to the caller next. It decides whether it
believes there is a single unambiguous task that the
user is trying to accomplish, and how to resolve any
ambiguity. The DM features for each of the first four
exchanges are the task-type label which includes a
label that indicates task ambiguity (sys-label), utter-
ance id within the dialogue (implicit in the encod-
ing), the name of the prompt played before the user
utterance (prompt), and whether that prompt was a
reprompt (reprompt), a confirmation (confirm), or a
subdialogue prompt (subdial), a superset of the re-
prompts and confirmation prompts.
The DM features are primarily motivated by pre-
vious work. The task-type label feature is to cap-
ture the fact that some tasks may be harder than
others. The utterance id feature is motivated by the
idea that the length of the dialogue may be impor-
tant, possibly in combination with other features like
task-type. The different prompt features for initial
prompts, reprompts, confirmation prompts and sub-
dialogue prompts are motivated by results indicating
that reprompts and confirmation prompts are frus-
trating for callers and that callers are likely to hy-
perarticulate when they have to repeat themselves,
which results in ASR errors (Shriberg et al., 1992;
Levow, 1998).
The DM features also include running tallies for
the number of reprompts (num-reprompts), number
of confirmation prompts (num-confirms), and num-
ber of subdialogue prompts (num-subdials), that had
been played up to each point in the dialogue, as well
as running percentages (percent-reprompts, percent.
confirms, percent-subdials). The use of running tal-
lies and percentages is based on the assumption that
these features are likely to produce generalized pre-
dictors (Litman et al., 1999).
The features obtained via hand-labelling were hu-
man transcripts of each user utterance (tscript), a
set of semantic labels that are closely related to the
system task-type labels (human-label), age (age) and
gender (gender) of the user, the actual modality of
the user utterance (user-modality) (one of: nothing,
speech, touchtone, speech+touchtone, non-speech),
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.998056">
213
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.999950315789474">
and a cleaned transcript with non-word noise infor-
mation removed (clean-tscript). From these features
we calculated two derived features. The first was the
number of words in the cleaned transcript (cltscript
numwords), again on the assumption that utterance
length is strongly correlated with ASR and NLU er-
rors. The second derived feature was based on cal-
culating whether the human-label matches the sys-
label from the dialogue manager (rsuccess). There
were four values for rsuccess: rcorrect, rmismatch,
rpartial-match and rvacuous-match, indicating re-
spectively correct understanding, incorrect under-
standing, partial understanding, and the fact that
there had been no input for ASR and NLU to oper-
ate on, either because the user didn&apos;t say anything
or because she used touch-tone.
The whole-dialogue features derived from the per-
utterance features were: num-utts, num-reprompts,
percent-reprompts, num-confirms, percent-confirms,
num-subdials, and per-cent-subdials for the whole di-
alogue, and the duration of the entire dialogue in
seconds (dial-duration) .
In the experiments, the features in Figure 5 except
the Hand-Labelled features are referred to as the AU-
TOMATIC feature set. We examine how well we can
identify or predict problematic dialogues using these
features, compared to the full feature set including
the Hand-Labelled features. As mentioned earlier,
we wish to generalize our problematic dialogue pre-
dictor to other systems. Thus we also discuss how
well we can predict problematic dialogues using only
features that are both automatically acquirable dur-
ing runtime and independent of the HMIHY task.
The subset of features from Figure 5 that fit this
qualification are in Figure 6. We refer to them as
the AUTO, TASK-INDEP feature set.
The output of each RIPPER experiment is a clas-
sification model learned from the training data. To
evaluate these results, the error rates of the learned
classification models are estimated using the resam-
pling method of cross-validation. In 5-fold cross-
validation, the total set of examples is randomly di-
vided into 5 disjoint test sets, and 5 runs of the learn-
ing program are performed. Thus, each run uses the
examples not in the test set for training and the re-
maining examples for testing. An estimated error
rate is obtained by averaging the error rate on the
testing portion of the data from each of the 5 runs.
Since we intend to integrate the rules learned
by RIPPER into the HMIHY system, we examine
the precision and recall performance of specific hy-
potheses. Because hypotheses from different cross-
validation experiments cannot readily be combined
together, we apply the hypothesis learned on one
randomly selected training set (80% of the data) to
that set&apos;s respective test data. Thus the precision
and recall results reported below are somewhat less
</bodyText>
<listItem confidence="0.9232294">
. Acoustic/ASR Features
— recog, recog-numwords, ASR-duration, dtmf-
flag, rg-modality
• NLU Features
— salience-coverage, inconsistency, context-shift,
top-confidence, cliff-confidence
• Dialogue Manager Features
— utt-id, reprompt, confirmation, subdial
— running tallies: num-reprompts,
um
</listItem>
<figureCaption confidence="0.7386595">
confirms, num-subdials, reprompt%, connfir--
mation%, subdialogue%
Figure 6: Automatic task independent (AUTO,
TASK-INDEP) features available at runtime.
</figureCaption>
<bodyText confidence="0.992598">
reliable than the error rates from cross-validation.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.999963" genericHeader="method">
4 Results
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999964742857143">
We present results for both predicting and identi-
fying problematic dialogues. Because we are inter-
ested in predicting that a dialogue will be problem-
atic at a point in the dialogue where the system can
do something about it, we compare prediction ac-
curacy after having only seen the first exchange of
the dialogue with prediction accuracy after having
seen the first two exchanges, with identification ac-
curacy after having seen the whole dialogue. For
each of these situations we also compare results for
the AUTOMATIC and AUTO, TASK-INDEP feature sets
(as described earlier), with results for the whole fea-
ture set including hand-labelled features. Table 1
summarizes the results.
The baseline on the first line of Table 1 repre-
sents the prediction accuracy from always guess-
ing the majority class. Since 64% of the dialogues
are TASKSUCCESS dialogues, we can achieve 64% ac-
curacy from simply guessing TASKSUCCESS without
having seen any of the dialogue yet.
The first EXCHANGE 1 row shows the results of
using the AUTOMATIC features from only the first
exchange to predict whether the dialogue outcome
will be TASKSUCCESS or PROBLEMATIC. The results
show that the machine-learned classifier can predict
problematic dialogues 8% better than the baseline
after having seen only the first user utterance. Using
only task-independent automatic features (Figure 6)
the EXCHANGE 1 classifier can still do nearly as well.
The ALL row for EXCHANGE 1 indicates that even
if we had access to human perceptual ability (the
hand-labelled features) we would still only be able
to distinguish between TASKSUCCESS and PROBLEM-
ATIC dialogues with 77% accuracy after having seen
the first exchange.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.995788">
214
</page>
<table confidence="0.999698818181818">
Features Used Accuracy (SE)
BASELINE (majority class) 64.0 %
EXCHANGE 1 AUTOMATIC 72.3 % 1.04 %
AUTO, TASK-INDEP 71.6 % 1.05 %
ALL 77.0 % 0.56 %
EXCHANGES 1862 AUTOMATIC 79.9 % 0.58 %
AUTO, TASK-INDEP 78.6 % 0.37 %
ALL 86.7 % 0.33 %
FULL DIALOGUE AUTOMATIC 87.0 % 0.72 %
AUTO, TASK-INDEP 86.7 % 0.82 %
TOPLINE ALL 92.3 % 0.72 %
</table>
<tableCaption confidence="0.999551">
Table 1: Results for predicting and identifying problematic dialogues (SE = Standard Error)
</tableCaption>
<bodyText confidence="0.999976769230769">
The EXCHANGE 18z2 rows of Table 1 show the re-
sults using features from the first two exchanges in
the dialogue to predict the outcome of the dialogue.&apos;
The additional exchange gives roughly an additional
7% boost in predictive accuracy using either of the
AUTOMATIC feature sets. This is only 8% less than
the accuracy we can achieve using these features af-
ter having seen the whole dialogue (see below). The
ALL row for EXCHANGE 18,z2 shows that we could
achieve over 86% accuracy if we had the ability to
utilize the hand-labelled features.
The FULL DIALOGUE row in Table 1 for AUTO-
MATIC and AUTO, TASK-INDEP features shows the
ability of the classifier to identify problematic dia-
logues, rather than predict them, using features for
the whole dialogue. The ALL row for the FULL DI-
ALOGUE shows that we could correctly identify over
92% of the outcomes accurately if we had the ability
to utilize the hand-labelled features.
Note that the task-independent automatic fea-
tures always perform within 2% error of the auto-
matic features, and the hand-labelled features con-
sistently perform with accuracies ranging from 6-8%
greater.
The rules that RIPPER learned on the basis of the
Exchange 1 automatic features are below.
</bodyText>
<construct confidence="0.809930833333333">
Exchange 1, Automatic Features:
if (el-top-confidence &lt; .924) A (el-dtmf-flag = &apos;1&apos;)
then problematic,
if (el-diff-confidence &lt; .916) A (el-asr-duration &gt; 6.92)
then problematic,
default is tasksuccess.
</construct>
<bodyText confidence="0.86832">
According to these rules, a dialogue will be prob-
lematic if the confidence score for the top-ranked
</bodyText>
<footnote confidence="0.994516">
4Since 23% of the dialogues consisted of only two ex-
changes, we exclude the second exchange features for those
dialogues where the second exchange consists only of the sys-
tern playing a closing prompt. We also excluded any features
that indicated to the classifier that the second exchange was
the last exchange in the dialogue.
</footnote>
<bodyText confidence="0.988814772727273">
task (given by the NLU module) is moderate or low
and there was touchtone input in the user utterance.
The second rule says that if the difference between
the top confidence score and the second-ranked con-
fidence score is moderate or low, and the duration
of the user utterance is more than 7 seconds, predict
PROBLEMATIC.
The performance of these rules is summarized in
Table 2. These results show that given the first ex-
change, this ruleset predicts that 22% of the dia-
logues will be problematic, while 36% of them ac-
tually will be. Of the dialogues that actually will
be problematic, it can predict 41% of them. Once
it predicts that a dialogue will be problematic, it is
correct 69% of the time. As mentioned earlier, this
reflects an overall improvement in accuracy of 8%
over the baseline.
The rules learned by training on the automatic
task-independent features for exchanges 1 and 2 are
given below. As in the first rule set, the features that
the classifier appears to be exploiting are primarily
those from the ASR and NLU modules.
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.945229">
Exchanges 18c2, Automatic
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.520132">
Task-
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.787759">
Independent Features:
</subsectionHeader>
<construct confidence="0.962742846153846">
if (e2-recog-numworcLs &lt; 0) A (el-diff-confidence &lt; .95)
then problematic.
if (el-salience-coverage &lt; .889) A (e2-recog contains
&amp;quot;I&amp;quot;) A (e2-asr-duration &gt; 7.48) then problematic.
if (el-top-confidence &lt; .924) A (e2-asr-duration &gt; 5.36)
A (el-asr-duration &gt; 8.6) then problematic.
if (e2-recog is blank) A (e2-asr-duration &gt; 2.8) then
problematic.
if (el-salience-coverage &lt; .737) A (el-recog contains
&amp;quot;help&amp;quot;) A (el-asr-duration &lt; 7.04) then problematic.
if (el-diff-confidence &lt; .924) A (el-dtmf-flag = &apos;1&apos;) A
(el-asr-duration &lt;6.68) then problematic.
default is tasksuccess.
</construct>
<bodyText confidence="0.690795333333333">
The performance of this ruleset is summarized in
Table 3. These results show that, given the first
two exchanges, this ruleset predicts that 26% of the
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.982237">
215
</page>
<table confidence="0.997442666666667">
Class Occurred Predicted Recall Precision
Success 64.1 % 78.3 % 89.44 % 73.14 %
Problematic 35.9 % 21.7 % 41.47 % 68.78 %
</table>
<tableCaption confidence="0.97208">
Table 2: Precision and Recall with Exchange 1 Automatic Features
</tableCaption>
<table confidence="0.998899">
Class Occurred Predicted Recall Precision
Success 64.1 % 75.3 % 91.42 % 77.81 %
Problematic 35.9 % 24.7 % 53.53 % 77.78 %
</table>
<tableCaption confidence="0.999885">
Table 3: Precision and Recall with Exchange 18z2 Automatic, Task-Independent Features
</tableCaption>
<bodyText confidence="0.999985531914894">
dialogues will be problematic, while 36% of them
actually will be. Of the problematic dialogues, it
can predict 57% of them. Once it predicts that a
dialogue will be problematic, it is correct 79% of
the time. Compared with the classifier for the first
utterance alone, this classifier has an improvement
of 16% in recall and 10% in precision, for an overall
improvement in accuracy of 7% over using the first
exchange alone.
One observation from these hypotheses is the clas-
sifier&apos;s preference for the asr-duration feature over
the feature for the number of words recognized
(recog-numwords). One would expect longer utter-
ances to be more difficult, but the learned rulesets
indicate that duration is a better measure of utter-
ance length than the number of words. Another ob-
servation is the usefulness of the NLU confidence
scores and the NLU salience-coverage in predicting
problematic dialogues. These features seem to pro-
vide good general indicators of the system&apos;s success
in recognition and understanding. The fact that the
main focus of the rules is detecting ASR and NLU
errors and that none of the DM behaviors are used
as predictors also indicates that, in all likelihood, the
DM is performing as well as it can, given the noisy
input that it is getting from ASR and NLU.
To identify potential improvements in the prob-
lematic dialogue predictor, we analyzed which hand-
labelled features made large performance improve-
ments, under the assumption that future work can
focus on developing automatic features that ap-
proximate the information provided by these hand-
labelled features. The analysis indicated that the
rsuccess feature alone improves the performance of
the TOPLINE from 88.5%, as reported in (Langkilde
et al., 1999), to 92.3%. Using rsuccess as the only
feature results in 73.75% accuracy for exchange 1,
81.9% accuracy for exchanges 1&amp;2 and 85.3% accu-
racy for the full dialogue. In addition, for Exchanges
1&amp;2, the accuracy of the AUTOMATIC, TASK-INDEP
feature set plus the rsuccess feature is 86.5%, which
is only 0.2% less than the accuracy of ALL the fea-
tures for Exchanges 1&amp;2 as shown in Table 1. The
rules that RIPPER learns for Exchanges 1&amp;2 when
the AUTOMATIC, TASK-INDEP feature set is aug-
mented with the single hand-labelled rsuccess fea-
ture is shown below.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.668958" genericHeader="method">
Exchanges 18z2, Rsuccess + Automatic
Task-Independent Features:
</sectionHeader>
<construct confidence="0.964898217391304">
if e2-salience-coverage &lt; 0.651 A e2-asr-duration &gt; 0.04
A e2-rsuccess=Rvacuous-match then problematic,
if e2-rsuccess=Rmismatch A el-top-confidence &lt; 0.909
then problematic,
if e2-rsuccess=Rmismatch A e2-context-shift &lt;0.014 A
e2-salience-coverage &gt; 0.2 A e2-recog-numwords &lt; 12 (
then problematic,
if e2-rsuccess=Rmismatch A el-rsuccess=Rmismatch
then problematic,
if e2-rsuccess=Rmismatch A e2-top-confidence &lt; 0.803
A e2-asr-duration &gt; 2.68 A e2-asr-duration &lt;6.32 then
problematic,
if el-rsuccess=Rmismatch A el-diff-confidence &gt; 0.83
then problematic,
if e2-rsuccess=Rmismatch A e2-context-shift &gt; 0.54
then problematic,
if e2-asr-duration &gt; 5.24 A e2-salience-coverage &lt; 0.833
A e2-top-confidence &lt; 0.801 A e2-recog-numwords &lt; 7
A e2-asr-duration &lt; 16.08 then problematic,
if el-diff-confidence &lt; 0.794 A el-asr-duration &gt; 7.2
A el-inconsistency &gt; 0.024 A el-inconsistency &gt; 0.755
then problematic,
default is tasksuccess
</construct>
<bodyText confidence="0.9994054">
Note that the rsuccess feature is frequently used in
the rules and that RIPPER learns rules that combine
the rsuccess feature with other features, such as the
confidence, asr-duration, and salience-coverage fea-
tures.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.998275" genericHeader="discussions">
5 Discussion and Future Work
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9991328">
In summary, our results show that: (1) All feature
sets significantly improve over the baseline; (2) Us-
ing automatic features from the whole dialogue, we
can identify problematic dialogues 23% better than
the baseline; (3) Just the first exchange provides sig-
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.996025">
216
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.999972">
nificantly better prediction (8%) than the baseline;
(4) The second exchange provides an additional sig-
nificant (7%) improvement, (5) A classifier based on
task-independent automatic features performs with
less than 1% degradation in error rate relative to
the automatic features. Even with current accuracy
rates, the improved ability to predict problematic
dialogues means that it may be possible to field the
system without human agent oversight, and we ex-
pect to be able to improve these results.
The research reported here is the first that we
know of to automatically analyze a corpus of logs
from a spoken dialogue system for the purpose of
learning to predict problematic situations. Our work
builds on earlier research on learning to identify di-
alogues in which the user experienced poor speech
recognizer performance (Litman et al., 1999). How-
ever, that work was based on a much smaller set of
experimental dialogues where the notion of a good or
bad dialogue was automatically approximated rather
than being labelled by humans. In addition, because
that work was based on features synthesized over the
entire dialogues, the hypotheses that were learned
could not be used for prediction during runtime.
We are exploring several ways to improve the per-
formance of and test the problematic dialogue pre-
dictor. First, we noted above the extent to which
the hand-labelled feature rsuccess improves classifier
performance. In other work we report results from
training an rsuccess classifier on a per-utterance level
(Walker et al., 2000), where we show that we can
achieve 85% accuracy using only fully automatic fea-
tures. In future work we intend to use the (noisy)
output from this classifier as input to our problem-
atic dialogue classifier with the hope of improving
the performance of the fully automatic feature sets.
In addition, since it is more important to minimize
errors in predicting PROBLEMATIC dialogues than er-
rors in predicting TASKSUCCESS dialogues, we intend
to experiment with RIPPER&apos;s loss ratio parameter,
which instructs RIPPER to achieve high accuracy for
the PROBLEMATIC class, while potentially reducing
overall accuracy. Finally, we plan to integrate the
learned rulesets into the HMIHY dialogue system to
improve the system&apos;s overall performance.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.999362" genericHeader="references">
References
</sectionHeader>
<reference confidence="0.999149261538461">
A. AbeIla and A.L. Gorin. 1999. Construct algebra:
An analytical method for dialog management. In
Proc. of the Association for Computational Lin-
guistics.
P. Baggia, G. Castagneri, and M. Danieli. 1998.
Field trials of the Italian Arise Train Timetable
System. In Interactive Voice Technology for
Telecommunications Applications, IVTTA, pages
97-102.
J. Chu-Carroll and R. Carpenter. 1999. Vector-
based natural language call routing. Computa-
tional Linguistics, 25-3:361-387.
W. Cohen. 1996. Learning trees and rules with set-
valued features. In 14th Conference of the Amer-
ican Association of Artificial Intelligence, AAAI.
A.L. Gorin E. Ammicht and T. Alonso. 1999.
Knowledge collection for natural language spoken
dialog systems. In Proc. of EUROSPEECH 99.
A.L. Gorin, G. Riccardi, and J.H. Wright. 1997.
How may I Help You? Speech Communication,
23:113-127.
I. Langkilde, M. Walker, J. Wright, A. Gorin, and
D. Litman. 1999. Automatic prediction of prob-
lematic human-computer dialogues in How May
I Help You? In Proc. IEEE Workshop on Auto-
matic Speech Recognition and Understanding.
G. A. Levow. 1998. Characterizing and recogniz-
ing spoken corrections in human-computer dia-
logue. In Proc. of the 36th Annual Meeting of the
Association of Computational Linguistics, COL-
ING/ACL 98, pages 736-742.
D. J. Litman, M. A. Walker, and M. J. Kearns. 1999.
Automatic detection of poor speech recognition at
the dialogue level. In Proc. of the 37th Annual
Meeting of the Association of Computational Lin-
guistics, A CL99, pages 309-316.
G. Riccardi and A.L. Gorin. to appear. Spoken lan-
guage adaptation over time and state in a natu-
ral spoken dialog system. IEEE Transactions on
Speech and Audio.
A. Sanderman, J. Sturm, E. den Os, L. Boves, and
A. Cremers. 1998. Evaluation of the Dutch Train
Timetable Information System developed in the
ARISE project. In Interactive Voice Technology
for Telecommunications Applications, pages 91-
96.
S. Seneff, V. Zue, J. Polifroni, C. Pao, L. Hethering-
ton, D. Goddeau, and J. Glass. 1995. The pre-
liminary development of a displayless PEGASUS
system. In ARPA SLT Workshop.
E. Shriberg, E. Wade, and P. Price. 1992. Human-
machine problem solving using spoken language
systems (SLS): Factors affecting performance and
user satisfaction. In Proc. of the DARPA Speech
and NL Workshop, pages 49-54.
M. A. Walker, J. C. Fromer, and S. Narayanan.
1998. Learning optimal dialogue strategies: A
case study of a spoken dialogue agent for email.
In Proc. of the 36th Annual Meeting of the
Association of Computational Linguistics, COL-
ING/ACL 98, pages 1345-1352.
M. Walker, I. Langkilde, and J. Wright. 2000. Us-
ing NLP and Discourse features to identify under-
standing errors in the How May I Help You spoken
dialogue system. In Submission.
</reference>
<page confidence="0.9984">
217
</page>
</variant>
</algorithm>
<algorithm name="ParsHed" version="110505">
<variant no="0" confidence="0.953624">
<title confidence="0.998196">Learning to Predict Problematic Situations in a Spoken Dialogue System: Experiments with How May I Help You?</title>
<author confidence="0.999666">Marilyn Walker</author>
<author confidence="0.999666">Irene Langkilde</author>
<author confidence="0.999666">Jerry Wright</author>
<author confidence="0.999666">Allen Gorin</author>
<author confidence="0.999666">Diane Litman</author>
<affiliation confidence="0.999967">AT&amp;T Labs—Research</affiliation>
<address confidence="0.9992375">180 Park Avenue Florham Park, NJ 07932-0971 USA</address>
<email confidence="0.999903">walker,jwright,algor,diane@research.att.corn,ilangkil@isi.edu</email>
<abstract confidence="0.997977952380952">Current spoken dialogue systems are deficient in their strategies for preventing, identifying and repairing problems that arise in the conversation. This paper reports results on learning to automatically identify and predict problematic human-computer dialogues in a corpus of 4774 dialogues collected with May I Help You dialogue system. Our expectation is that the ability to predict problematic dialogues will allow the system&apos;s dialogue manager to modify its behavior to repair problems, and even perhaps, to prevent them. We train a problematic dialogue classifier using automaticallyobtainable features that can identify problematic dialogues significantly better (23%) than the baseline. A classifier trained with only automatic features from the first exchange in the dialogue can predict problematic dialogues 7% more accurately than the baseline, and one trained with automatic features from the first two exchanges can perform 14% better than the baseline.</abstract>
</variant>
</algorithm>
<algorithm name="ParsCit" version="110505">
<citationList>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>A AbeIla</author>
<author>A L Gorin</author>
</authors>
<title>Construct algebra: An analytical method for dialog management.</title>
<date>1999</date>
<booktitle>In Proc. of the Association for Computational Linguistics.</booktitle>
<marker>AbeIla, Gorin, 1999</marker>
<rawString>A. AbeIla and A.L. Gorin. 1999. Construct algebra: An analytical method for dialog management. In Proc. of the Association for Computational Linguistics.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>P Baggia</author>
<author>G Castagneri</author>
<author>M Danieli</author>
</authors>
<title>Field trials of the Italian Arise Train Timetable System. In Interactive Voice Technology for Telecommunications Applications, IVTTA,</title>
<date>1998</date>
<pages>97--102</pages>
<contexts>
<context position="1798" citStr="Baggia et al., 1998" startWordPosition="259" endWordPosition="262"> the baseline, and one trained with automatic features from the first two exchanges can perform 14% better than the baseline. 1 Introduction Spoken dialogue systems promise efficient and natural access to a large variety of information sources and services from any phone. Systems that support short utterances to select a particular function (through a statement such as &amp;quot;Say credit card, collect or person-to-person&amp;quot;) are saving companies millions of dollars. Research prototypes exist for applications such as personal email and calendars, travel and restaurant information, and personal banking (Baggia et al., 1998; Walker et al., 1998; Seneff et al., 1995; Sanderman et al., 1998; Chu-Carroll and Carpenter, 1999) inter a/ia. Yet there are still many research challenges: current systems are limited in the interaction they support and brittle in many respects. We show how spoken dialogue systems can learn to support more natural interaction on the basis of their previous experience. One way that current spoken dialogue systems are quite limited is in their strategies for detecting and repairing problems that arise in conversation. If a problem can be detected, the system can either transfer the call to a </context>
</contexts>
<marker>Baggia, Castagneri, Danieli, 1998</marker>
<rawString>P. Baggia, G. Castagneri, and M. Danieli. 1998. Field trials of the Italian Arise Train Timetable System. In Interactive Voice Technology for Telecommunications Applications, IVTTA, pages 97-102.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>J Chu-Carroll</author>
<author>R Carpenter</author>
</authors>
<title>Vectorbased natural language call routing.</title>
<date>1999</date>
<journal>Computational Linguistics,</journal>
<pages>25--3</pages>
<contexts>
<context position="1898" citStr="Chu-Carroll and Carpenter, 1999" startWordPosition="275" endWordPosition="278"> perform 14% better than the baseline. 1 Introduction Spoken dialogue systems promise efficient and natural access to a large variety of information sources and services from any phone. Systems that support short utterances to select a particular function (through a statement such as &amp;quot;Say credit card, collect or person-to-person&amp;quot;) are saving companies millions of dollars. Research prototypes exist for applications such as personal email and calendars, travel and restaurant information, and personal banking (Baggia et al., 1998; Walker et al., 1998; Seneff et al., 1995; Sanderman et al., 1998; Chu-Carroll and Carpenter, 1999) inter a/ia. Yet there are still many research challenges: current systems are limited in the interaction they support and brittle in many respects. We show how spoken dialogue systems can learn to support more natural interaction on the basis of their previous experience. One way that current spoken dialogue systems are quite limited is in their strategies for detecting and repairing problems that arise in conversation. If a problem can be detected, the system can either transfer the call to a human operator or modify its dialogue strategy in an attempt to repair the problem. We can train sys</context>
<context position="5394" citStr="Chu-Carroll and Carpenter, 1999" startWordPosition="892" endWordPosition="895">res with an accuracy ranging from 72% to 87%, depending on how much of the dialogue the system has seen so far. Section 2 describes HMIHY and the dialogue corpus which the experiments are based on. Section 3 details the encoding of the dialogues and the methods used for utilizing the machine learning program RIPPER to train an automatic problematic dialogue predictor (Cohen, 1996). Section 4 presents the results and section 5 summarizes the paper and describes future work. 2 Experimental System and Data HMIHY is a spoken dialogue system based on the notion of call routing (Gorin et al., 1997; Chu-Carroll and Carpenter, 1999). In the HMIHY call routing system, services that the user can access are classified into 14 categories, plus a category called other for calls that cannot be automated and must be transferred to a human operator (Gorin et al., 1997).2 Each category describes a different task, such as person-to-person dialing, or receiving credit for a misdialed number. The system determines which task the caller is requesting on the basis of its understanding of the caller&apos;s response to the open-ended system greeting AT&amp;T, How May I Help You?. Once the task has been determined, the information needed for comp</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Chu-Carroll, Carpenter, 1999</marker>
<rawString>J. Chu-Carroll and R. Carpenter. 1999. Vectorbased natural language call routing. Computational Linguistics, 25-3:361-387.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>W Cohen</author>
</authors>
<title>Learning trees and rules with setvalued features.</title>
<date>1996</date>
<booktitle>In 14th Conference of the American Association of Artificial Intelligence,</booktitle>
<publisher>AAAI.</publisher>
<contexts>
<context position="5145" citStr="Cohen, 1996" startWordPosition="852" endWordPosition="853"> an automatic classifer for predicting problematic dialogues from features that can be automatically extracted from the HMIHY corpus. The results show that we can learn to predict problematic dialogues using fully automatic features with an accuracy ranging from 72% to 87%, depending on how much of the dialogue the system has seen so far. Section 2 describes HMIHY and the dialogue corpus which the experiments are based on. Section 3 details the encoding of the dialogues and the methods used for utilizing the machine learning program RIPPER to train an automatic problematic dialogue predictor (Cohen, 1996). Section 4 presents the results and section 5 summarizes the paper and describes future work. 2 Experimental System and Data HMIHY is a spoken dialogue system based on the notion of call routing (Gorin et al., 1997; Chu-Carroll and Carpenter, 1999). In the HMIHY call routing system, services that the user can access are classified into 14 categories, plus a category called other for calls that cannot be automated and must be transferred to a human operator (Gorin et al., 1997).2 Each category describes a different task, such as person-to-person dialing, or receiving credit for a misdialed num</context>
<context position="10151" citStr="Cohen, 1996" startWordPosition="1750" endWordPosition="1751">rth. S3: What phone number would you like the call billed to? U3: Urn the access number. S4: Sorry. Could I have that phone number again? U4: 1 8 hundred 2 2 5 5 2 8 8. 55: What number would you like to call? U5: 800 225 5288 (touchtone input) S6: Thank you. Figure 4: Sample TAsKFAILuRE Dialogue task that the caller was asking HMIHY to perform, on a per utterance basis. The logfiles also included labels indicating whether the wizard had taken over the call or the user had hung up. 3 Training an Automatic Problematic Dialogue Predictor Our experiments apply the machine learning program RIPPER (Cohen, 1996) to automatically induce a &amp;quot;problematic dialogue&amp;quot; classification model. RIPPER takes as input the names of a set of classes to be learned, the names and ranges of values of a fixed set of features, and training data specifying the class and feature values for each example in a training set. Its output is a classification model for predicting the class of future examples. In RIPPER, the classification model is learned using greedy search guided by an information gain metric, and is expressed as an ordered set of if-then rules. To apply RIPPER, the dialogues in the corpus must be encoded in term</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Cohen, 1996</marker>
<rawString>W. Cohen. 1996. Learning trees and rules with setvalued features. In 14th Conference of the American Association of Artificial Intelligence, AAAI.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>A L Gorin E Ammicht</author>
<author>T Alonso</author>
</authors>
<title>Knowledge collection for natural language spoken dialog systems.</title>
<date>1999</date>
<booktitle>In Proc. of EUROSPEECH 99.</booktitle>
<contexts>
<context position="3268" citStr="Ammicht and Alonso, 1999" startWordPosition="502" endWordPosition="505">e dialogues can be used to predict that a problem is likely to occur. We expect that the ability to predict that a dialogue is likely to be problematic will allow the system&apos;s dialogue manager to apply more sophisticated strategies to repairing problems, and even perhaps, to prevent them. This paper reports experiments on predicting problems in spoken dialogue interaction by training a problematic dialogue predictor on a corpus of 4774 dialogues collected in an experimental trial of AT&amp;T&apos;s How May I Help You (HMIHY) spoken dialogue system (Gorin et al., 1997; Riccardi and Gorin, to appear; E. Ammicht and Alonso, 1999). In this trial, the HMIHY system was installed at an AT&amp;T customer care center. HMIHY answered calls from live customer traffic and successfully automated a large number of customer requests. An example of a dialogue that HMIHY completed successfully is shown in Figure 1.1 SI: AT&amp;T How may I help you? UI: I need to [ uh ] put a call on my calling card please S2: May I have your card number, please? U2: 7 6 5 4 3 2 1 0 9 8 7 6 5 4 S3: What number would you like to call? U3: 8 1 4 7 7 7 6 6 6 6 (rnisrecognized) S4: May I have that number again? U4: 8 1 4 7 7 7 6 6 6 6 S5: Thank you. Figure 1: S</context>
<context position="8987" citStr="Ammicht and Alonso, 1999" startWordPosition="1534" endWordPosition="1537"> are cases where the system completed the call, but carried out a task that was not the task that the customer was actually requesting. An example TASKFAILURE dialogue is given in Figure 4: HMIHY interpreted utterance U2 as a request to make a third-party call e.g. to bill it to my home phone. HMIHY then asked the caller for the information it needed to carry out this task, the caller complied, and the system completed the call. The corpus of 4774 dialogues used in our experiments was collected in several experimental trials of HMIHY on live customer traffic (Riccardi and Gorin, to appear; E. Ammicht and Alonso, 1999), and is referred to as HM2 in (Riccardi and Gorin, to appear)). During the trial, all of the system behaviors were automatically recorded in a log file, and later the dialogues were transcribed by humans and labelled with a semantic category representing the 30f course we can only infer what might have motivated the wizard to take over the call, but we assume that the wizard had good reason for doing so. 211 Si: AT&amp;T How may I help you? Ul: (silence) S2: Sorry. Please briefly tell me how I may help you? U2: I wanta find out how much my bill&apos;s worth. S3: What phone number would you like the ca</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Ammicht, Alonso, 1999</marker>
<rawString>A.L. Gorin E. Ammicht and T. Alonso. 1999. Knowledge collection for natural language spoken dialog systems. In Proc. of EUROSPEECH 99.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>A L Gorin</author>
<author>G Riccardi</author>
<author>J H Wright</author>
</authors>
<title>How may I Help You? Speech Communication,</title>
<date>1997</date>
<pages>23--113</pages>
<contexts>
<context position="3207" citStr="Gorin et al., 1997" startWordPosition="492" endWordPosition="495">actions with human users. The initial segments of these dialogues can be used to predict that a problem is likely to occur. We expect that the ability to predict that a dialogue is likely to be problematic will allow the system&apos;s dialogue manager to apply more sophisticated strategies to repairing problems, and even perhaps, to prevent them. This paper reports experiments on predicting problems in spoken dialogue interaction by training a problematic dialogue predictor on a corpus of 4774 dialogues collected in an experimental trial of AT&amp;T&apos;s How May I Help You (HMIHY) spoken dialogue system (Gorin et al., 1997; Riccardi and Gorin, to appear; E. Ammicht and Alonso, 1999). In this trial, the HMIHY system was installed at an AT&amp;T customer care center. HMIHY answered calls from live customer traffic and successfully automated a large number of customer requests. An example of a dialogue that HMIHY completed successfully is shown in Figure 1.1 SI: AT&amp;T How may I help you? UI: I need to [ uh ] put a call on my calling card please S2: May I have your card number, please? U2: 7 6 5 4 3 2 1 0 9 8 7 6 5 4 S3: What number would you like to call? U3: 8 1 4 7 7 7 6 6 6 6 (rnisrecognized) S4: May I have that num</context>
<context position="5360" citStr="Gorin et al., 1997" startWordPosition="888" endWordPosition="891">ully automatic features with an accuracy ranging from 72% to 87%, depending on how much of the dialogue the system has seen so far. Section 2 describes HMIHY and the dialogue corpus which the experiments are based on. Section 3 details the encoding of the dialogues and the methods used for utilizing the machine learning program RIPPER to train an automatic problematic dialogue predictor (Cohen, 1996). Section 4 presents the results and section 5 summarizes the paper and describes future work. 2 Experimental System and Data HMIHY is a spoken dialogue system based on the notion of call routing (Gorin et al., 1997; Chu-Carroll and Carpenter, 1999). In the HMIHY call routing system, services that the user can access are classified into 14 categories, plus a category called other for calls that cannot be automated and must be transferred to a human operator (Gorin et al., 1997).2 Each category describes a different task, such as person-to-person dialing, or receiving credit for a misdialed number. The system determines which task the caller is requesting on the basis of its understanding of the caller&apos;s response to the open-ended system greeting AT&amp;T, How May I Help You?. Once the task has been determine</context>
<context position="14495" citStr="Gorin et al., 1997" startWordPosition="2438" endWordPosition="2441">t with a subset of features that are task-independent. We compare results for predicting problematic dia212 logues, with results for identifying problematic dialogues, when the classifier has access to features representing the whole dialogue. We utilized features logged by the system because they are produced automatically, and thus could be used during runtime to alter the course of the dialogue. The system modules that we collected information from were the acoustic processer/automatic speech recognizer (ASR) (Riccardi and Gorin, to appear), the natural language understanding (NLU) module (Gorin et al., 1997), and the dialogue manager (DM) (Abella and Gorin, 1999). Below we describe each module and the features obtained from it. ASR takes as input the acoustic signal and outputs a potentially errorful transcription of what it believes the caller said. The ASR features for each of the first four exchanges were the output of the speech recognizer (recog), the number of words in the recognizer output (recog-numwords), the duration in seconds of the input to the recognizer (asr-duration), a flag for touchtone input (dtmf-flag), the input modality expected by the recognizer (rg-modality) (one of: none,</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Gorin, Riccardi, Wright, 1997</marker>
<rawString>A.L. Gorin, G. Riccardi, and J.H. Wright. 1997. How may I Help You? Speech Communication, 23:113-127.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>I Langkilde</author>
<author>M Walker</author>
<author>J Wright</author>
<author>A Gorin</author>
<author>D Litman</author>
</authors>
<title>Automatic prediction of problematic human-computer dialogues in How May I Help You?</title>
<date>1999</date>
<booktitle>In Proc. IEEE Workshop on Automatic Speech Recognition and Understanding.</booktitle>
<contexts>
<context position="30764" citStr="Langkilde et al., 1999" startWordPosition="5032" endWordPosition="5035">ehaviors are used as predictors also indicates that, in all likelihood, the DM is performing as well as it can, given the noisy input that it is getting from ASR and NLU. To identify potential improvements in the problematic dialogue predictor, we analyzed which handlabelled features made large performance improvements, under the assumption that future work can focus on developing automatic features that approximate the information provided by these handlabelled features. The analysis indicated that the rsuccess feature alone improves the performance of the TOPLINE from 88.5%, as reported in (Langkilde et al., 1999), to 92.3%. Using rsuccess as the only feature results in 73.75% accuracy for exchange 1, 81.9% accuracy for exchanges 1&amp;2 and 85.3% accuracy for the full dialogue. In addition, for Exchanges 1&amp;2, the accuracy of the AUTOMATIC, TASK-INDEP feature set plus the rsuccess feature is 86.5%, which is only 0.2% less than the accuracy of ALL the features for Exchanges 1&amp;2 as shown in Table 1. The rules that RIPPER learns for Exchanges 1&amp;2 when the AUTOMATIC, TASK-INDEP feature set is augmented with the single hand-labelled rsuccess feature is shown below. Exchanges 18z2, Rsuccess + Automatic Task-Inde</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Langkilde, Walker, Wright, Gorin, Litman, 1999</marker>
<rawString>I. Langkilde, M. Walker, J. Wright, A. Gorin, and D. Litman. 1999. Automatic prediction of problematic human-computer dialogues in How May I Help You? In Proc. IEEE Workshop on Automatic Speech Recognition and Understanding.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>G A Levow</author>
</authors>
<title>Characterizing and recognizing spoken corrections in human-computer dialogue.</title>
<date>1998</date>
<booktitle>In Proc. of the 36th Annual Meeting of the Association of Computational Linguistics, COLING/ACL 98,</booktitle>
<pages>736--742</pages>
<contexts>
<context position="18659" citStr="Levow, 1998" startWordPosition="3111" endWordPosition="3112">he task-type label feature is to capture the fact that some tasks may be harder than others. The utterance id feature is motivated by the idea that the length of the dialogue may be important, possibly in combination with other features like task-type. The different prompt features for initial prompts, reprompts, confirmation prompts and subdialogue prompts are motivated by results indicating that reprompts and confirmation prompts are frustrating for callers and that callers are likely to hyperarticulate when they have to repeat themselves, which results in ASR errors (Shriberg et al., 1992; Levow, 1998). The DM features also include running tallies for the number of reprompts (num-reprompts), number of confirmation prompts (num-confirms), and number of subdialogue prompts (num-subdials), that had been played up to each point in the dialogue, as well as running percentages (percent-reprompts, percent. confirms, percent-subdials). The use of running tallies and percentages is based on the assumption that these features are likely to produce generalized predictors (Litman et al., 1999). The features obtained via hand-labelling were human transcripts of each user utterance (tscript), a set of se</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Levow, 1998</marker>
<rawString>G. A. Levow. 1998. Characterizing and recognizing spoken corrections in human-computer dialogue. In Proc. of the 36th Annual Meeting of the Association of Computational Linguistics, COLING/ACL 98, pages 736-742.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>D J Litman</author>
<author>M A Walker</author>
<author>M J Kearns</author>
</authors>
<title>Automatic detection of poor speech recognition at the dialogue level.</title>
<date>1999</date>
<booktitle>In Proc. of the 37th Annual Meeting of the Association of Computational Linguistics, A CL99,</booktitle>
<pages>309--316</pages>
<contexts>
<context position="19148" citStr="Litman et al., 1999" startWordPosition="3181" endWordPosition="3184">are likely to hyperarticulate when they have to repeat themselves, which results in ASR errors (Shriberg et al., 1992; Levow, 1998). The DM features also include running tallies for the number of reprompts (num-reprompts), number of confirmation prompts (num-confirms), and number of subdialogue prompts (num-subdials), that had been played up to each point in the dialogue, as well as running percentages (percent-reprompts, percent. confirms, percent-subdials). The use of running tallies and percentages is based on the assumption that these features are likely to produce generalized predictors (Litman et al., 1999). The features obtained via hand-labelling were human transcripts of each user utterance (tscript), a set of semantic labels that are closely related to the system task-type labels (human-label), age (age) and gender (gender) of the user, the actual modality of the user utterance (user-modality) (one of: nothing, speech, touchtone, speech+touchtone, non-speech), 213 and a cleaned transcript with non-word noise information removed (clean-tscript). From these features we calculated two derived features. The first was the number of words in the cleaned transcript (cltscript numwords), again on th</context>
<context position="33668" citStr="Litman et al., 1999" startWordPosition="5464" endWordPosition="5467">on in error rate relative to the automatic features. Even with current accuracy rates, the improved ability to predict problematic dialogues means that it may be possible to field the system without human agent oversight, and we expect to be able to improve these results. The research reported here is the first that we know of to automatically analyze a corpus of logs from a spoken dialogue system for the purpose of learning to predict problematic situations. Our work builds on earlier research on learning to identify dialogues in which the user experienced poor speech recognizer performance (Litman et al., 1999). However, that work was based on a much smaller set of experimental dialogues where the notion of a good or bad dialogue was automatically approximated rather than being labelled by humans. In addition, because that work was based on features synthesized over the entire dialogues, the hypotheses that were learned could not be used for prediction during runtime. We are exploring several ways to improve the performance of and test the problematic dialogue predictor. First, we noted above the extent to which the hand-labelled feature rsuccess improves classifier performance. In other work we rep</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Litman, Walker, Kearns, 1999</marker>
<rawString>D. J. Litman, M. A. Walker, and M. J. Kearns. 1999. Automatic detection of poor speech recognition at the dialogue level. In Proc. of the 37th Annual Meeting of the Association of Computational Linguistics, A CL99, pages 309-316.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="false">
<authors>
<author>G Riccardi</author>
<author>A L Gorin</author>
</authors>
<title>to appear. Spoken language adaptation over time and state in a natural spoken dialog system.</title>
<journal>IEEE Transactions on Speech and Audio.</journal>
<marker>Riccardi, Gorin, </marker>
<rawString>G. Riccardi and A.L. Gorin. to appear. Spoken language adaptation over time and state in a natural spoken dialog system. IEEE Transactions on Speech and Audio.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="false">
<authors>
<author>A Sanderman</author>
<author>J Sturm</author>
<author>E den Os</author>
<author>L Boves</author>
</authors>
<location>and</location>
<marker>Sanderman, Sturm, den Os, Boves, </marker>
<rawString>A. Sanderman, J. Sturm, E. den Os, L. Boves, and</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>A Cremers</author>
</authors>
<title>Evaluation of the Dutch Train Timetable Information System developed in the ARISE project.</title>
<date>1998</date>
<booktitle>In Interactive Voice Technology for Telecommunications Applications,</booktitle>
<pages>91--96</pages>
<marker>Cremers, 1998</marker>
<rawString>A. Cremers. 1998. Evaluation of the Dutch Train Timetable Information System developed in the ARISE project. In Interactive Voice Technology for Telecommunications Applications, pages 91-96.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>S Seneff</author>
<author>V Zue</author>
<author>J Polifroni</author>
<author>C Pao</author>
<author>L Hetherington</author>
<author>D Goddeau</author>
<author>J Glass</author>
</authors>
<title>The preliminary development of a displayless PEGASUS system.</title>
<date>1995</date>
<booktitle>In ARPA SLT Workshop.</booktitle>
<contexts>
<context position="1840" citStr="Seneff et al., 1995" startWordPosition="267" endWordPosition="270">tic features from the first two exchanges can perform 14% better than the baseline. 1 Introduction Spoken dialogue systems promise efficient and natural access to a large variety of information sources and services from any phone. Systems that support short utterances to select a particular function (through a statement such as &amp;quot;Say credit card, collect or person-to-person&amp;quot;) are saving companies millions of dollars. Research prototypes exist for applications such as personal email and calendars, travel and restaurant information, and personal banking (Baggia et al., 1998; Walker et al., 1998; Seneff et al., 1995; Sanderman et al., 1998; Chu-Carroll and Carpenter, 1999) inter a/ia. Yet there are still many research challenges: current systems are limited in the interaction they support and brittle in many respects. We show how spoken dialogue systems can learn to support more natural interaction on the basis of their previous experience. One way that current spoken dialogue systems are quite limited is in their strategies for detecting and repairing problems that arise in conversation. If a problem can be detected, the system can either transfer the call to a human operator or modify its dialogue stra</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Seneff, Zue, Polifroni, Pao, Hetherington, Goddeau, Glass, 1995</marker>
<rawString>S. Seneff, V. Zue, J. Polifroni, C. Pao, L. Hetherington, D. Goddeau, and J. Glass. 1995. The preliminary development of a displayless PEGASUS system. In ARPA SLT Workshop.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>E Shriberg</author>
<author>E Wade</author>
<author>P Price</author>
</authors>
<title>Humanmachine problem solving using spoken language systems (SLS): Factors affecting performance and user satisfaction.</title>
<date>1992</date>
<booktitle>In Proc. of the DARPA Speech and NL Workshop,</booktitle>
<pages>49--54</pages>
<contexts>
<context position="18645" citStr="Shriberg et al., 1992" startWordPosition="3107" endWordPosition="3110">ted by previous work. The task-type label feature is to capture the fact that some tasks may be harder than others. The utterance id feature is motivated by the idea that the length of the dialogue may be important, possibly in combination with other features like task-type. The different prompt features for initial prompts, reprompts, confirmation prompts and subdialogue prompts are motivated by results indicating that reprompts and confirmation prompts are frustrating for callers and that callers are likely to hyperarticulate when they have to repeat themselves, which results in ASR errors (Shriberg et al., 1992; Levow, 1998). The DM features also include running tallies for the number of reprompts (num-reprompts), number of confirmation prompts (num-confirms), and number of subdialogue prompts (num-subdials), that had been played up to each point in the dialogue, as well as running percentages (percent-reprompts, percent. confirms, percent-subdials). The use of running tallies and percentages is based on the assumption that these features are likely to produce generalized predictors (Litman et al., 1999). The features obtained via hand-labelling were human transcripts of each user utterance (tscript</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Shriberg, Wade, Price, 1992</marker>
<rawString>E. Shriberg, E. Wade, and P. Price. 1992. Humanmachine problem solving using spoken language systems (SLS): Factors affecting performance and user satisfaction. In Proc. of the DARPA Speech and NL Workshop, pages 49-54.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>M A Walker</author>
<author>J C Fromer</author>
<author>S Narayanan</author>
</authors>
<title>Learning optimal dialogue strategies: A case study of a spoken dialogue agent for email.</title>
<date>1998</date>
<booktitle>In Proc. of the 36th Annual Meeting of the Association of Computational Linguistics, COLING/ACL 98,</booktitle>
<pages>1345--1352</pages>
<contexts>
<context position="1819" citStr="Walker et al., 1998" startWordPosition="263" endWordPosition="266">e trained with automatic features from the first two exchanges can perform 14% better than the baseline. 1 Introduction Spoken dialogue systems promise efficient and natural access to a large variety of information sources and services from any phone. Systems that support short utterances to select a particular function (through a statement such as &amp;quot;Say credit card, collect or person-to-person&amp;quot;) are saving companies millions of dollars. Research prototypes exist for applications such as personal email and calendars, travel and restaurant information, and personal banking (Baggia et al., 1998; Walker et al., 1998; Seneff et al., 1995; Sanderman et al., 1998; Chu-Carroll and Carpenter, 1999) inter a/ia. Yet there are still many research challenges: current systems are limited in the interaction they support and brittle in many respects. We show how spoken dialogue systems can learn to support more natural interaction on the basis of their previous experience. One way that current spoken dialogue systems are quite limited is in their strategies for detecting and repairing problems that arise in conversation. If a problem can be detected, the system can either transfer the call to a human operator or mod</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Walker, Fromer, Narayanan, 1998</marker>
<rawString>M. A. Walker, J. C. Fromer, and S. Narayanan. 1998. Learning optimal dialogue strategies: A case study of a spoken dialogue agent for email. In Proc. of the 36th Annual Meeting of the Association of Computational Linguistics, COLING/ACL 98, pages 1345-1352.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>M Walker</author>
<author>I Langkilde</author>
<author>J Wright</author>
</authors>
<title>Using NLP and Discourse features to identify understanding errors in the How May I Help You spoken dialogue system.</title>
<date>2000</date>
<booktitle>In Submission.</booktitle>
<contexts>
<context position="34363" citStr="Walker et al., 2000" startWordPosition="5575" endWordPosition="5578">ues where the notion of a good or bad dialogue was automatically approximated rather than being labelled by humans. In addition, because that work was based on features synthesized over the entire dialogues, the hypotheses that were learned could not be used for prediction during runtime. We are exploring several ways to improve the performance of and test the problematic dialogue predictor. First, we noted above the extent to which the hand-labelled feature rsuccess improves classifier performance. In other work we report results from training an rsuccess classifier on a per-utterance level (Walker et al., 2000), where we show that we can achieve 85% accuracy using only fully automatic features. In future work we intend to use the (noisy) output from this classifier as input to our problematic dialogue classifier with the hope of improving the performance of the fully automatic feature sets. In addition, since it is more important to minimize errors in predicting PROBLEMATIC dialogues than errors in predicting TASKSUCCESS dialogues, we intend to experiment with RIPPER&apos;s loss ratio parameter, which instructs RIPPER to achieve high accuracy for the PROBLEMATIC class, while potentially reducing overall </context>
</contexts>
<marker>Walker, Langkilde, Wright, 2000</marker>
<rawString>M. Walker, I. Langkilde, and J. Wright. 2000. Using NLP and Discourse features to identify understanding errors in the How May I Help You spoken dialogue system. In Submission.</rawString>
</citation>
</citationList>
</algorithm>
</algorithms>