<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<algorithms version="110505">
<algorithm name="SectLabel" version="110505">
<variant no="0" confidence="0.000459">
<title confidence="0.9986245">
Introduction to the Special Issue on
Computational Anaphora Resolution
</title>
<author confidence="0.994127">
Ruslan Mitkov* Branimir Boguraevt
</author>
<affiliation confidence="0.987517">
University of Wolverhampton IBM T. J. Watson Research Center
</affiliation>
<author confidence="0.873117">
Shalom Lappint
</author>
<affiliation confidence="0.6784">
King&apos;s College, London
</affiliation>
<bodyText confidence="0.9925550625">
Anaphora accounts for cohesion in texts and is a phenomenon under active study
in formal and computational linguistics alike. The correct interpretation of anaphora
is vital for natural language processing (NLP). For example, anaphora resolution is
a key task in natural language interfaces, machine translation, text summarization,
information extraction, question answering, and a number of other NLP applications.
After considerable initial research, followed by years of relative silence in the early
1980s, anaphora resolution has attracted the attention of many researchers in the last 10
years and a great deal of successful work on the topic has been carried out. Discourse-
oriented theories and formalisms such as Discourse Representation Theory and Cen-
tering Theory inspired new research on the computational treatment of anaphora. The
drive toward corpus-based robust NLP solutions further stimulated interest in alterna-
tive and/or data-enriched approaches. Last, but not least, application-driven research
in areas such as automatic abstracting and information extraction independently high-
lighted the importance of anaphora and coreference resolution, boosting research in
this area.
Much of the earlier work in anaphora resolution heavily exploited domain and lin-
guistic knowledge (Sidner 1979; Carter 1987; Rich and LuperFoy 1988; Carbonell and
Brown 1988), which was difficult both to represent and to process, and which required
considerable human input. However, the pressing need for the development of robust
and inexpensive solutions to meet the demands of practical NLP systems encouraged
many researchers to move away from extensive domain and linguistic knowledge and
to embark instead upon knowledge-poor anaphora resolution strategies. A number of
proposals in the 1990s deliberately limited the extent to which they relied on domain
and/or linguistic knowledge and reported promising results in knowledge-poor oper-
ational environments (Dagan and Itai 1990, 1991; Lappin and Leass 1994; Nasukawa
1994; Kennedy and Boguraev 1996; Williams, Harvey, and Preston 1996; Baldwin 1997;
Mitkov 1996, 1998b).
The drive toward knowledge-poor and robust approaches was further motivated
by the emergence of cheaper and more reliable corpus-based NLP tools such as part-
of-speech taggers and shallow parsers, alongside the increasing availability of corpora
and other NLP resources (e.g., ontologies). In fact, the availability of corpora, both raw
and annotated with coreferential links, provided a strong impetus to anaphora resolu-
</bodyText>
<note confidence="0.909969">
* School of Humanities, Language and Social Sciences, Stafford Street, Wolverhampton WV1 1SB, UK.
</note>
<email confidence="0.990356">
E-mail: r.mitkov@w1v.ac.uk
</email>
<author confidence="0.527935">
t 30 Saw Mill River Road, Hawthorne, NY 10532, USA. E-mail: bkb@watson.ibm.com
</author>
<affiliation confidence="0.992784">
Department of Computer Science, King&apos;s College, The Strand, London WC2R 2LS, UK.
</affiliation>
<email confidence="0.998859">
E-mail: lappin@dcs.kcl.ac.uk
</email>
<note confidence="0.9849415">
C) 2001 Association for Computational Linguistics
Computational Linguistics Volume 27, Number 4
</note>
<bodyText confidence="0.99903262745098">
tion with regard to both training and evaluation. Corpora (especially when annotated)
are an invaluable source not only for empirical research but also for automated learning
(e.g., machine learning) methods aiming to develop new rules and approaches; they
also provide an important resource for evaluation of the implemented approaches.
From simple co-occurrence rules (Dagan and Itai 1990) through training decision trees
to identify anaphor-antecedent pairs (Aone and Bennett 1995) to genetic algorithms to
optimize the resolution factors (Ordsan, Evans, and Mitkov 2000), the successful per-
formance of more and more modern approaches was made possible by the availability
of suitable corpora.
While the shift toward knowledge-poor strategies and the use of corpora repre-
sented the main trends of anaphora resolution in the 1990s, there are other signifi-
cant highlights in recent anaphora resolution research. The inclusion of the corefer-
ence task in the Sixth and Seventh Message Understanding Conferences (MUC-6 and
MUC-7) gave a considerable impetus to the development of coreference resolution
algorithms and systems, such as those described in Baldwin et al. (1995), Gaizauskas
and Humphreys (1996), and Kameyama (1997). The last decade of the 20th century
saw a number of anaphora resolution projects for languages other than English such as
French, German, Japanese, Spanish, Portuguese, and Turkish. Against the background
of a growing interest in multilingual NLP, multilingual anaphora /coreference reso-
lution has gained considerable momentum in recent years (Aone and McKee 1993;
Azzam, Humphreys, and Gaizauskas 1998; Harabagiu and Maiorano 2000; Mitkov
and Barbu 2000; Mitkov 1999; Mitkov and Stys 1997; Mitkov, Belguith, and Stys 1998).
Other milestones of recent research include the deployment of probabilistic and ma-
chine learning techniques (Aone and Bennett 1995; Kehler 1997; Ge, Hale, and Char-
niak 1998; Cardie and Wagstaff 1999; the continuing interest in centering, used either
in original or in revised form (Abracos and Lopes 1994; Strube and Hahn 1996; Hahn
and Strube 1997; Tetreault 1999); and proposals related to the evaluation methodology
in anaphora resolution (Mitkov 1998a, 2001b). For a more detailed survey of the state
of the art in anaphora resolution, see Mitkov (forthcoming).
The papers published in this issue reflect the major trends in anaphora resolution
in recent years. Some of them describe approaches that do not exploit full syntactic
knowledge (as in the case of Palomar et al.&apos;s and Stuckardt&apos;s work) or that employ
machine learning techniques (Soon, Ng, and Lim); others present centering-based pro-
noun resolution (Tetreault) or discuss theoretical centering issues (Kibble). Almost all
of the papers feature extensive evaluation (including comparative evaluation as in
the case of Tetreault&apos;s and Palomar et al.&apos;s work) or discuss general evaluation issues
(Byron as well as Stuckardt).
Palomar et al.&apos;s paper describes an approach that works from the output of a
partial parser and handles third person personal, demonstrative, reflexive, and zero
pronouns, featuring among other things syntactic conditions on Spanish NP-pronoun
noncoreference and an enhanced set of resolution preferences. The authors also im-
plement several known methods and compare their performance with that of their
own algorithm. An indirect conclusion from this work is that an algorithm requires
semantic knowledge in order to hope for a success rate higher than 75%.
Soon, Ng, and Lim describe a C5-based learning approach to coreference resolu-
tion of noun phrases in unrestricted text. The approach learns from a small, annotated
corpus and tackles pronouns, proper names, and definite descriptions. The coreference
resolution module is part of a larger coreference resolution system that also includes
sentence segmentation, tokenization, morphological analysis, part-of-speech tagging,
noun phrase identification, named entity recognition, and semantic class determina-
tion (via WordNet). The evaluation is carried out on the MUC-6 and MUC-7 test
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.934466">
474
</page>
<note confidence="0.488508">
Mitkov, Boguraev, and Lappin Anaphora Resolution: Introduction
</note>
<bodyText confidence="0.999147488888889">
corpora. The paper reports on experiments aimed at quantifying the contribution of
each resolution factor and features error analysis.
Stuckardt&apos;s work presents an anaphor resolution algorithm for systems where only
partial syntactic information is available. Stuckardt applies Government and Bind-
ing Theory principles A, B, and C to the task of coreference resolution on partially
parsed texts. He also argues that evaluation of anaphora resolution systems should
take into account several factors beyond simple accuracy of resolution. In particular,
both developer-oriented (e.g., related to the selection of optimal resolution factors)
and application-oriented (e.g., related to the requirement of the application, as in the
case of information extraction, where a proper name antecedent is needed) evaluation
metrics should be considered.
Tetreault&apos;s contribution features comparative evaluation involving the author&apos;s
own centering-based pronoun resolution algorithm called the Left-Right Centering
algorithm (LRC) as well as three other pronoun resolution methods: Hobbs&apos;s naive
algorithm (Hobbs 1978), BFP (Brennan, Friedman, and Pollard 1987), and Strube&apos;s 5-
list approach (Strube 1998). The LRC is an alternative to the original BFP algorithm in
that it processes utterances incrementally. It works by first searching for an antecedent
in the current sentence; if none can be found, it continues the search on the Cf-list of
the previous and the other preceding utterances in a left-to-right fashion.
In her squib, Byron maintains that additional kinds of information should be
included in an evaluation in order to make the performance of algorithms on pronoun
resolution more transparent. In particular, she suggests that the pronoun coverage be
explicitly reported and proposes that the evaluation details be presented in a concise
and compact tabular format called standard disclosure. Byron also proposes a measure,
the resolution rate, which is computed as the number of pronouns resolved correctly
divided by the number of (only) referential pronouns.
Finally, in his squib Kibble discusses a reformulation of the centering transitions
(Continue, Retain, and Shift), which specify the center movement across sentences.
Instead of defining a total preference ordering, Kibble argues that a partial ordering
emerges from the interaction among cohesion (maintaining the same center), salience
(realizing the center as subject), and cheapness (realizing the anticipated center of a
following utterance as subject).
The last years have seen considerable advances in the field of anaphora resolution,
but a number of outstanding issues either remain unsolved or need more attention
and, as a consequence, represent major challenges to the further development of the
field (Mitkov 2001a). A fundamental question that needs further investigation is how
far the performance of anaphora resolution algorithms can go and what the limitations
of knowledge-poor methods are. In particular, more research should be carried out on
the factors influencing the performance of these algorithms. One of the impediments
to the evaluation or fuller utilization of machine learning techniques is the lack of
widely available corpora annotated for anaphoric or coreferential links. More work
toward the proposal of consistent and comprehensive evaluation is necessary; so too
is work in multilingual contexts. Some of these challenges have been addressed in the
papers published in this issue, but ongoing research will continue to address them in
the near future.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.755287" genericHeader="abstract">
References
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.99207975">
Abracos, Jose and José Lopes. 1994.
Extending DRT with a focusing
mechanism for pronominal anaphora and
ellipsis resolution. In Proceedings of the 15th
</bodyText>
<subsubsectionHeader confidence="0.540717">
International Conference on Computational
</subsubsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9983325">
Linguistics (COLING&apos;94), pages 1128-1132,
Kyoto, Japan.
Aone, Chinatsu and Scott Bennett. 1995.
Evaluating automated and manual
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.994362">
475
</page>
<note confidence="0.581225">
Computational Linguistics Volume 27, Number 4
</note>
<bodyText confidence="0.9683081">
acquisition of anaphora resolution
strategies. In Proceedings of the 33rd Annual
Meeting of the Association for Computational
Linguistics (ACL&apos;95), pages 122-129, Las
Cruces, NM.
Aone, Chinatsu and Douglas McKee. 1993.
A language-independent anaphora
resolution system for understanding
multilingual texts. In Proceedings of the 31st
Annual Meeting of the Association for
</bodyText>
<reference confidence="0.51828734375">
Computational Linguistics (ACL&apos;93),
pages 156-163, Columbus, OH.
Azzam, Saliha, Kevin Humphreys, and
Robert Gaizauskas. 1998. Coreference
resolution in a multilingual information
extraction. In Proceedings of a Workshop on
Linguistic Coreference, Granada, Spain.
Baldwin, Breck. 1997. CogNIAC: High
precision coreference with limited
knowledge and linguistic resources. In
Proceedings of the ACL&apos;97/EACL&apos;97
Workshop on Operational Factors in Practical,
Robust Anaphora Resolution for Unrestricted
Texts, pages 38-45, Madrid, Spain.
Baldwin, Breck, Jeff Reynar, Mike Collins,
Jason Eisner, Adwait Ratnaparki, Joseph
Rosenzweig, Anoop Sarkar, and Srivinas
Bangalore. 1995. Description of the
University of Pennsylvania system used
for MUC-6. In Proceedings of the Sixth
Message Understanding Conference
(MUC-6), pages 177-191, Columbia, MD.
Brennan, Susan, Marilyn Friedman, and
Carl Pollard. 1987. A centering approach
to pronouns. In Proceedings of the 25th
Annual Meeting of the Association for
Computational Linguistics (ACL&apos;87),
pages 155-162, Stanford, CA.
Carbonell, Jaime and Ralf Brown. 1988.
Anaphora resolution: A multi-strategy
approach. In Proceedings of the 12th
International Conference on Computational
</reference>
<bodyText confidence="0.945983230769231">
Linguistics (COLING&apos;88), volume 1,
pages 96-101, Budapest,
Hungary.
Cardie, Claire and Kin Wagstaff. 1999.
Noun phrase coreference as clustering. In
Proceedings of the 1999 Joint SIGDAT
Conference on Empirical Methods in Natural
Language Processing and Very Large Corpora,
pages 82-89, College Park, MD.
Carter, David M. 1987. Interpreting Anaphors
in Natural Language Texts. Ellis Horwood,
Chichester, UK.
Dagan, Ido and Alon Itai. 1990. Automatic
processing of large corpora for the
resolution of anaphora references. In
Proceedings of the 13th International
Conference on Computational Linguistics
(COLING&apos;90), volume 3, pages 1-3,
Helsinki, Finland.
Dagan, Ido and Alon Itai. 1991. A statistical
filter for resolving pronoun references. In
Yishai A. Feldman and Alfred Bruckstein,
editors, Artificial Intelligence and Computer
Vision. Elsevier Science Publishers B.V.
(North-Holland), Amsterdam, pages
125-135.
</bodyText>
<figureCaption confidence="0.80488375">
Gaizauskas, Robert and Kevin Humphreys.
1996. Quantitative evaluation of
coreference algorithms in an information
extraction system. Presented at Discourse
Anaphora and Anaphor Resolution
Colloquium (DAARC-1), Lancaster, UK.
Reprinted in Simon Botley and Tony
McEnery, editors, Corpus-Based and
</figureCaption>
<reference confidence="0.973804904761905">
Computational Approaches to Discourse
Anaphora. John Benjamins, Amsterdam,
2000, pages 143-167.
Ge, Niyu, John Hale, and Eugene Charniak.
1998. A statistical approach to anaphora
resolution. In Proceedings of the Sixth
Workshop on Very Large Corpora,
pages 161-170, Montreal, Canada.
Hahn, Udo and Michael Strube. 1997.
Centering-in-the-large: Computing
referential discourse segments. In
Proceedings of the 35th Annual Meeting of the
Association for Computational Linguistics
(ACL&apos;97/EACL&apos;97), pages 104-111,
Madrid, Spain.
Harabagiu, Sanda and Steven Maiorano.
2000. Multilingual coreference resolution.
In Proceedings of Conference on Applied
Natural Language Processing/North American
Chapter of the Association for Computational
Linguistics (ANLP-NAACL2000), pages
142-149, Seattle, WA.
Hobbs, Jerry. 1978. Resolving pronoun
references. Lingua, 44:311-338.
Kameyama, Megumi. 1997. Recognizing
referential links: An information
extraction perspective. In Proceedings of the
ACL&apos;97/EACL&apos;97 Workshop on Operational
Factors in Practical, Robust Anaphora
Resolution for Unrestricted Texts,
pages 46-53, Madrid, Spain.
Kehler, Andrew. 1997. Probabilistic
coreference in information extraction. In
Proceedings of the 2nd Conference on
Empirical Methods in Natural Language
Processing (EMNLP-2), pages 163-173,
Providence, RI.
Kennedy, Christopher and Branimir
Boguraev. 1996. Anaphora for everyone:
Pronominal anaphora resolution without
a parser. In Proceedings of the 16th
International Conference on Computational
</reference>
<bodyText confidence="0.51940125">
Linguistics (COLING&apos;96), pages 113-118,
Copenhagen, Denmark.
Lappin, Shalom and Herbert Leass. 1994.
An algorithm for pronominal anaphora
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.998433">
476
</page>
<note confidence="0.908275">
Mitkov, Boguraev, and Lappin Anaphora Resolution: Introduction
</note>
<reference confidence="0.997729355769231">
resolution. Computational Linguistics,
20(4):535-561.
Mitkov, Ruslan. 1996. Pronoun resolution:
The practical alternative. Presented at the
Discourse Anaphora and Anaphor
Resolution Colloquium (DAARC-1),
Lancaster, UK. Reprinted in Simon Botley
and Tony McEnery, editors, Corpus-Based
and Computational Approaches to Discourse
Anaphora. John Benjamins, Amsterdam,
2000,189-212.
Mitkov, Ruslan. 1998a. Evaluating anaphora
resolution approaches. In Proceedings of the
Discourse Anaphora and Anaphora Resolution
Colloquium (DAARC-2), Lancaster, UK.
Mitkov, Ruslan. 1998b. Robust pronoun
resolution with limited knowledge. In
Proceedings of the 36th Annual Meeting of the
Association for Computational Linguistics and
the 17th International Conference on
Computational Linguistics
(COLING&apos;98/ACL&apos;98), pages 869-875,
Montreal, Canada.
Mitkov, Ruslan. 1999. Multilingual anaphora
resolution. Machine Translation,
14(3-4):281-299.
Mitkov, Ruslan. 2001a. Outstanding issues
in anaphora resolution. In Alexander
Gelbukh, editor, Computational Linguistics
and Intelligent Text Processing. Springer,
Berlin, pages 110-125.
Mitkov, Ruslan. 2001b. Towards a more
consistent and comprehensive evaluation
of anaphora resolution algorithms and
systems. Applied Artificial Intelligence: An
International Journal, 15:253-276.
Mitkov, Ruslan. Forthcoming. Anaphora
Resolution. Longman, Harlow, UK.
Mitkov, Ruslan, Lamia Belguith, and
Malgorzata Stys. 1998. Multilingual robust
anaphora resolution. In Proceedings of the
Third International Conference on Empirical
Methods in Natural Language Processing
(EMNLP-3), pages 7-16, Granada, Spain.
Mitkov, Ruslan and Malgorzata Stys. 1997.
Robust reference resolution with limited
knowledge: High precision genre-specific
approach for English and Polish. In
Proceedings of the International Conference on
Recent Advances in Natural Language
Processing (RANLP&apos;97), pages 74-81,
Tzigov Chark, Bulgaria.
Mitkov, Ruslan and Catalina Barbu. 2000.
Improving pronoun resolution in two
languages by means of bilingual corpora.
In Proceedings of the Discourse, Anaphora and
Reference Resolution Conference (DAARC
2000), pages 133-137, Lancaster, UK.
Nasukawa, Tetsuya. 1994. Robust method of
pronoun resolution using full-text
information. In Proceedings of the 15th
International Conference on Computational
Linguistics (COLING&apos;94), pages 1157-1163,
Kyoto, Japan.
Orasan, Constantin, Richard Evans, and
Ruslan Mitkov. 2000. Enhancing
preference-based anaphora resolution
with genetic algorithms. In Proceedings of
NLP-2000, pages 185-195, Patras, Greece.
Rich, Elaine and Susann LuperFoy. 1988. An
architecture for anaphora resolution. In
Proceedings of the Second Conference on
Applied Natural Language Processing
(ANLP-2), pages 18-24, Austin, TX.
Sidner, Candace. 1979. Toward a
computational theory of definite anaphora
comprehension in English. Technical
Report AI-TR-537, MIT, Cambridge, MA.
Strube, Michael. 1998. Never look back: An
alternative to centering. In Proceedings of
the 36th Annual Meeting of the Association for
Computational Linguistics and the 17th
International Conference on Computational
Linguistics (COLING&apos;98/ACL&apos;98),
pages 1251-1257, Montreal, Canada.
Strube, Michael and Udo Hahn. 1996.
Functional centering. In Proceedings of the
34th Annual Meeting of the Association for
Computational Linguistics (ACL&apos;96),
pages 270-277, Santa Cruz, CA.
Tetreault, Joel. 1999. Analysis of
syntax-based pronoun resolution
methods. In Proceedings of the 37th Annual
Meeting of the Association for Computational
Linguistics (ACL&apos;99), pages 602-605,
College Park, MD.
Williams, Sandra, Mark Harvey, and Keith
Preston. 1996. Rule-based reference
resolution for unrestricted text using
part-of-speech tagging and noun phrase
parsing. In Proceedings of the Discourse
Anaphora and Anaphora Resolution
Colloquium (DAARC-1), pages 441-456,
Lancaster, UK.
</reference>
<page confidence="0.998421">
477
</page>
</variant>
</algorithm>

<algorithm name="ParsCit" version="110505">
<citationList>
<citation valid="false">
<booktitle>Computational Linguistics (ACL&apos;93),</booktitle>
<pages>156--163</pages>
<location>Columbus, OH.</location>
<marker></marker>
<rawString>Computational Linguistics (ACL&apos;93), pages 156-163, Columbus, OH.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Saliha Azzam</author>
<author>Kevin Humphreys</author>
<author>Robert Gaizauskas</author>
</authors>
<title>Coreference resolution in a multilingual information extraction.</title>
<date>1998</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of a Workshop on Linguistic Coreference,</booktitle>
<location>Granada,</location>
<marker>Azzam, Humphreys, Gaizauskas, 1998</marker>
<rawString>Azzam, Saliha, Kevin Humphreys, and Robert Gaizauskas. 1998. Coreference resolution in a multilingual information extraction. In Proceedings of a Workshop on Linguistic Coreference, Granada, Spain.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Breck Baldwin</author>
</authors>
<title>CogNIAC: High precision coreference with limited knowledge and linguistic resources.</title>
<date>1997</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the ACL&apos;97/EACL&apos;97 Workshop on Operational Factors in Practical, Robust Anaphora Resolution for Unrestricted Texts,</booktitle>
<pages>38--45</pages>
<location>Madrid,</location>
<contexts>
<context position="2306" citStr="Baldwin 1997" startWordPosition="328" endWordPosition="329">ng need for the development of robust and inexpensive solutions to meet the demands of practical NLP systems encouraged many researchers to move away from extensive domain and linguistic knowledge and to embark instead upon knowledge-poor anaphora resolution strategies. A number of proposals in the 1990s deliberately limited the extent to which they relied on domain and/or linguistic knowledge and reported promising results in knowledge-poor operational environments (Dagan and Itai 1990, 1991; Lappin and Leass 1994; Nasukawa 1994; Kennedy and Boguraev 1996; Williams, Harvey, and Preston 1996; Baldwin 1997; Mitkov 1996, 1998b). The drive toward knowledge-poor and robust approaches was further motivated by the emergence of cheaper and more reliable corpus-based NLP tools such as partof-speech taggers and shallow parsers, alongside the increasing availability of corpora and other NLP resources (e.g., ontologies). In fact, the availability of corpora, both raw and annotated with coreferential links, provided a strong impetus to anaphora resolu* School of Humanities, Language and Social Sciences, Stafford Street, Wolverhampton WV1 1SB, UK. E-mail: r.mitkov@w1v.ac.uk t 30 Saw Mill River Road, Hawtho</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Baldwin, 1997</marker>
<rawString>Baldwin, Breck. 1997. CogNIAC: High precision coreference with limited knowledge and linguistic resources. In Proceedings of the ACL&apos;97/EACL&apos;97 Workshop on Operational Factors in Practical, Robust Anaphora Resolution for Unrestricted Texts, pages 38-45, Madrid, Spain.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Breck Baldwin</author>
<author>Jeff Reynar</author>
<author>Mike Collins</author>
<author>Jason Eisner</author>
<author>Adwait Ratnaparki</author>
<author>Joseph Rosenzweig</author>
<author>Anoop Sarkar</author>
<author>Srivinas Bangalore</author>
</authors>
<title>Description of the University of Pennsylvania system used for MUC-6.</title>
<date>1995</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the Sixth Message Understanding Conference (MUC-6),</booktitle>
<pages>177--191</pages>
<location>Columbia, MD.</location>
<contexts>
<context position="4332" citStr="Baldwin et al. (1995)" startWordPosition="618" endWordPosition="621">vans, and Mitkov 2000), the successful performance of more and more modern approaches was made possible by the availability of suitable corpora. While the shift toward knowledge-poor strategies and the use of corpora represented the main trends of anaphora resolution in the 1990s, there are other significant highlights in recent anaphora resolution research. The inclusion of the coreference task in the Sixth and Seventh Message Understanding Conferences (MUC-6 and MUC-7) gave a considerable impetus to the development of coreference resolution algorithms and systems, such as those described in Baldwin et al. (1995), Gaizauskas and Humphreys (1996), and Kameyama (1997). The last decade of the 20th century saw a number of anaphora resolution projects for languages other than English such as French, German, Japanese, Spanish, Portuguese, and Turkish. Against the background of a growing interest in multilingual NLP, multilingual anaphora /coreference resolution has gained considerable momentum in recent years (Aone and McKee 1993; Azzam, Humphreys, and Gaizauskas 1998; Harabagiu and Maiorano 2000; Mitkov and Barbu 2000; Mitkov 1999; Mitkov and Stys 1997; Mitkov, Belguith, and Stys 1998). Other milestones of</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Baldwin, Reynar, Collins, Eisner, Ratnaparki, Rosenzweig, Sarkar, Bangalore, 1995</marker>
<rawString>Baldwin, Breck, Jeff Reynar, Mike Collins, Jason Eisner, Adwait Ratnaparki, Joseph Rosenzweig, Anoop Sarkar, and Srivinas Bangalore. 1995. Description of the University of Pennsylvania system used for MUC-6. In Proceedings of the Sixth Message Understanding Conference (MUC-6), pages 177-191, Columbia, MD.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Susan Brennan</author>
<author>Marilyn Friedman</author>
<author>Carl Pollard</author>
</authors>
<title>A centering approach to pronouns.</title>
<date>1987</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the 25th Annual Meeting of the Association for Computational Linguistics (ACL&apos;87),</booktitle>
<pages>155--162</pages>
<location>Stanford, CA.</location>
<marker>Brennan, Friedman, Pollard, 1987</marker>
<rawString>Brennan, Susan, Marilyn Friedman, and Carl Pollard. 1987. A centering approach to pronouns. In Proceedings of the 25th Annual Meeting of the Association for Computational Linguistics (ACL&apos;87), pages 155-162, Stanford, CA.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Jaime Carbonell</author>
<author>Ralf Brown</author>
</authors>
<title>Anaphora resolution: A multi-strategy approach.</title>
<date>1988</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the 12th International Conference on Computational Computational Approaches to Discourse Anaphora. John Benjamins,</booktitle>
<pages>143--167</pages>
<location>Amsterdam,</location>
<contexts>
<context position="1574" citStr="Carbonell and Brown 1988" startWordPosition="219" endWordPosition="222">n Theory and Centering Theory inspired new research on the computational treatment of anaphora. The drive toward corpus-based robust NLP solutions further stimulated interest in alternative and/or data-enriched approaches. Last, but not least, application-driven research in areas such as automatic abstracting and information extraction independently highlighted the importance of anaphora and coreference resolution, boosting research in this area. Much of the earlier work in anaphora resolution heavily exploited domain and linguistic knowledge (Sidner 1979; Carter 1987; Rich and LuperFoy 1988; Carbonell and Brown 1988), which was difficult both to represent and to process, and which required considerable human input. However, the pressing need for the development of robust and inexpensive solutions to meet the demands of practical NLP systems encouraged many researchers to move away from extensive domain and linguistic knowledge and to embark instead upon knowledge-poor anaphora resolution strategies. A number of proposals in the 1990s deliberately limited the extent to which they relied on domain and/or linguistic knowledge and reported promising results in knowledge-poor operational environments (Dagan an</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Carbonell, Brown, 1988</marker>
<rawString>Carbonell, Jaime and Ralf Brown. 1988. Anaphora resolution: A multi-strategy approach. In Proceedings of the 12th International Conference on Computational Computational Approaches to Discourse Anaphora. John Benjamins, Amsterdam, 2000, pages 143-167.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Niyu Ge</author>
<author>John Hale</author>
<author>Eugene Charniak</author>
</authors>
<title>A statistical approach to anaphora resolution.</title>
<date>1998</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the Sixth Workshop on Very Large Corpora,</booktitle>
<pages>161--170</pages>
<location>Montreal, Canada.</location>
<marker>Ge, Hale, Charniak, 1998</marker>
<rawString>Ge, Niyu, John Hale, and Eugene Charniak. 1998. A statistical approach to anaphora resolution. In Proceedings of the Sixth Workshop on Very Large Corpora, pages 161-170, Montreal, Canada.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Udo Hahn</author>
<author>Michael Strube</author>
</authors>
<title>Centering-in-the-large: Computing referential discourse segments.</title>
<date>1997</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the 35th Annual Meeting of the Association for Computational Linguistics (ACL&apos;97/EACL&apos;97),</booktitle>
<pages>104--111</pages>
<location>Madrid,</location>
<contexts>
<context position="5261" citStr="Hahn and Strube 1997" startWordPosition="759" endWordPosition="762">lingual anaphora /coreference resolution has gained considerable momentum in recent years (Aone and McKee 1993; Azzam, Humphreys, and Gaizauskas 1998; Harabagiu and Maiorano 2000; Mitkov and Barbu 2000; Mitkov 1999; Mitkov and Stys 1997; Mitkov, Belguith, and Stys 1998). Other milestones of recent research include the deployment of probabilistic and machine learning techniques (Aone and Bennett 1995; Kehler 1997; Ge, Hale, and Charniak 1998; Cardie and Wagstaff 1999; the continuing interest in centering, used either in original or in revised form (Abracos and Lopes 1994; Strube and Hahn 1996; Hahn and Strube 1997; Tetreault 1999); and proposals related to the evaluation methodology in anaphora resolution (Mitkov 1998a, 2001b). For a more detailed survey of the state of the art in anaphora resolution, see Mitkov (forthcoming). The papers published in this issue reflect the major trends in anaphora resolution in recent years. Some of them describe approaches that do not exploit full syntactic knowledge (as in the case of Palomar et al.&apos;s and Stuckardt&apos;s work) or that employ machine learning techniques (Soon, Ng, and Lim); others present centering-based pronoun resolution (Tetreault) or discuss theoretic</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Hahn, Strube, 1997</marker>
<rawString>Hahn, Udo and Michael Strube. 1997. Centering-in-the-large: Computing referential discourse segments. In Proceedings of the 35th Annual Meeting of the Association for Computational Linguistics (ACL&apos;97/EACL&apos;97), pages 104-111, Madrid, Spain.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Sanda Harabagiu</author>
<author>Steven Maiorano</author>
</authors>
<title>Multilingual coreference resolution.</title>
<date>2000</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of Conference on Applied Natural Language Processing/North American Chapter of the Association for Computational Linguistics (ANLP-NAACL2000),</booktitle>
<pages>142--149</pages>
<location>Seattle, WA.</location>
<contexts>
<context position="4819" citStr="Harabagiu and Maiorano 2000" startWordPosition="688" endWordPosition="691">a considerable impetus to the development of coreference resolution algorithms and systems, such as those described in Baldwin et al. (1995), Gaizauskas and Humphreys (1996), and Kameyama (1997). The last decade of the 20th century saw a number of anaphora resolution projects for languages other than English such as French, German, Japanese, Spanish, Portuguese, and Turkish. Against the background of a growing interest in multilingual NLP, multilingual anaphora /coreference resolution has gained considerable momentum in recent years (Aone and McKee 1993; Azzam, Humphreys, and Gaizauskas 1998; Harabagiu and Maiorano 2000; Mitkov and Barbu 2000; Mitkov 1999; Mitkov and Stys 1997; Mitkov, Belguith, and Stys 1998). Other milestones of recent research include the deployment of probabilistic and machine learning techniques (Aone and Bennett 1995; Kehler 1997; Ge, Hale, and Charniak 1998; Cardie and Wagstaff 1999; the continuing interest in centering, used either in original or in revised form (Abracos and Lopes 1994; Strube and Hahn 1996; Hahn and Strube 1997; Tetreault 1999); and proposals related to the evaluation methodology in anaphora resolution (Mitkov 1998a, 2001b). For a more detailed survey of the state o</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Harabagiu, Maiorano, 2000</marker>
<rawString>Harabagiu, Sanda and Steven Maiorano. 2000. Multilingual coreference resolution. In Proceedings of Conference on Applied Natural Language Processing/North American Chapter of the Association for Computational Linguistics (ANLP-NAACL2000), pages 142-149, Seattle, WA.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Jerry Hobbs</author>
</authors>
<title>Resolving pronoun references.</title>
<date>1978</date>
<journal>Lingua,</journal>
<pages>44--311</pages>
<contexts>
<context position="8418" citStr="Hobbs 1978" startWordPosition="1212" endWordPosition="1213">rs beyond simple accuracy of resolution. In particular, both developer-oriented (e.g., related to the selection of optimal resolution factors) and application-oriented (e.g., related to the requirement of the application, as in the case of information extraction, where a proper name antecedent is needed) evaluation metrics should be considered. Tetreault&apos;s contribution features comparative evaluation involving the author&apos;s own centering-based pronoun resolution algorithm called the Left-Right Centering algorithm (LRC) as well as three other pronoun resolution methods: Hobbs&apos;s naive algorithm (Hobbs 1978), BFP (Brennan, Friedman, and Pollard 1987), and Strube&apos;s 5- list approach (Strube 1998). The LRC is an alternative to the original BFP algorithm in that it processes utterances incrementally. It works by first searching for an antecedent in the current sentence; if none can be found, it continues the search on the Cf-list of the previous and the other preceding utterances in a left-to-right fashion. In her squib, Byron maintains that additional kinds of information should be included in an evaluation in order to make the performance of algorithms on pronoun resolution more transparent. In par</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Hobbs, 1978</marker>
<rawString>Hobbs, Jerry. 1978. Resolving pronoun references. Lingua, 44:311-338.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Megumi Kameyama</author>
</authors>
<title>Recognizing referential links: An information extraction perspective.</title>
<date>1997</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the ACL&apos;97/EACL&apos;97 Workshop on Operational Factors in Practical, Robust Anaphora Resolution for Unrestricted Texts,</booktitle>
<pages>46--53</pages>
<location>Madrid,</location>
<contexts>
<context position="4386" citStr="Kameyama (1997)" startWordPosition="627" endWordPosition="628">nd more modern approaches was made possible by the availability of suitable corpora. While the shift toward knowledge-poor strategies and the use of corpora represented the main trends of anaphora resolution in the 1990s, there are other significant highlights in recent anaphora resolution research. The inclusion of the coreference task in the Sixth and Seventh Message Understanding Conferences (MUC-6 and MUC-7) gave a considerable impetus to the development of coreference resolution algorithms and systems, such as those described in Baldwin et al. (1995), Gaizauskas and Humphreys (1996), and Kameyama (1997). The last decade of the 20th century saw a number of anaphora resolution projects for languages other than English such as French, German, Japanese, Spanish, Portuguese, and Turkish. Against the background of a growing interest in multilingual NLP, multilingual anaphora /coreference resolution has gained considerable momentum in recent years (Aone and McKee 1993; Azzam, Humphreys, and Gaizauskas 1998; Harabagiu and Maiorano 2000; Mitkov and Barbu 2000; Mitkov 1999; Mitkov and Stys 1997; Mitkov, Belguith, and Stys 1998). Other milestones of recent research include the deployment of probabilist</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Kameyama, 1997</marker>
<rawString>Kameyama, Megumi. 1997. Recognizing referential links: An information extraction perspective. In Proceedings of the ACL&apos;97/EACL&apos;97 Workshop on Operational Factors in Practical, Robust Anaphora Resolution for Unrestricted Texts, pages 46-53, Madrid, Spain.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Andrew Kehler</author>
</authors>
<title>Probabilistic coreference in information extraction.</title>
<date>1997</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the 2nd Conference on Empirical Methods in Natural Language Processing (EMNLP-2),</booktitle>
<pages>163--173</pages>
<location>Providence, RI.</location>
<contexts>
<context position="5056" citStr="Kehler 1997" startWordPosition="726" endWordPosition="727">ora resolution projects for languages other than English such as French, German, Japanese, Spanish, Portuguese, and Turkish. Against the background of a growing interest in multilingual NLP, multilingual anaphora /coreference resolution has gained considerable momentum in recent years (Aone and McKee 1993; Azzam, Humphreys, and Gaizauskas 1998; Harabagiu and Maiorano 2000; Mitkov and Barbu 2000; Mitkov 1999; Mitkov and Stys 1997; Mitkov, Belguith, and Stys 1998). Other milestones of recent research include the deployment of probabilistic and machine learning techniques (Aone and Bennett 1995; Kehler 1997; Ge, Hale, and Charniak 1998; Cardie and Wagstaff 1999; the continuing interest in centering, used either in original or in revised form (Abracos and Lopes 1994; Strube and Hahn 1996; Hahn and Strube 1997; Tetreault 1999); and proposals related to the evaluation methodology in anaphora resolution (Mitkov 1998a, 2001b). For a more detailed survey of the state of the art in anaphora resolution, see Mitkov (forthcoming). The papers published in this issue reflect the major trends in anaphora resolution in recent years. Some of them describe approaches that do not exploit full syntactic knowledge</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Kehler, 1997</marker>
<rawString>Kehler, Andrew. 1997. Probabilistic coreference in information extraction. In Proceedings of the 2nd Conference on Empirical Methods in Natural Language Processing (EMNLP-2), pages 163-173, Providence, RI.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Christopher Kennedy</author>
<author>Branimir Boguraev</author>
</authors>
<title>Anaphora for everyone: Pronominal anaphora resolution without a parser.</title>
<date>1996</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the 16th International Conference on Computational resolution. Computational Linguistics,</booktitle>
<pages>20--4</pages>
<contexts>
<context position="2256" citStr="Kennedy and Boguraev 1996" startWordPosition="319" endWordPosition="322">nd which required considerable human input. However, the pressing need for the development of robust and inexpensive solutions to meet the demands of practical NLP systems encouraged many researchers to move away from extensive domain and linguistic knowledge and to embark instead upon knowledge-poor anaphora resolution strategies. A number of proposals in the 1990s deliberately limited the extent to which they relied on domain and/or linguistic knowledge and reported promising results in knowledge-poor operational environments (Dagan and Itai 1990, 1991; Lappin and Leass 1994; Nasukawa 1994; Kennedy and Boguraev 1996; Williams, Harvey, and Preston 1996; Baldwin 1997; Mitkov 1996, 1998b). The drive toward knowledge-poor and robust approaches was further motivated by the emergence of cheaper and more reliable corpus-based NLP tools such as partof-speech taggers and shallow parsers, alongside the increasing availability of corpora and other NLP resources (e.g., ontologies). In fact, the availability of corpora, both raw and annotated with coreferential links, provided a strong impetus to anaphora resolu* School of Humanities, Language and Social Sciences, Stafford Street, Wolverhampton WV1 1SB, UK. E-mail: r</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Kennedy, Boguraev, 1996</marker>
<rawString>Kennedy, Christopher and Branimir Boguraev. 1996. Anaphora for everyone: Pronominal anaphora resolution without a parser. In Proceedings of the 16th International Conference on Computational resolution. Computational Linguistics, 20(4):535-561.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Ruslan Mitkov</author>
</authors>
<title>Pronoun resolution: The practical alternative. Presented at the Discourse Anaphora and Anaphor Resolution Colloquium (DAARC-1),</title>
<date>1996</date>
<booktitle>Corpus-Based and Computational Approaches to Discourse Anaphora. John Benjamins,</booktitle>
<pages>2000--189</pages>
<editor>Simon Botley and Tony McEnery, editors,</editor>
<location>Lancaster, UK.</location>
<note>Reprinted in</note>
<contexts>
<context position="2319" citStr="Mitkov 1996" startWordPosition="330" endWordPosition="331">e development of robust and inexpensive solutions to meet the demands of practical NLP systems encouraged many researchers to move away from extensive domain and linguistic knowledge and to embark instead upon knowledge-poor anaphora resolution strategies. A number of proposals in the 1990s deliberately limited the extent to which they relied on domain and/or linguistic knowledge and reported promising results in knowledge-poor operational environments (Dagan and Itai 1990, 1991; Lappin and Leass 1994; Nasukawa 1994; Kennedy and Boguraev 1996; Williams, Harvey, and Preston 1996; Baldwin 1997; Mitkov 1996, 1998b). The drive toward knowledge-poor and robust approaches was further motivated by the emergence of cheaper and more reliable corpus-based NLP tools such as partof-speech taggers and shallow parsers, alongside the increasing availability of corpora and other NLP resources (e.g., ontologies). In fact, the availability of corpora, both raw and annotated with coreferential links, provided a strong impetus to anaphora resolu* School of Humanities, Language and Social Sciences, Stafford Street, Wolverhampton WV1 1SB, UK. E-mail: r.mitkov@w1v.ac.uk t 30 Saw Mill River Road, Hawthorne, NY 10532</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Mitkov, 1996</marker>
<rawString>Mitkov, Ruslan. 1996. Pronoun resolution: The practical alternative. Presented at the Discourse Anaphora and Anaphor Resolution Colloquium (DAARC-1), Lancaster, UK. Reprinted in Simon Botley and Tony McEnery, editors, Corpus-Based and Computational Approaches to Discourse Anaphora. John Benjamins, Amsterdam, 2000,189-212.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Ruslan Mitkov</author>
</authors>
<title>Evaluating anaphora resolution approaches.</title>
<date>1998</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the Discourse Anaphora and Anaphora Resolution Colloquium (DAARC-2),</booktitle>
<location>Lancaster, UK.</location>
<contexts>
<context position="5367" citStr="Mitkov 1998" startWordPosition="775" endWordPosition="776">am, Humphreys, and Gaizauskas 1998; Harabagiu and Maiorano 2000; Mitkov and Barbu 2000; Mitkov 1999; Mitkov and Stys 1997; Mitkov, Belguith, and Stys 1998). Other milestones of recent research include the deployment of probabilistic and machine learning techniques (Aone and Bennett 1995; Kehler 1997; Ge, Hale, and Charniak 1998; Cardie and Wagstaff 1999; the continuing interest in centering, used either in original or in revised form (Abracos and Lopes 1994; Strube and Hahn 1996; Hahn and Strube 1997; Tetreault 1999); and proposals related to the evaluation methodology in anaphora resolution (Mitkov 1998a, 2001b). For a more detailed survey of the state of the art in anaphora resolution, see Mitkov (forthcoming). The papers published in this issue reflect the major trends in anaphora resolution in recent years. Some of them describe approaches that do not exploit full syntactic knowledge (as in the case of Palomar et al.&apos;s and Stuckardt&apos;s work) or that employ machine learning techniques (Soon, Ng, and Lim); others present centering-based pronoun resolution (Tetreault) or discuss theoretical centering issues (Kibble). Almost all of the papers feature extensive evaluation (including comparative</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Mitkov, 1998</marker>
<rawString>Mitkov, Ruslan. 1998a. Evaluating anaphora resolution approaches. In Proceedings of the Discourse Anaphora and Anaphora Resolution Colloquium (DAARC-2), Lancaster, UK.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Ruslan Mitkov</author>
</authors>
<title>Robust pronoun resolution with limited knowledge.</title>
<date>1998</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the 36th Annual Meeting of the Association for Computational Linguistics and the 17th International Conference on Computational Linguistics (COLING&apos;98/ACL&apos;98),</booktitle>
<pages>869--875</pages>
<location>Montreal, Canada.</location>
<contexts>
<context position="5367" citStr="Mitkov 1998" startWordPosition="775" endWordPosition="776">am, Humphreys, and Gaizauskas 1998; Harabagiu and Maiorano 2000; Mitkov and Barbu 2000; Mitkov 1999; Mitkov and Stys 1997; Mitkov, Belguith, and Stys 1998). Other milestones of recent research include the deployment of probabilistic and machine learning techniques (Aone and Bennett 1995; Kehler 1997; Ge, Hale, and Charniak 1998; Cardie and Wagstaff 1999; the continuing interest in centering, used either in original or in revised form (Abracos and Lopes 1994; Strube and Hahn 1996; Hahn and Strube 1997; Tetreault 1999); and proposals related to the evaluation methodology in anaphora resolution (Mitkov 1998a, 2001b). For a more detailed survey of the state of the art in anaphora resolution, see Mitkov (forthcoming). The papers published in this issue reflect the major trends in anaphora resolution in recent years. Some of them describe approaches that do not exploit full syntactic knowledge (as in the case of Palomar et al.&apos;s and Stuckardt&apos;s work) or that employ machine learning techniques (Soon, Ng, and Lim); others present centering-based pronoun resolution (Tetreault) or discuss theoretical centering issues (Kibble). Almost all of the papers feature extensive evaluation (including comparative</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Mitkov, 1998</marker>
<rawString>Mitkov, Ruslan. 1998b. Robust pronoun resolution with limited knowledge. In Proceedings of the 36th Annual Meeting of the Association for Computational Linguistics and the 17th International Conference on Computational Linguistics (COLING&apos;98/ACL&apos;98), pages 869-875, Montreal, Canada.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Ruslan Mitkov</author>
</authors>
<title>Multilingual anaphora resolution.</title>
<date>1999</date>
<journal>Machine Translation,</journal>
<pages>14--3</pages>
<contexts>
<context position="4855" citStr="Mitkov 1999" startWordPosition="696" endWordPosition="697">ence resolution algorithms and systems, such as those described in Baldwin et al. (1995), Gaizauskas and Humphreys (1996), and Kameyama (1997). The last decade of the 20th century saw a number of anaphora resolution projects for languages other than English such as French, German, Japanese, Spanish, Portuguese, and Turkish. Against the background of a growing interest in multilingual NLP, multilingual anaphora /coreference resolution has gained considerable momentum in recent years (Aone and McKee 1993; Azzam, Humphreys, and Gaizauskas 1998; Harabagiu and Maiorano 2000; Mitkov and Barbu 2000; Mitkov 1999; Mitkov and Stys 1997; Mitkov, Belguith, and Stys 1998). Other milestones of recent research include the deployment of probabilistic and machine learning techniques (Aone and Bennett 1995; Kehler 1997; Ge, Hale, and Charniak 1998; Cardie and Wagstaff 1999; the continuing interest in centering, used either in original or in revised form (Abracos and Lopes 1994; Strube and Hahn 1996; Hahn and Strube 1997; Tetreault 1999); and proposals related to the evaluation methodology in anaphora resolution (Mitkov 1998a, 2001b). For a more detailed survey of the state of the art in anaphora resolution, se</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Mitkov, 1999</marker>
<rawString>Mitkov, Ruslan. 1999. Multilingual anaphora resolution. Machine Translation, 14(3-4):281-299.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Ruslan Mitkov</author>
</authors>
<title>Outstanding issues in anaphora resolution.</title>
<date>2001</date>
<booktitle>Computational Linguistics and Intelligent Text Processing.</booktitle>
<pages>110--125</pages>
<editor>In Alexander Gelbukh, editor,</editor>
<publisher>Springer,</publisher>
<location>Berlin,</location>
<contexts>
<context position="10106" citStr="Mitkov 2001" startWordPosition="1467" endWordPosition="1468">which specify the center movement across sentences. Instead of defining a total preference ordering, Kibble argues that a partial ordering emerges from the interaction among cohesion (maintaining the same center), salience (realizing the center as subject), and cheapness (realizing the anticipated center of a following utterance as subject). The last years have seen considerable advances in the field of anaphora resolution, but a number of outstanding issues either remain unsolved or need more attention and, as a consequence, represent major challenges to the further development of the field (Mitkov 2001a). A fundamental question that needs further investigation is how far the performance of anaphora resolution algorithms can go and what the limitations of knowledge-poor methods are. In particular, more research should be carried out on the factors influencing the performance of these algorithms. One of the impediments to the evaluation or fuller utilization of machine learning techniques is the lack of widely available corpora annotated for anaphoric or coreferential links. More work toward the proposal of consistent and comprehensive evaluation is necessary; so too is work in multilingual c</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Mitkov, 2001</marker>
<rawString>Mitkov, Ruslan. 2001a. Outstanding issues in anaphora resolution. In Alexander Gelbukh, editor, Computational Linguistics and Intelligent Text Processing. Springer, Berlin, pages 110-125.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Ruslan Mitkov</author>
</authors>
<title>Towards a more consistent and comprehensive evaluation of anaphora resolution algorithms and systems.</title>
<date>2001</date>
<journal>Applied Artificial Intelligence: An International Journal,</journal>
<pages>15--253</pages>
<contexts>
<context position="10106" citStr="Mitkov 2001" startWordPosition="1467" endWordPosition="1468">which specify the center movement across sentences. Instead of defining a total preference ordering, Kibble argues that a partial ordering emerges from the interaction among cohesion (maintaining the same center), salience (realizing the center as subject), and cheapness (realizing the anticipated center of a following utterance as subject). The last years have seen considerable advances in the field of anaphora resolution, but a number of outstanding issues either remain unsolved or need more attention and, as a consequence, represent major challenges to the further development of the field (Mitkov 2001a). A fundamental question that needs further investigation is how far the performance of anaphora resolution algorithms can go and what the limitations of knowledge-poor methods are. In particular, more research should be carried out on the factors influencing the performance of these algorithms. One of the impediments to the evaluation or fuller utilization of machine learning techniques is the lack of widely available corpora annotated for anaphoric or coreferential links. More work toward the proposal of consistent and comprehensive evaluation is necessary; so too is work in multilingual c</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Mitkov, 2001</marker>
<rawString>Mitkov, Ruslan. 2001b. Towards a more consistent and comprehensive evaluation of anaphora resolution algorithms and systems. Applied Artificial Intelligence: An International Journal, 15:253-276.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="false">
<authors>
<author>Ruslan Mitkov</author>
</authors>
<title>Forthcoming. Anaphora Resolution.</title>
<publisher>Longman,</publisher>
<location>Harlow, UK.</location>
<marker>Mitkov, </marker>
<rawString>Mitkov, Ruslan. Forthcoming. Anaphora Resolution. Longman, Harlow, UK.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Ruslan Mitkov</author>
<author>Lamia Belguith</author>
<author>Malgorzata Stys</author>
</authors>
<title>Multilingual robust anaphora resolution.</title>
<date>1998</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the Third International Conference on Empirical Methods in Natural Language Processing (EMNLP-3),</booktitle>
<pages>7--16</pages>
<location>Granada,</location>
<marker>Mitkov, Belguith, Stys, 1998</marker>
<rawString>Mitkov, Ruslan, Lamia Belguith, and Malgorzata Stys. 1998. Multilingual robust anaphora resolution. In Proceedings of the Third International Conference on Empirical Methods in Natural Language Processing (EMNLP-3), pages 7-16, Granada, Spain.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Ruslan Mitkov</author>
<author>Malgorzata Stys</author>
</authors>
<title>Robust reference resolution with limited knowledge: High precision genre-specific approach for English and Polish.</title>
<date>1997</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the International Conference on Recent Advances in Natural Language Processing (RANLP&apos;97),</booktitle>
<pages>74--81</pages>
<location>Tzigov Chark, Bulgaria.</location>
<contexts>
<context position="4877" citStr="Mitkov and Stys 1997" startWordPosition="698" endWordPosition="701">on algorithms and systems, such as those described in Baldwin et al. (1995), Gaizauskas and Humphreys (1996), and Kameyama (1997). The last decade of the 20th century saw a number of anaphora resolution projects for languages other than English such as French, German, Japanese, Spanish, Portuguese, and Turkish. Against the background of a growing interest in multilingual NLP, multilingual anaphora /coreference resolution has gained considerable momentum in recent years (Aone and McKee 1993; Azzam, Humphreys, and Gaizauskas 1998; Harabagiu and Maiorano 2000; Mitkov and Barbu 2000; Mitkov 1999; Mitkov and Stys 1997; Mitkov, Belguith, and Stys 1998). Other milestones of recent research include the deployment of probabilistic and machine learning techniques (Aone and Bennett 1995; Kehler 1997; Ge, Hale, and Charniak 1998; Cardie and Wagstaff 1999; the continuing interest in centering, used either in original or in revised form (Abracos and Lopes 1994; Strube and Hahn 1996; Hahn and Strube 1997; Tetreault 1999); and proposals related to the evaluation methodology in anaphora resolution (Mitkov 1998a, 2001b). For a more detailed survey of the state of the art in anaphora resolution, see Mitkov (forthcoming)</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Mitkov, Stys, 1997</marker>
<rawString>Mitkov, Ruslan and Malgorzata Stys. 1997. Robust reference resolution with limited knowledge: High precision genre-specific approach for English and Polish. In Proceedings of the International Conference on Recent Advances in Natural Language Processing (RANLP&apos;97), pages 74-81, Tzigov Chark, Bulgaria.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Ruslan Mitkov</author>
<author>Catalina Barbu</author>
</authors>
<title>Improving pronoun resolution in two languages by means of bilingual corpora.</title>
<date>2000</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the Discourse, Anaphora and Reference Resolution Conference (DAARC</booktitle>
<pages>133--137</pages>
<location>Lancaster, UK.</location>
<contexts>
<context position="4842" citStr="Mitkov and Barbu 2000" startWordPosition="692" endWordPosition="695"> development of coreference resolution algorithms and systems, such as those described in Baldwin et al. (1995), Gaizauskas and Humphreys (1996), and Kameyama (1997). The last decade of the 20th century saw a number of anaphora resolution projects for languages other than English such as French, German, Japanese, Spanish, Portuguese, and Turkish. Against the background of a growing interest in multilingual NLP, multilingual anaphora /coreference resolution has gained considerable momentum in recent years (Aone and McKee 1993; Azzam, Humphreys, and Gaizauskas 1998; Harabagiu and Maiorano 2000; Mitkov and Barbu 2000; Mitkov 1999; Mitkov and Stys 1997; Mitkov, Belguith, and Stys 1998). Other milestones of recent research include the deployment of probabilistic and machine learning techniques (Aone and Bennett 1995; Kehler 1997; Ge, Hale, and Charniak 1998; Cardie and Wagstaff 1999; the continuing interest in centering, used either in original or in revised form (Abracos and Lopes 1994; Strube and Hahn 1996; Hahn and Strube 1997; Tetreault 1999); and proposals related to the evaluation methodology in anaphora resolution (Mitkov 1998a, 2001b). For a more detailed survey of the state of the art in anaphora r</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Mitkov, Barbu, 2000</marker>
<rawString>Mitkov, Ruslan and Catalina Barbu. 2000. Improving pronoun resolution in two languages by means of bilingual corpora. In Proceedings of the Discourse, Anaphora and Reference Resolution Conference (DAARC 2000), pages 133-137, Lancaster, UK.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Tetsuya Nasukawa</author>
</authors>
<title>Robust method of pronoun resolution using full-text information.</title>
<date>1994</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the 15th International Conference on Computational Linguistics (COLING&apos;94),</booktitle>
<pages>1157--1163</pages>
<location>Kyoto, Japan.</location>
<contexts>
<context position="2229" citStr="Nasukawa 1994" startWordPosition="317" endWordPosition="318">d to process, and which required considerable human input. However, the pressing need for the development of robust and inexpensive solutions to meet the demands of practical NLP systems encouraged many researchers to move away from extensive domain and linguistic knowledge and to embark instead upon knowledge-poor anaphora resolution strategies. A number of proposals in the 1990s deliberately limited the extent to which they relied on domain and/or linguistic knowledge and reported promising results in knowledge-poor operational environments (Dagan and Itai 1990, 1991; Lappin and Leass 1994; Nasukawa 1994; Kennedy and Boguraev 1996; Williams, Harvey, and Preston 1996; Baldwin 1997; Mitkov 1996, 1998b). The drive toward knowledge-poor and robust approaches was further motivated by the emergence of cheaper and more reliable corpus-based NLP tools such as partof-speech taggers and shallow parsers, alongside the increasing availability of corpora and other NLP resources (e.g., ontologies). In fact, the availability of corpora, both raw and annotated with coreferential links, provided a strong impetus to anaphora resolu* School of Humanities, Language and Social Sciences, Stafford Street, Wolverham</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Nasukawa, 1994</marker>
<rawString>Nasukawa, Tetsuya. 1994. Robust method of pronoun resolution using full-text information. In Proceedings of the 15th International Conference on Computational Linguistics (COLING&apos;94), pages 1157-1163, Kyoto, Japan.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Constantin Orasan</author>
<author>Richard Evans</author>
<author>Ruslan Mitkov</author>
</authors>
<title>Enhancing preference-based anaphora resolution with genetic algorithms.</title>
<date>2000</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of NLP-2000,</booktitle>
<pages>185--195</pages>
<location>Patras, Greece.</location>
<marker>Orasan, Evans, Mitkov, 2000</marker>
<rawString>Orasan, Constantin, Richard Evans, and Ruslan Mitkov. 2000. Enhancing preference-based anaphora resolution with genetic algorithms. In Proceedings of NLP-2000, pages 185-195, Patras, Greece.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Elaine Rich</author>
<author>Susann LuperFoy</author>
</authors>
<title>An architecture for anaphora resolution.</title>
<date>1988</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the Second Conference on Applied Natural Language Processing (ANLP-2),</booktitle>
<pages>18--24</pages>
<location>Austin, TX.</location>
<contexts>
<context position="1547" citStr="Rich and LuperFoy 1988" startWordPosition="215" endWordPosition="218"> Discourse Representation Theory and Centering Theory inspired new research on the computational treatment of anaphora. The drive toward corpus-based robust NLP solutions further stimulated interest in alternative and/or data-enriched approaches. Last, but not least, application-driven research in areas such as automatic abstracting and information extraction independently highlighted the importance of anaphora and coreference resolution, boosting research in this area. Much of the earlier work in anaphora resolution heavily exploited domain and linguistic knowledge (Sidner 1979; Carter 1987; Rich and LuperFoy 1988; Carbonell and Brown 1988), which was difficult both to represent and to process, and which required considerable human input. However, the pressing need for the development of robust and inexpensive solutions to meet the demands of practical NLP systems encouraged many researchers to move away from extensive domain and linguistic knowledge and to embark instead upon knowledge-poor anaphora resolution strategies. A number of proposals in the 1990s deliberately limited the extent to which they relied on domain and/or linguistic knowledge and reported promising results in knowledge-poor operati</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Rich, LuperFoy, 1988</marker>
<rawString>Rich, Elaine and Susann LuperFoy. 1988. An architecture for anaphora resolution. In Proceedings of the Second Conference on Applied Natural Language Processing (ANLP-2), pages 18-24, Austin, TX.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Candace Sidner</author>
</authors>
<title>Toward a computational theory of definite anaphora comprehension in English.</title>
<date>1979</date>
<tech>Technical Report AI-TR-537,</tech>
<location>MIT, Cambridge, MA.</location>
<contexts>
<context position="1510" citStr="Sidner 1979" startWordPosition="211" endWordPosition="212">ies and formalisms such as Discourse Representation Theory and Centering Theory inspired new research on the computational treatment of anaphora. The drive toward corpus-based robust NLP solutions further stimulated interest in alternative and/or data-enriched approaches. Last, but not least, application-driven research in areas such as automatic abstracting and information extraction independently highlighted the importance of anaphora and coreference resolution, boosting research in this area. Much of the earlier work in anaphora resolution heavily exploited domain and linguistic knowledge (Sidner 1979; Carter 1987; Rich and LuperFoy 1988; Carbonell and Brown 1988), which was difficult both to represent and to process, and which required considerable human input. However, the pressing need for the development of robust and inexpensive solutions to meet the demands of practical NLP systems encouraged many researchers to move away from extensive domain and linguistic knowledge and to embark instead upon knowledge-poor anaphora resolution strategies. A number of proposals in the 1990s deliberately limited the extent to which they relied on domain and/or linguistic knowledge and reported promis</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Sidner, 1979</marker>
<rawString>Sidner, Candace. 1979. Toward a computational theory of definite anaphora comprehension in English. Technical Report AI-TR-537, MIT, Cambridge, MA.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Michael Strube</author>
</authors>
<title>Never look back: An alternative to centering.</title>
<date>1998</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the 36th Annual Meeting of the Association for Computational Linguistics and the 17th International Conference on Computational Linguistics (COLING&apos;98/ACL&apos;98),</booktitle>
<pages>1251--1257</pages>
<location>Montreal, Canada.</location>
<contexts>
<context position="8506" citStr="Strube 1998" startWordPosition="1225" endWordPosition="1226">related to the selection of optimal resolution factors) and application-oriented (e.g., related to the requirement of the application, as in the case of information extraction, where a proper name antecedent is needed) evaluation metrics should be considered. Tetreault&apos;s contribution features comparative evaluation involving the author&apos;s own centering-based pronoun resolution algorithm called the Left-Right Centering algorithm (LRC) as well as three other pronoun resolution methods: Hobbs&apos;s naive algorithm (Hobbs 1978), BFP (Brennan, Friedman, and Pollard 1987), and Strube&apos;s 5- list approach (Strube 1998). The LRC is an alternative to the original BFP algorithm in that it processes utterances incrementally. It works by first searching for an antecedent in the current sentence; if none can be found, it continues the search on the Cf-list of the previous and the other preceding utterances in a left-to-right fashion. In her squib, Byron maintains that additional kinds of information should be included in an evaluation in order to make the performance of algorithms on pronoun resolution more transparent. In particular, she suggests that the pronoun coverage be explicitly reported and proposes that</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Strube, 1998</marker>
<rawString>Strube, Michael. 1998. Never look back: An alternative to centering. In Proceedings of the 36th Annual Meeting of the Association for Computational Linguistics and the 17th International Conference on Computational Linguistics (COLING&apos;98/ACL&apos;98), pages 1251-1257, Montreal, Canada.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Michael Strube</author>
<author>Udo Hahn</author>
</authors>
<title>Functional centering.</title>
<date>1996</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the 34th Annual Meeting of the Association for Computational Linguistics (ACL&apos;96),</booktitle>
<pages>270--277</pages>
<location>Santa Cruz, CA.</location>
<contexts>
<context position="5239" citStr="Strube and Hahn 1996" startWordPosition="755" endWordPosition="758">ultilingual NLP, multilingual anaphora /coreference resolution has gained considerable momentum in recent years (Aone and McKee 1993; Azzam, Humphreys, and Gaizauskas 1998; Harabagiu and Maiorano 2000; Mitkov and Barbu 2000; Mitkov 1999; Mitkov and Stys 1997; Mitkov, Belguith, and Stys 1998). Other milestones of recent research include the deployment of probabilistic and machine learning techniques (Aone and Bennett 1995; Kehler 1997; Ge, Hale, and Charniak 1998; Cardie and Wagstaff 1999; the continuing interest in centering, used either in original or in revised form (Abracos and Lopes 1994; Strube and Hahn 1996; Hahn and Strube 1997; Tetreault 1999); and proposals related to the evaluation methodology in anaphora resolution (Mitkov 1998a, 2001b). For a more detailed survey of the state of the art in anaphora resolution, see Mitkov (forthcoming). The papers published in this issue reflect the major trends in anaphora resolution in recent years. Some of them describe approaches that do not exploit full syntactic knowledge (as in the case of Palomar et al.&apos;s and Stuckardt&apos;s work) or that employ machine learning techniques (Soon, Ng, and Lim); others present centering-based pronoun resolution (Tetreault</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Strube, Hahn, 1996</marker>
<rawString>Strube, Michael and Udo Hahn. 1996. Functional centering. In Proceedings of the 34th Annual Meeting of the Association for Computational Linguistics (ACL&apos;96), pages 270-277, Santa Cruz, CA.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Joel Tetreault</author>
</authors>
<title>Analysis of syntax-based pronoun resolution methods.</title>
<date>1999</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the 37th Annual Meeting of the Association for Computational Linguistics (ACL&apos;99),</booktitle>
<pages>602--605</pages>
<location>College Park, MD.</location>
<contexts>
<context position="5278" citStr="Tetreault 1999" startWordPosition="763" endWordPosition="764">ference resolution has gained considerable momentum in recent years (Aone and McKee 1993; Azzam, Humphreys, and Gaizauskas 1998; Harabagiu and Maiorano 2000; Mitkov and Barbu 2000; Mitkov 1999; Mitkov and Stys 1997; Mitkov, Belguith, and Stys 1998). Other milestones of recent research include the deployment of probabilistic and machine learning techniques (Aone and Bennett 1995; Kehler 1997; Ge, Hale, and Charniak 1998; Cardie and Wagstaff 1999; the continuing interest in centering, used either in original or in revised form (Abracos and Lopes 1994; Strube and Hahn 1996; Hahn and Strube 1997; Tetreault 1999); and proposals related to the evaluation methodology in anaphora resolution (Mitkov 1998a, 2001b). For a more detailed survey of the state of the art in anaphora resolution, see Mitkov (forthcoming). The papers published in this issue reflect the major trends in anaphora resolution in recent years. Some of them describe approaches that do not exploit full syntactic knowledge (as in the case of Palomar et al.&apos;s and Stuckardt&apos;s work) or that employ machine learning techniques (Soon, Ng, and Lim); others present centering-based pronoun resolution (Tetreault) or discuss theoretical centering issu</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Tetreault, 1999</marker>
<rawString>Tetreault, Joel. 1999. Analysis of syntax-based pronoun resolution methods. In Proceedings of the 37th Annual Meeting of the Association for Computational Linguistics (ACL&apos;99), pages 602-605, College Park, MD.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Sandra Williams</author>
<author>Mark Harvey</author>
<author>Keith Preston</author>
</authors>
<title>Rule-based reference resolution for unrestricted text using part-of-speech tagging and noun phrase parsing.</title>
<date>1996</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the Discourse Anaphora and Anaphora Resolution Colloquium (DAARC-1),</booktitle>
<pages>441--456</pages>
<location>Lancaster, UK.</location>
<marker>Williams, Harvey, Preston, 1996</marker>
<rawString>Williams, Sandra, Mark Harvey, and Keith Preston. 1996. Rule-based reference resolution for unrestricted text using part-of-speech tagging and noun phrase parsing. In Proceedings of the Discourse Anaphora and Anaphora Resolution Colloquium (DAARC-1), pages 441-456, Lancaster, UK.</rawString>
</citation>
</citationList>
</algorithm>
</algorithms>