<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<algorithms version="110505">
<algorithm name="SectLabel" version="110505">
<variant no="0" confidence="0.000000">
<title confidence="0.96941">
A COMPUTATIONAL GRAMMAR OF DISCOURSE-NEUTRAL PROSODIC
PHRASING IN ENGLISH
</title>
<author confidence="0.796494666666667">
J. Bachenko and E. Fitzpatrick
AT &amp; T Bell Laboratories
Murray Hill, NJ 07974
</author>
<bodyText confidence="0.999555166666667">
We describe an experimental text-to-speech system that uses information about syntactic constituency,
adjacency to a verb, and constituent length to determine prosodic phrasing for synthetic speech. A central
goal of our work has been to characterize &amp;quot;discourse neutral&amp;quot; phrasing, i.e. sentence-level phrasing patterns
that are independent of discourse semantics. Our account builds on Bachenko et al. (1986), but differs in its
treatment of clausal structure and predicate-argument relations. Results so far indicate that the current
system performs well when measured against a corpus of judgments of prosodic phrasing.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.997784" genericHeader="abstract">
1 INTRODUCTION
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999985">
In previous work (Bachenko et al. 1986), we described an
experimental text-to-speech system that determined pro-
sodic phrasing for the Olive—Liberman synthesizer (Olive
and Liberman 1985). The system generated phrase bound-
aries using information derived from the syntactic struc-
ture of a sentence. While we saw significant improvements
in the resulting synthesized speech, we also observed prob-
lems with the system. Often these stemmed from our
assumptions that both clausal structure and predicate-
argument relations were important in determining prosodic
phrasing. This paper reconsiders those assumptions and
describes an analysis of phrasing that we believe corrects
many of the problems of the earlier version. Like the earlier
version, it has been implemented in a text-to-speech system
that uses a natural language parser and prosody rules to
generate information about the location and relative
strength of prosodic phrase boundaries.
Our current analysis rests on two ideas. First, it is
possible to describe a level of prosodic phrasing that is
independent of discourse semantics. Second, this discourse-
neutral phrasing depends on a mix of syntactic and nonsyn-
tactic factors; chiefly, syntactic constituency, left-to-right
word order, and constituent length. There is no necessary fit
between syntactic structure and phrasing, since prosodic
phrasing may ignore major syntactic boundaries in order to
satisfy the constraints on phrase length. Our approach thus
follows that of Grosjean et al. (1979), namely, that phras-
ing reflects &amp;quot;. . . two (sometimes conflicting) demands on
the speaker: the need to respect the linguistic structure of
the sentence and the need to balance the length of the
constituents in the output&amp;quot; (p. 75).
Section 2 will outline our analysis, focusing on the rela-
tionship between syntactic and prosodic structure. The
analysis is developed within the framework of generative
grammar, but we believe it is consistent with other ap-
proaches to syntactic description.&apos; Our main point will be
that the syntax plays a necessary but not sufficient role in
determining phrasing, its effects being filtered by separate
conditions on prosodic well-formedness (e.g. length). Sec-
tion 3 describes the implementation of our analysis in an
experimental text-to-speech system, and Section 4 summa-
rizes our main conclusions. Unless otherwise noted, the
corpus we used as a source of observations on phrasing in
human speech consisted of a taped professional dramatiza-
tion of the Sherlock Holmes story The Speckled Band and
a documentary about Mount Everest that includes both
professional &amp;quot;prepared&amp;quot; narration and the spontaneous
speech of interviews. The Holmes story involved two male
speakers and one female speaker; the Everest documentary
involved a male narrator and several male interviewees.
Both of us independently transcribed the tapes according to
our perceptions of prosodic phrasing. Other examples come
from transcriptions of speech that we recorded at Bell
Laboratories. In the transcriptions, we both distinguished
three types of prosodic event: a primary phrase boundary, a
secondary phrase boundary, and the absence of a boundary.
The most salient characteristic of the primary phrase bound-
ary was a pause, while that of the secondary boundary
involved a change in pitch. In comparing the two transcrip-
tions, we discarded cases in which there was a discrepancy
between the two markings, which left us with a corpus of
approximately 500 sentences against which the prosodic
phrasing rules were tested.
</bodyText>
<note confidence="0.737085">
Computational Linguistics Volume 16, Number 3, September 1990 155
J. Bachenko and E. Fitzpatrick Discourse-Neutral Prosodic Phrasing in English
</note>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.794304666666667" genericHeader="method">
2 AN ANALYSIS OF PHRASING
2.1 BACKGROUND: THE FACTORS THAT
CONTRIBUTE TO PROSODIC PHRASING
</sectionHeader>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.78408">
2.1.1 SYNTAX AND PROSODIC PHRASING
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9988786">
What is the exact contribution of syntax to sound? There
are well-known local syntactic phenomena that affect both
phonetic segment quality and the stress pattern of the
phrase. A difference in syntactic category affects phonetic
quality in examples 1-3 below:
</bodyText>
<listItem confidence="0.9999">
1. a. They live in Canada. (live = verb)
b. He ate live lobster. (live = adjective)
2. a. Can you estimate the damage? (estimate = verb)
b. Give us an estimate. (estimate = noun)
3. a. As the water grew colder, their hands grew number.
(number = adjective)
b. Do you have his phone number? (number = noun)
</listItem>
<bodyText confidence="0.997858">
The type of object that a verb takes correlates with the
pronunciation of the verb in 4 and 5:
</bodyText>
<listItem confidence="0.995703">
4. He resided in Holland. (reside pronounced [rizaid])
5. He resided the house with aluminum. (reside pro-
nounced [risaid])
</listItem>
<bodyText confidence="0.985237666666667">
Syntactic category information also influences word pros-
ody, as in 6 and 7, where knowledge of category member-
ship is necessary to determine the correct stress pattern.
</bodyText>
<listItem confidence="0.996635">
6. a. Both content and style are important.
(content = noun)
b. They are content to remain here.
(content = adjective)
7. a. This ticket is invalid. (invalid = adjective)
b. He is an invalid. (invalid = noun)
</listItem>
<bodyText confidence="0.962620708333333">
Syntactic category may also affect phrasal stress. For
example, the sequence power units has stress on units in the
verb-noun sequence in 8, but it has stress on power in the
noun-noun sequence in 9:
8. If house current fails, power units from battery.
9. The power units failed.
Finally, syntactic gaps affect segment quality. For exam-
ple, the vowel in the preposition to is normally weak, as in
10. But if a gap like the one that is associated with the
question word who in 11 follows the preposition, the vowel
of to is strong.
10 We spoke to John. (to pronounced/t/)
11. Who did you speak to? (to pronounced /tu/)
When it comes to sentence-level prosody, especially phras-
ing, it is often true, as we will see below, that a sequence of
words dominated by the same syntactic node cohere more
closely than a sequence of words dominated by two dif-
ferent nodes. This observation has led some researchers,
e.g., Cooper and Paccia-Cooper (1980), to claim a direct
mapping between the syntactic phrase and the prosodic
phrase. However, this claim is controversial because of the
misa:ignments that occur between the two levels of phras-
ing. For example, in considering the connection between
syntax and phrasing, the linguistic literature most often
refers to examples of embedded sentences. Sentences like
12, from Chomsky (1965), are frequently cited. (Square
brackets mark off the NP constituents that contain embed-
ded sentences.)
12. This is [Nip the cat that caught [NI, the rat that stole [NI,
the cheese] ] ]
In such cases, the syntactic constituency indicated by brack-
eting is not in alignment with the prosodic phrasing. In-
stead, 12 has the prosodic phrasing in 13a. The phrasing in
13b, which most closely matches constituency, is strange at
best. (In these and other examples, the most prominent
prosodic boundaries are marked by vertical bars.)
13. a. This is the cat il that caught the rat II that stole the
cheese,
b. ??This is lithe cat that caught lithe rat that stole il
he cheese.
To account for such mismatches, &amp;quot;readjustment rules&amp;quot; that
change constituent structure by adjoining each embedded
sentence to the node dominating it have been posited. The
result is a flattened structure that more accurately reflects
the prosodic phrasing. In Chomsky and Halle (1968), this
flattening process is not part of the grammar. Rather, it is
viewed as &amp;quot;. . a performance factor, related to the diffi-
culty of producing right branching structures such as [12]&amp;quot;
(p. 372). Thus phrasing, in their approach, is only indi-
rectly related to syntax, since readjustment is done by
special rules outside the grammar proper.
Langendoen (1975) proposes readjustment rules similar
to those of Chomsky and Halle, but he claims that the
readjustment of structure is part of the grammar, not part
of the performance model. He thus makes explicit what is
often a tacit assumption in both the linguistic and psycho-
linguistic literature2—that there is a direct connection
between syntactic constituency and prosodic phrasing, with
apparent misalignments readjusted before syntax inter-
faces with prosodic phonology.
Langendoen&apos;s proposal works well for sentences such as
12 because it predicts that important prosodic phrase bound-
aries will coincide with sentence boundaries. But this does
not always fit the prosodic facts—sentences that lack overt
complementizers or relative pronouns often resist the inser-
tion of a break to set them off. For example, when applied
to They believe California sales are still off 75 percent,
readjustment rules cause the embedded sentence to be set
off prosodically, as in 14a. This seems quite unnatural
compared with 14b (an observed example), where a bound-
ary has been inserted not before the sentence, but after the
embedded subject.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.754706">
156 Computational Linguistics Volume 16, Number 3, September 1990
</page>
<note confidence="0.620395666666667">
J. Bachenko and E. Fitzpatrick Discourse-Neutral Prosodic Phrasing in English
14 a. ??They believe II California sales are still off 75%.
b. They believe California sales II are still off 75%.
</note>
<bodyText confidence="0.999140857142857">
Similarly, flattening the relative clause it saw in It was
ready to bite the first person it saw has the questionable
effect of inserting a prosodic phrase boundary before the
relative clause, as in 15a. But in our data, this sentence
actually has the phrasing in 15b, where the relative clause
is not set off. (The relative clause in these examples is
italicized.)
</bodyText>
<listItem confidence="0.4996505">
15. a. ??It was ready to bite the first person II it saw.
b. It was ready to bite lithe first person it saw.
</listItem>
<bodyText confidence="0.9945335">
Moreover, there are certain distinctions among clause types,
for example the difference between restrictive and apposi-
tive relatives, that are captured only by the presence or
absence of a separate prosodic phrase for the clause. How-
ever, Langendoen&apos;s claim that embedded clauses are flat-
tened would nullify this difference. The flattening and
consequent setting off of restrictive relatives would render
sentences such as 16a unintelligible because the associated
appositive reading forces a contradiction between who
came from Plymouth and who came from Falmouth. We
believe the only intelligible version of this sentence is 16b,
where there has been no readjustment of the come from
clauses.
16. a. ??The pilgrims II who came from Plymouth II were a
lusty bunch II while the pilgrims II who came from
Falmouth 11 were not.
b. The pilgrims who came from Plymouth II were a
lusty bunch II while the pilgrims who came from Fal-
mouth il were not.
In sum, the contribution of syntax to sound is borne out
by several phenomena. Even at the level of prosodic phras-
ing, syntactic constituents often cohere. Where misalign-
ments between the syntactic and the prosodic phrasing
occur, however, the notion of readjusting the syntax to fit
the prosody is problematic and, we believe, compares unfa-
vorably with an approach that views the semantic and
phonological components as contributing to prosodic phrase
boundary determination.
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.949843">
2.1.2 SEMANTICS AND PROSODIC PHRASING
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999500421052632">
The syntax/prosody misalignment may be viewed as result-
ing in part from semantic considerations. Both predicate-
argument relations and discourse factors have been exam-
ined for their possible input to prosodic phrasing.
Crystal (1969) claims that prosodic phrase boundaries
will co-occur with grammatical functions such as subject,
predicate, modifier, and adjunct. Selkirk (1984) and Ne-
spor and Vogel (1986) take a similar approach, but within
a different theoretical framework. Previous versions of our
work, as described in Bachenko et al. (1986) also assume
that phrasing is dependent on predicate-argument struc-
ture. The problem here is that the phrasing in observed
data often ignores the argument status of constituents. In
17a—f, for example, the phrasing makes no distinction
between arguments and adjuncts. All of the sentences have
the same X(VY) pattern even though Y is a complement in
the first case (the first serious attempt) and an adjunct in
the others. (The complement in 17a and the adjuncts in
17b—f are italicized.)
</bodyText>
<listItem confidence="0.994101375">
17. a. A British expedition il launched the first serious
attempt.
b. A single bright light II shone out from the darkness.
c. There were several little changes II carried out about
that time.
d. Were there any gypsies II camping in the planta-
tion. . . .
e. . . like the claws of a crab II thrown out on each side.
</listItem>
<bodyText confidence="0.989767290322581">
f. Two years II have passed since then.
The relation between discourse and prosodic phrasing
has been examined in some detail by Bing (1985), who
argues that each noun phrase in an utterance constitutes a
separate prosodic phrase unless it is destressed because of
reference to previous discourse. Bing also observes that
constituents that refer to items newly introduced into a
discourse tend to be longer. This may be the reason that
word count and syllable count play a prominent role in
prosodic phrasing (see Section 2.1.3.). To our knowledge,
no work has explicitly explored the relation between the
length of a constituent and its status in the discourse.
Hirschberg and Litman (1987) and Litman and Hirsch-
berg (1990) also examine the relation between discourse
and prosodic phrasing. Their work succeeds in distinguish-
ing the use of items like now, so, and well as discourse cues
from their denotative lexical use on the basis of a complex
combination of pitch accent type and phrasing.
The Hirschberg and Litman studies identify a specific
discourse distinction that relates to phrasing. These studies
are not intended to give a picture of the extent to which
discourse relates to phrasing. On the other hand, Bing&apos;s
work gives a broader picture of the relation between dis-
course and phrasing, but it deals only with noun phrases.
Thus both of these efforts leave open the question as to
whether discourse features completely determine prosodic
phrasing or are a complement to some more basic set of
determinants, syntactic and/or phonological. In other words,
when prosodic features that reflect facts of the discourse
are removed, is there a residual, neutral phrasing?
Our work on the prosodic phrase status of clause final
prepositional phrases, which we discuss below, suggests the
existence of a discourse-neutral phrasing that depends on
syntactic constituency mediated by string adjacency and
length of a potential prosodic phrase.3 Such phrasing pro-
vides us with a typical phrasing pattern analogous to the
typical phrasal stress patterns examined in Liberman and
Prince (1977), which &amp;quot;are often overwhelmed by the chiar-
oscuro of highlight and background in discourse, but retain
the status of null-hypothesis patterns that emerge when
Computational Linguistics Volume 16, Number 3, September 1990 157
J. Bachenko and E. Fitzpatrick Discourse-Neutral Prosodic Phrasing in English
there is no good reason to take some other option&amp;quot; (p. 251).
This approach to prosodic phrase boundary determination
brings us closer to a framework in which phonological,
syntactic, and discourse features all contribute to prosodic
phrasing.
The possibility of a discourse-neutral prosodic phrasing
is also of import to the prosodic quality of synthetic speech,
since it allows us to &amp;quot;get by&amp;quot; without a complete description
of the discourse features of a given text, many of which
have yet to be characterized. Interestingly, in the data we
examined we found only 14 percent of the phrases to be
discourse-determined.
The identification of a preferred phrasing that is indepen-
dent of discourse also aids us in identifying and characteriz-
ing the discourse features that impinge on prosodic phras-
ing. Several well-known discourse phenomena—coreference,
contrast, and parallelism—affected the phrasing of the
clause final prepositional phrases in our corpus. We are left
with three or four unexplained cases that are suggestive of a
discourse explanation.
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.8535485">
2.1.3 PHONOLOGICAL LENGTH AND
PROSODIC PHRASING
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999700511111111">
The psycholinguistic studies of Martin (1970), Allen (1975),
Hillinger et al. (1976), Grosjean et al. (1979), Dommer-
gues and Grosjean (1983), and Gee and Grosjean (1983),
responding to the idea of readjusted syntax as the source of
prosodic phrasing, show that grammatical structure, even
if readjusted, is not in itself a reliable predictor of prosodic
phrasing: mismatches between syntax and prosody occur
often and systematically, and can be related to specific
nonsyntactic factors such as length and word frequency.
For example, although prosodic boundaries between sub-
ject and verb do occur, there also exist prosodic patterns in
which the boundary comes between the verb and object,
i.e., the data reveal both X(VY) and (XV)Y groupings.
Grosjean et al. (1979) claims that such mismatches are due
for the most part to constituent length, which interacts with
grammatical structure and, in some cases, overrides it.
Thus syntactic and prosodic structure match when the
major constituents of a sentence are roughly equal in
length; for example, the main prosodic phrase break corre-
sponds to the subject-predicate boundary in Waiters who
remember well II serve orders correctly. Discrepancies in
length throw constituents off balance, and so prosodic
phrasing will cross constituent boundaries in order to give
the phrases similar lengths; this is the case in Chickens
were eating II the remaining green vegetables, where
the subject-predicate boundary finds no prosodic
correspondent.4
The most explicit version of this approach is the analysis
presented in Gee and Grosjean (1983) (henceforth G&amp;G).
Drawing on the psycholinguistic studies mentioned above
and on aspects of the grammar of prosody outlined in
Selkirk (1984), G&amp;G propose an algorithm for mapping
syntactic structure onto a hierarchical representation of
phrasing; the rules they present accomplish this by integrat-
ing syntactic information (e.g. constituent structure, left-to-
right ordering) with information about constituent length.
We have found that their rules, which are described in
detail, provide a productive model for investigations of
phrasing, and in what follows we shall frequently refer to
their analysis. But, as we will show, G&amp;G fall short of
providing a comprehensive theory. Their rules are too
limited and their syntax too underspecified to achieve
moderate coverage for an unrestricted collection of sen-
tences or to provide an adequate description for imple-
mental ion.5
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.999065">
2.2 CURRENT ANALYSIS
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.997994666666666">
Our goal has been to develop a theory of syntax/prosody
relations that we could test in an experimental text-to-
speech system. We approached the problem with the as-
sumption that there is a level of prosodic phrase determina-
tion that does not include discourse factors, and that aiming
for this level would yield an appropriate phrasing for a
sentence. Both the output of the system and our prelimi-
nary findings, which show that discourse factors influence
just a small part of the phrasings that follow a verb,
indicate that this approach is feasible.
The analysis that we arrived at takes G&amp;G and, to some
extent, Selkirk (1984) as its starting point. Hence we are
assuming that there is no necessary match between syntac-
tic structure and prosodic phrasing. Prosody rules refer to
syntactic structure, but they are not obliged to preserve it;
independent principles of prosodic well-formedness, in par-
ticular length calculations, may create entirely different
structures that appear at odds with the syntax. Here we
shall describe the main features of our analysis and then go
on to a description of the implementation.
Our prosody rules are intended to account for two as-
pects of phrasing: boundary location and boundary sa-
lience. In 18, for example, the rules need to stipulate that a
phrase boundary comes between the subject and predicate.
18. The light among the trees II was extinguished.
But when there is more than one important phrase bound-
ary in a sentence, the rules will also specify a relative
salience, or perceptibility, for each boundary. Thus in the
observed sentence 19, where an adjunct has been prefixed
to the sentence, the boundary between subject and predi-
cate diminishes in deference to the stronger boundary
between adjunct and core sentence. A single vertical bar
marks the diminished boundary.
</bodyText>
<listItem confidence="0.5319295">
19. About nine o&apos;clock II the light among the trees I was
extinguished.
</listItem>
<bodyText confidence="0.998783">
After deciding which boundaries will be diminished and
which highlighted, the rules assign each boundary an acous-
tic value that reflects its relative strength. Our current
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.753241">
158 Computational Linguistics Volume 16, Number 3, September 1990
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.966542916666667">
J. Bachenko and E. Fitzpatrick Discourse-Neutral Prosodic Phrasing in English
system uses three values made available by the synthesizer.
A pause and its concomitant prosodic effects mark the
strongest boundaries, a pitch change signifies intermediate
boundaries, and the weakest boundaries are assigned a
phrase accent.
Our work so far has focused solely on the issues of
location and relative salience; the rules for associating the
different boundaries with specific intonation contours and
acoustic values are still quite rudimentary. Consequently
our discussion will center on the location and salience rules,
and we will mention the third rule class only in passing.
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.788761">
2.2.1 BOUNDARY LOCATION RULES
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.988710590909091">
V NP PP
We+saw spring+up among+the+trees
The location rules identify possible boundary sites by first
deriving phonological words from the lexical items in a
parse tree, and then grouping the phonological words into
larger phonological phrases. The boundaries that separate
phonological phrases are the candidates for prosodic phrase
boundaries, since the prosodic phrases of speech consist of
one or more phonological phrases.
Our rules for phonological word formation are adopted,
for the most part, from G &amp;G, Grosjean and Gee (1987),
and the account of monosyllabic destressing in Selkirk
(1984). Thus in our analysis, rules of phonological word
formation apply to the non-null terminal nodes in a syntax
tree. If the terminal is a content word, i.e. noun, verb,
adjective, or adverb, then this terminal may have the status
of a phonological word on its own. Otherwise the word
combines with one or more orthographically distinct words
to form a single phonological word that has no internal
word or phrase boundaries. This is accomplished by adjoin-
ing a word to its left or right neighbor depending on its
lexical category and its position in the tree. Function words,
e.g. auxiliary verbs, articles, prepositions, pronouns, and
conjunctions, are all eligible for adjunction in certain syn-
tactic contexts. Content words, copular verbs, demonstra-
tives, quantifiers and elements in the complementizer node
can serve as hosts for the adjoined material or stand alone.
Figure 1 illustrates the effects of phonological word
formation; the &amp;quot;+&amp;quot; indicates that adjunction has taken
place.
Article adjunction, for example, attaches a, an, and the
to a following word, so that a sudden and the trees in Figure
1 each becomes a single phonological word in which the
article acts as an unstressed syllable. The rule of preposi-
tion adjunction, which has applied twice in Figure 1, at-
taches a preposition to the material on its right only if it is
the head of a PP, otherwise the preposition attaches left-
ward. Thus in 20a, where the preposition is a syntactic
head, in + the + dimly forms a single phonological word
after article and preposition adjunction. The phrase bound-
ary in this case will precede the preposition. But in 20b,
where there is no PP (rather, the preposition is a sister of
the verb in the syntax tree), filled + in is a phonological
word. Hence the boundary will follow the preposition.
</bodyText>
<figure confidence="0.872809">
Adj
a+sudden light
</figure>
<figureCaption confidence="0.99324">
Figure 1 Phonological Word Formation.
</figureCaption>
<bodyText confidence="0.99618752631579">
20. a. Holmes waited I in + the + dimly lit room.
b.. . .and filled + in I a few of the gaps.6
Rules of phonological phrase formation now build the
next level of prosodic constituents.&apos; Each phonological
phrase consists of a syntactic head and the material that
intervenes between it and a preceding head (usually, the
pre-head modifiers, e.g. pre-nominal adjectives, pre-verbal
adverbs). Following Selkirk (1984), we have limited the
eligible head categories to noun, verb, adjective, and adverb
(although adjectives and adverbs do not count if they
directly precede and modify another head). Examples 21a–b
illustrate the results of phonological phrase formation. In
each case, the phonological phrase is created by a left-to-
right process that collects material up to and including the
head of a syntactic constituent. Every phonological phrase
boundary thus marks a syntactic head as well as the site of
a possible prosodic boundary in speech. (The sequences
with + are words formed by adjunction; I stands for a
phonological phrase boundary.)
</bodyText>
<listItem confidence="0.99708975">
21. a. A + British expedition I launched I the + first
serious attempt.
b. We + saw I a + sudden light I spring + up I among
+ the + trees.
</listItem>
<bodyText confidence="0.882469944444444">
Which boundaries become the prominent ones is deter-
mined by the salience rules described below.
The elements of phonological phrases cohere strongly in
speech—they cannot be separated into smaller phrases
without a dramatic effect on the semantic content of the
sentence. In 22a, for instance, the italicized phrase must be
treated as a minimal element with respect to phrasing; the
Computational Linguistics Volume 16, Number 3, September 1990 159
J. Bachenko and E. Fitzpatrick Discourse-Neutral Prosodic Phrasing in English
phrasing of 22b, where an important break comes before
the syntactic head, is rare in our data.
22. a. I shall never forget I that April morning.
b. ??I shall never forget that I April morning.
Example 23a, with a phonological phrase boundary before
the preposition of, follows the pattern that is found in
nearly all of our data. The observed pattern in 23b, where
the boundary follows the of, creates a noticeably theatrical
effect with emphatic stress on strange.
</bodyText>
<listItem confidence="0.929208">
23. a. He&apos;s a collector I of strange animals.
b. He&apos;s a collector of I strange animals.
</listItem>
<subsubsectionHeader confidence="0.926601">
2.2.2 BOUNDARY SALIENCE RULES
</subsubsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.99826275">
The rules for salience apply to a combination of phonologi-
cal phrases and syntactic constituents. Their input is a
structure like that in Figure 2, where syntactic constituents
may contain one or more phonological phrases. The NP in
Figure 2 consists of a single phonological phrase, and the
top-level PP contains two. The absence of VP in this figure
will be explained below.
When they apply, the salience rules merge phonological
phrases to create larger prosodic phrases, which are also
merged into a final phrase hierarchy. Boundaries between
the phrases are thus diminished or emphasized, finally
giving the impression of a balanced, rhythmic pattern
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.7227516">
Sentence
V-phph
we+locked
N-phph
of+the+cheetah
</equation>
<bodyText confidence="0.943879642857143">
We locked our doors for fear of the cheetah
Figure 2 Input to Salience Rules
(phph = phonological phrase).
whose components appear to be equal in length. The sa-
lience rules apply on the basis of (i) adjacency to a verb, (ii)
length, and (iii) constituent type.
All three factors interact in the initial balancing of
material around a verb. In this process, the verb groups to
the left to form a (XV)Y pattern or it groups to the right to
produce a X(VY) pattern. Our analysis generally follows
G&amp;G, who propose the following rule, where, in their
formulation, Xis a prosodic constituent or null, Vis a verb,
Y is a nonsentential complement, and C refers to phonolog-
ical word count.
</bodyText>
<listItem confidence="0.6351364">
24. Verb Balancing Rule
in [XV Y]
if C(X) + C( V) &lt; C(Y)
then [(XV)Y]
otherwise [X(VY)]
</listItem>
<bodyText confidence="0.945774447368421">
The rule works through a sentence from left to right. It says
that if combining the verb with the constituent to its left
yields a word count less than that of the complement, the
verb forms a prosodic phrase with its left neighbor. Conse-
quently, the phrase boundary following the verb is strength-
ened. For all other cases, the verb groups to the right so that
the boundary preceding the verb becomes reinforced (G&amp;G
442). In 24, X and Y contain prosodic constituents, either
phonological phrases or prosodic phrases formed by other
salience rules (e.g. the constituent rules that build NP and
PP into separate prosodic phrases; see G&amp;G, p.441). Word
count (C) is determined solely by the number of phonologi-
cal vvords.8
Example 25a gives the phonological phrasing (indicated
by I) for This little incident gives a new zest to our
investigation. Applied to this string, the verb rule will
group the verb to the right and derive the X(VY) pattern
since This little incident plus gives adds up to four words,
while a new zest is only two words; the to-phrase is not
adjacent to the verb and so is not considered by the rule.
The final phrasing is given in 25b, where the verb rule
accounts for the break after the subject, and length rules
that are discussed below account for the second boundary.
25. a. This little incident I gives I a + new zest I to + our
+ investigation.
b. This little incident II gives a + new zest I to + our +
investigation.
Similarly in 26, Holmes&apos; eyes traveled adds up to three, but
the post-verb conjoined phrase round and round only counts
for two. Hence the verb groups to the right.
26. Holmes&apos; eyes II traveled round and + round.
The sentences in 27 follow the (XV) Yoption. In 27, as +
the + lamp plus was + lit add up to two words versus the
three words in + one of + the + sitting rooms. In 27b,
Chickens plus were + eating also add up to two words, the
+ remaining green vegetables adds up to three. In 27c, and
+ his + eyes plus were + fixed adds up to two words, while
in + a + dreadful rigid stare adds up to three.
</bodyText>
<figure confidence="0.5961785">
N-phph PP
our+doors N-phph
for+fear
PP
160 Computational Linguistics Volume 16, Number 3, September 1990
J. Bachenko and E. Fitzpatrick Discourse-Neutral Prosodic Phrasing in English
</figure>
<listItem confidence="0.901791666666667">
27. a. as + the + lamp was + lit II in + one of + the +
sitting rooms. . .
b. Chickens were + eating II the + remaining green
vegetables.
c. and + his + eyes were + fixed II in + a + dreadful
rigid stare.
</listItem>
<bodyText confidence="0.999419875">
In their formulation of the verb rule, G&amp;G impose two
conditions on its application. First, the rule may examine
only arguments of the verb, i.e., complements are candi-
dates for Yin 24, but modifiers and adjuncts are not. Hence
the rule must have access to VP constituency since verb
complements, in the generative grammar framework as-
sumed by G&amp;G, are represented as sisters of V in VP, while
modifiers and adjuncts are outside of the VP. Second, the
rule cannot cross S boundaries—embedded clauses form
separate prosodic units in G&amp;G&apos;s analysis.
Our studies indicate that these conditions are too strong:
balancing around a verb often crosses both VP and S
boundaries in our taped data. For example, in 28a–b, where
the verb and its complement occur in a single prosodic
phrase, the phrasing may appear to be influenced by the
presence of a VP (the complement is italicized.).
</bodyText>
<figure confidence="0.7358185">
28. a. A + British expedition II launched the + first
serious attempt.
b. The + 48 channel module II can + have only two
di-groups.
</figure>
<bodyText confidence="0.897330888888889">
Yet the verb also forms a single prosodic phrase with
sentence adjuncts. This is the case in 29a–c, where the verb
and adjunct are separated by an important boundary in the
syntax (VP), but not in the prosody. In these sentences,
while a secondary break may set off the adjunct, the main
prosodic phrase boundary comes before a verb + adjunct
sequence (the adjunct is italicized).
29. a. Seven of + our + porters II were + killed in + the +
fall
</bodyText>
<listItem confidence="0.998633333333333">
b. a + crack II opened in + the + snow.
c. the + elements of + personal interest II must + be
+ introduced at + all costs
</listItem>
<bodyText confidence="0.999933206896552">
If the verb-balancing rule is restricted to subcategorized
complements of the verb, as G&amp;G assume, then the phras-
ing in 29a–c has no explanation since, with the restriction,
the main boundary in these sentences has to come between
the verb and adjunct, a prediction that contradicts the
observed pattern and sounds strange at best. Sentences
such as those in 29a–c suggest that Yin the verb rule of 24
should not be limited to material within VP but should
include anything to the right of V. Hence we are assuming
that the key to phrasing in 28a–b, 29a–c is the adjacency
relationship between a verb and the constituent on its right,
not verb phrase structure, or, equivalently, the complement
versus noncomplement status of a constituent. In particu-
lar, phrasing around the verb depends on the relative length
of constitutents that are adjacent to a verb and, as we will
observe, the presence of specific verb-adjacent items (e.g.
phrasal and).
The phrasing of embedded sentences follows a similar
course. Prominent phrase boundaries often co-occur with
clause boundaries, e.g. Customers are asking retailers II
whether their watermelons come from California, but we
believe that this is only apparently due to clausal constitu-
ency. In our data, components of S can form a prosodic
phrase with nearly any adjacent material, regardless of
where the S boundary falls. For example, 30 a–c has the
most prominent break before the matrix verb, not before
the embedded S (which is italicized). The sentences of 31
have the most prominent prosodic break within the embed-
ded sentence.
</bodyText>
<listItem confidence="0.9751965">
30. a. Even my + fiance II believes it&apos;s only my + imagina-
tion.
b. Did + Dr. Roylott II continue to + practice?
c. A + terrible change II began to + come + over our
+ stepfather.
31. a. They + believe California sales II are + still off 75
percent.
b. I&apos;ve + heard that + the + crocuses II promise very
well.
c. Experience has + proved that + savages II are the +
tyrants of + the + female sex.
d. I + seem to + see dimly II what you&apos;re driving at.
</listItem>
<bodyText confidence="0.994820666666667">
Here again it appears that G&amp;G&apos;s formulation of verb
balancing, which prohibits the rule from crossing sentence
boundaries, is too strict. Requiring the prosody rules to
preserve the constituent status of embedded clauses pre-
dicts that when the verb is followed by an embedded clause,
as in 30a–c and 31a–d, balancing is superceded by rules
that work on the internal structure of the embedded S; the
result in most cases is a prominent prosodic boundary
before the embedded clause. According to this approach,
the sentence Did Dr. Roylott continue to practice? would
have the odd phrasing Did Dr. Roylott continue II to
practice? instead of the observed phrasing of 30b.
The phrasing patterns of 30a–c and 31a–d are easy to
explain if we assume that prosody rules ignore clausal
constituency so that verb balancing applies across S bound-
aries. Evidence from sentence adjuncts, e.g. the purposive
in We went out to the Himalaya to climb. . . and the
relative clause in It was ready to bite II the first person it
saw leads us to believe that prosody rules ignore these
clausal constituents as well. Our analysis thus adopts the
basic mechanism G&amp;G propose with their verb rule, but
without the conditions on verb complements and clausal
constituency. While NP, PP, and AdjP constituents
&amp;quot;count&amp;quot;in our prosody rules, VP and S constituents do not.
Consequently, eligible material to the right of V in the verb
rule 24 may be a complement, a modifier, an adjunct, or the
initial constituent of an embedded sentence. The exact
treatment of the left-adjacent constituent is still a topic for
investigation, and there is currently no requirement that
the material to the left of a verb be a subject.
G&amp;G intend the balancing rule to make the verb a
prosodic center by grouping constituents in such a way as to
Computational Linguistics Volume 16, Number 3, September 1990 161
J. Bachenko and E. Fitzpatrick Discourse-Neutral Prosodic Phrasing in English
create, in most cases, two phrases of approximately equal
length, with the verb as a left or right edge. During
subsequent processing, this balancing effect is usually lost
since neither length nor adjacency to a verb play any
further role in G&amp;G&apos;s analysis. After verb balancing, the
remaining constituents are bundled from left to right into a
left-branching binary tree like that in Figure 3. As we will
discuss below, the higher the constituent is in the prosody
tree, the more prominent will be the boundaries that set it
off in speech. Hence, when constituents are bundled, as in
Figure 3, material that comes at the end of a sentence will
usually be set off by the largest breaks. This is what
happens in 32a—b, where a strong boundary before the final
(italicized) constituent seems desirable.
</bodyText>
<listItem confidence="0.515152">
32. a. . . .walk away from your helper II approximately 50
feet.
b. I suddenly heard in the silence of the night II that
same low whistle.
</listItem>
<bodyText confidence="0.999152625">
But the application of bundling immediately after the
verb rule often leads to problems. The salience of a bound-
ary that occurs toward the end of a sentence tends to be
overestimated when the final constituent is relatively short.
When this happens, the final constituent may be set off
unnaturally from the rest of the sentence. In 33a—c, for
example, a strong boundary before the italicized constitu-
ent is inappropriate.9
</bodyText>
<listItem confidence="0.962144">
33. a. ??The speaker pronounced the names of the charac-
ters II on the left.
b. ??We locked our door for fear II of the cheetah.
c. ??She had caught an early morning train II from
London.
</listItem>
<bodyText confidence="0.9691236">
We believe that the problems raised by final bundling
can be avoided largely by extending the effects of length
and verb adjacency beyond the verb balancing rule. In our
analysis, this is accomplished by an adjacency rule and two
I gave the book to John for Christmas
</bodyText>
<figureCaption confidence="0.839857">
Figure 3 Final Bundling (adapted from G&amp;G,
p. 443).
</figureCaption>
<bodyText confidence="0.99762">
length rules that, in effect, sustain verb centering and
determine the prosodic weight of constituents not adjacent
to a verb. The adjacency rule in 34 applies after the
balancing rule of 24 and groups the &amp;quot;unclaimed&amp;quot; verb-
adjacent constituent with the phrase that was formed by 24
(this will be either ( VY) or (XV)). X in 34a and Yin 34b
are prosodic constituents.
</bodyText>
<listItem confidence="0.659274333333333">
34. Verb Adjacency Rule
a.[. . . X(VY). . [. . .(X(VY)). . .1
b. [. . . (XV) Y. . .] [. . .((XV)Y). . .]
</listItem>
<bodyText confidence="0.974796176470588">
where.. . is a phonological phrase or null
and X may or may not be a subject.
Case 34a says that if ( VY) is a prosodic constituent, then
create a new prosodic constituent composed of ( VY) and
adjacent material to the left. Likewise 34b creates a new
prosodic constituent by combining (XV) with adjacent
material on the right. What results is a prosodic verb
phase--a cluster of two prosodic phrases with the verb in
the middle as a left or right edge. In 35a—b, for example,
constituents abutting the verb have been worked into a
single prosodic verb phrase by (i) the verb balancing rule,
which groups the verb rightward with the complement
(giving. . . X(VY). and (ii) the adjacency rule in 34b,
which generates a larger phrase containing the constituent
on the left (= . . .(X(XY)). . The prosodic verb phrase is
italicized; its internal boundary is marked by a single
vertical bar.
</bodyText>
<listItem confidence="0.996638">
35. a. Everest I is an + enormous pyramid II with + three
wide faces and + three ridges.
b. Mrs. Welles I wrote a + weekly sports column II for
+ the + Christian Science Monitor.
</listItem>
<bodyText confidence="0.999402041666667">
Constituents that are not adjacent to the verb form the
periphery of a prosodic verb phrase. In 35a, the periphery
consists of with three wide faces and and three ridges; in
35b it consists of for the Christian Science Monitor. While
our understanding of phrasing of the periphery of a sen-
tence is far from satisfactory, we have been conducting a
study that so far suggests that, at least with respect to
clause-final prepositional phrases, length of a peripheral
constituent is an important determinant of its prosodic
prominence. The phrases considered all occur to the right
of the verb with some material intervening between the
verb and a prepositional phrase, PP. The intervening mate-
rial varies from a full phrase to a single word that functions
as a syntactic head to which the PP under consideration is a
complement. In a test of 129 clause-final prepositional
phrases, we noted the pattern shown in Figure 4. The clear
bifurcation of the numbers in this test suggests that length
of the PP is determining the degree to which final PPs are
set off. Many of the 18 apparent counterexamples to this
claim also indicate that length establishes a discourse-
neutral phrasing for sentence-final PPs that is contravened
only by predictable syntactic and discourse factors. For
example, the of-PP in the partitive construction of 36a is
not in a separate prosodic phrase, even though it contains
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.815346">
162 Computational Linguistics Volume 16, Number 3, September 1990
</page>
<figure confidence="0.9298815">
J. Bachenko and E. Fitzpatrick Discourse-Neutral Prosodic Phrasing in English
PP=1 stress foot
Pause precedes 6
No perceptible 48
prosodic event
precedes
</figure>
<figureCaption confidence="0.964773">
Figure 4 Phrasing of final PPs.&apos;
</figureCaption>
<figure confidence="0.570415666666667">
PP&gt;1 stress foot
63
12
</figure>
<bodyText confidence="0.9982385">
two stress feet (west and wing). This contrasts with 36b,
where the of-PP is not a partitive.
</bodyText>
<listItem confidence="0.99332925">
36. a. . . .blue smoke I curling + up from + the +
chimneys II showed that part of + the + west wing. . .
b. A + single bright light II shone + out from + the +
darkness ii of + the + west wing.
</listItem>
<bodyText confidence="0.971368258064516">
Similarly, while the italicized PP in 37a follows the rule
of being greater than one phonological word and therefore
set off, a similar PP in 37b is not set off because the
repetition of room causes this item to be destressed and
consequently to merge with the relevant PP.
37. a. Holmes passed at + once II into + the + room I in
+ which Helen Stoner II was now sleeping.
b. so + that I&apos;ve + had to + move out + of + my +
own room II into + the + room next door lithe + room
in + which my + sister died.
In the implementation, the length rules extend these
results to include post-verb peripheral constituents other
than PPs; specifically, interjections and adverbials. Cur-
rently, the length rules perform two operations on post-verb
peripheral material, depending on word count. In one case,
if a phrase, P1, consists of a single phonological word, it is
adjoined to the most recently created phrase, PO (usually a
prosodic verb phrase). The result is a new phrase, P2,
whose boundary salience is equal to that of PO. This is
illustrated in Figure 5, where i is a number representing
salience (Section 3 shows how salience indices are derived).
In the second case, a longer phrase, P1, will be bundled
with its preceding material, PO, in order to form a new
phrase, P2, whose salience is the sum of salience value for
PO and the value of PI (= word count + 1). In Figure 6, for
example, the &apos;long&apos; PP is set off by a relatively large index.
Peripheral material at the beginning of a sentence is
currently picked up by left-to-right bundling without re-
gard to constituent type or length. The correct treatment of
sentence-initial peripheral material remains a topic of inves-
tigation.
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.531807">
2.2.3 A PROSODIC LEFT&apos; CORNER CONSTRAINT
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.919496">
In some cases, phrasing is influenced by the lexical content
of a constituent. Phrasal and, i.e. the left corner of a NP,
PP, AdjP, or AdvP conjunct, always starts a new phrase, as
in Next to it ii he placed a box of matches II and a candle.&amp;quot;
she+had+caught an+early morning train from+London
She had caught an early morning train from London
</bodyText>
<figureCaption confidence="0.790053">
Figure 5 Adjunction of Short Peripheral Phrase
(i = boundary salience).
</figureCaption>
<bodyText confidence="0.9841441875">
In our analysis, this fact is captured by a global constraint
on the prosody rules: no boundary location or salience rule
may apply to a constituent whose left corner is a phrasal
conjunct. Hence when phrasal and is adjacent to a verb, the
prosodic left corner constraint will block the rules that form
prosodic verb phrases. In 38 the verb rule is prevented from
merging was extinguished with and all, as it would do if
and were treated as any other function word.
38. The light among the trees was extinguished and all was
dark.
Although the constraint should probably include other
material, such as the subordinate conjunctions (e.g. be-
cause, while, although), our current analysis acknowledges
only phrasal and, or, and nor, requiring that they always
introduce a separate phrase. In our implementation of the
Everest is an+enormous pyramid with+three wide faces
</bodyText>
<footnote confidence="0.530244">
Everest is an enormous pyramid with three wide faces
</footnote>
<figureCaption confidence="0.8045505">
Figure 6 Long Prepositional Phrase Attachment
(i = boundary salience).
</figureCaption>
<bodyText confidence="0.947852333333333">
Computational Linguistics Volume 16, Number 3, September 1990 163
J. Bachenko and E. Fitzpatrick Discourse-Neutral Prosodic Phrasing in English
prosody rules, we have extended the constraint to punctua-
tion. For example, the comma in After Robert ate, his cat
Freddy took a nap is first adjoined to the constituent on its
right, to give After Robert ate, +his cat Freddy took a
nap, and then, like phrasal and, obligatorily starts a new
phrase, preventing the prosody rules from merging ate and
his cat.
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.719414">
2.2.4 SUMMARY
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.99998855">
In this section, we have described an analysis of prosodic
phrasing that incorporates two classes of rules. Boundary
location rules form phonological words from the terminal
elements of syntactic structure and build phonological
phrases (the first tier of prosodic constituency), using infor-
mation about syntactic heads. Boundary salience rules
assign a relative strength, or perceptibility, to each phrase
boundary according to syntactic labeling, length, and adja-
cency; they ignore verb phrase and clausal constituency
and predicate-argument relations. The primary salience
rules are, in order, syntactic constituency, which converts
NP, PP, and AdjP constituents into prosodic phrases (see
G &amp;G, p. 441); verb balancing and verb adjacency, which
derive prosodic verb phrases; length rules, which apply to
the material on the right of a prosodic verb phrase; and final
bundling, which collects phrases built up by the previous
rules into a binary tree (see Figure 3). Location and
salience rules are both subject to a left corner constraint on
their application. In the following section, we discuss how
the rules work in an experimental text-to-speech system.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.83389" genericHeader="method">
3 AN EXPERIMENTAL TEXT-TO-SPEECH
SYSTEM
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.99997445">
We have built an experimental text-to-speech system that
uses our analysis of prosody to generate phrase boundaries
for the Olive–Liberman synthesizer (Olive and Liberman
1985). Two concerns motivated our implementation. First,
we hoped the system would provide us with a research tool
for testing our ideas about syntax and phrasing against a
large unrestricted collection of sentences. Second, we wished
to investigate how well our approach would work for deter-
mining prosodic phrasing in a text-to-speech synthesizer.
Existing text-to-speech systems perform well on word pro-
nunciation and short sentences,12 but when it comes to long
sentences and paragraphs, synthetic speech tends to be
difficult to listen to and understand. Many investigators
(e.g. Allen 1976; Elowitz et al. 1976; Luce et al. 1983;
Cahn 1988) have suggested that the poor prosody of syn-
thetic speech, in comparison with natural speech, is the
primary factor leading to difficulties in the comprehension
of fluent synthetic speech. And while researchers in text-to-
speech synthesis have adopted a variety of approaches to
prosodic phrase generation—from the simple punctuation-
based rules and function word listings of existing commer-
cial systems to the sophisticated prosodic heuristics de-
scribed in Emorine and Martin (1988) and O&apos;Shaughnessy
(1989)--the generation of appropriate prosodic phrasing in
unrestricted text has remained a problem.
As we will show, our results so far indicate that our
experimental system, which assigns a discourse neutral
prosodic phrasing on the level of sentences, provides a
significant improvement in the quality of synthesized speech.
We believe that one reason for the improvement has to do
with the increased pitch range that our system uses. Text-
to-speech systems that lack sentence-level phrasing must
take a conservative approach to pitch settings in order to
avoid misleading and inappropriate pitch modulations. Cor-
rect phrase identification makes it possible to adopt an
expanded pitch range that greatly enhances the naturalness
of the final speech. In constructing the system, we focused
on two core questions: (i) what kind of parser is needed for
the prosody rules? and (ii) how should prosodic phrasing,
i.e. boundary location and strength, be represented?
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.967544">
3.1 PARSING FOR PROSODY
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.948647894736842">
The rules for discourse-neutral phrasing that we propose
need examine only a subset of the syntactic information
that most parsers provide. That is, the rules require access
to lexical category, syntactic heads, NP/PP/AdjP/AdvP
constituency, and left-to-right word order, but not to clausal
constituency, predicate-argument relations, or modifier at-
tachment. We believe the rules must also recognize the
trace of wh-movement (e.g. the trace that precedes the
phrase break in The slope on which we were standing
[trace] started to move), although other null terminals
such as the trace of passivization are ignored.13 At the
outset of our project, we had available to us a moderate
coverage deterministic parser—Fidditch14—that we
adapted to the syntactic requirements for prosodic phras-
ing. This modified &amp;quot;speech parser&amp;quot; produces parse trees
like that in Figure 7. The tree represents syntactic informa-
tion necessary for phrasing, but omits nodes (S, VP) and
PRO told PRO AD! N PRO
London several days
</bodyText>
<note confidence="0.361851">
He told me Iasi night he was coming to London for several days.
</note>
<figureCaption confidence="0.999656">
Figure 7 Syntactic Input to Phrasing Rules.
</figureCaption>
<figure confidence="0.998162166666667">
NP V NP NP AUX viNG A iN
he me last night he
was coming
P NP
to PNP for
DET N
</figure>
<page confidence="0.863896">
164 Computational Linguistics Volume 16, Number 3, September 1990
</page>
<note confidence="0.568894">
J. Bachenko and E. Fitzpatrick Discourse-Neutral Prosodic Phrasing in English
</note>
<bodyText confidence="0.9740885">
branches that are unnecessary for prosodic phrase determi-
nation.
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.998874">
3.2 PROSODIC PHRASE REPRESENTATION
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.968794696969697">
Following G&amp;G, we require that the prosody rules build a
binary tree whose terminals are phonological words and
whose node labels are indices that mark boundary salience.
An alternative representation based on Liberman and Prince
(1977) is presented in Selkirk (1984), which contends that
prosody, including prosodic phrasing, is more properly
represented as a grid instead of a tree. Although a grid may
be more descriptively suitable for some aspects of prosody
(for example, Sproat and Liberman (1987) use the grid
representation for their implementation of stress assign-
ment in compound nominals), we are not aware of any
evidence for or against a grid representation of discourse-
neutral phrasing.
Figure 8 shows the phonological phrase tree that is built
from the syntactic structure of Figure 7. The rules for
building this tree apply from left to right, following the
analysis we described in the preceding section. Figures
9-11. show the prosodic phrase derivation. Numbered nodes
refer to salience values, with higher numbers indicating
greater salience. The index is assigned according to phono-
logical word count, with one point added for the node itself.
Figure 11 is the final prosodic phrase tree; in the notation
we have been using, the phrasing represented by Figure 11
is He told me I last night II he was coming to London II for
several days.
Figure 9 shows the effect of two applications of verb
balancing. Applying from left to right, the rule first looks at
the phonological verb he + told + me. Since the material
to the left of the verb is null, the rule must group this verb
with the constituent on its right to form the node labeled 0.
On its second application, the rule balances the prosodic
phrase it has just formed against the single phonological
he+told+me last night
</bodyText>
<figureCaption confidence="0.946953">
Figure 9 Two Applications of Verb Balancing.
</figureCaption>
<bodyText confidence="0.967192294117647">
word to + London, and groups the verb rightward to form
node 0.
Verb adjacency is now triggered by the contiguity of 0
and the verb he + was + coming. In Figure 10, this rule
has formed the prosodic verb phrase 0.
It remains to collect the &amp;quot;long&amp;quot; peripheral constituent
for + several days. In Figure 11, the length rule has built
the final node of the tree; because the peripheral item
consists of two phonological words, the value of the topnode
is affected by the word count of the peripheral item. If the
peripheral item had consisted of a single phonological
word, the value of the top node would have been 8 instead of
11.
Finally, each node index is converted into one of three
acoustic values. High indices are marked as a minor phrase
boundary; mid-range indices are signified with a downstep
on the first phonological word following the boundary
</bodyText>
<figure confidence="0.993989357142857">
V-phph NP-phph V-phph PP-phph tori-several days
he+was+coming to+London
PP-phph
PP-phph
he+was+coming
N-phph
V-phph NP
he+told+me
to+London for+several days
PP-phph
for+several days
V-phph NP-phph V-phph PP-phph
Adj night
last
</figure>
<figureCaption confidence="0.804135">
Figure 8 Phonological Phrasing.
he+told+me last night he+was+coming to+London
Figure 10 Verb Adjacency.
</figureCaption>
<figure confidence="0.576708333333333">
Computational Linguistics Volume 16, Number 3, September 1990 165
J. Bachenko and E. Fitzpatrick Discourse-Neutral Prosodic Phrasing in English
he+told+me last night he+was+coming to+London
</figure>
<figureCaption confidence="0.987531">
Figure 11 Length Rule—Long Phrase (final rule).
</figureCaption>
<bodyText confidence="0.9998822">
(Pierrehumbert 1980), and those in the lowest range re-
ceive a phrase accent. The mapping onto three different
values reflects a simple subjective choice. A more complete
analysis would consider finer acoustic &amp;quot;tunings&amp;quot; for the
indices.
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.994418">
3.3 EVALUATING THE PHRASING SYSTEM
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.998620238095238">
In testing a prosodic phrase system, it is necessary to be
clear about the goals of the work. At the level of basic
inquiry, such a system should aim to correlate well with
human speech production, assuming that we are able to
abstract away from speaker variability. However, in work-
ing under the assumption that discourse plays a role,
however limited, in prosodic phrase determination, the
comparison of synthetic to human phrasing becomes less
meaningful since factors unknown to our system influence
the placement of phrase boundaries.
At the level of system building, a prosodic phrasing
system should aim to make a text-to-speech system easier
to understand. In general, adding phrasing to a text-to-
speech system will enhance synthetic speech both by break-
ing a run-on delivery into more easily processed chunks of
speech and by allowing the pitch range to be increased,
enhancing naturalness. The primary requirement for mak-
ing synthetic speech easier to understand, however, is that
the phrasing system should first do no harm, i.e., it should
avoid misleading phrasings and phrasings like 38 that are
difficult for a listener to process.
38. ??This is lithe cat that caught lithe rat that stole lithe
cheese.
To address the issue of avoiding undesirable phrasings, a
system like ours must be run against a set of utterances of
disparate lengths and syntactic types to see where it breaks.
To do this, we accumulated a set of syntactically varied test
sentences, had them read by two speakers, marked the
prosodic phrase boundaries as we had done with the Holmes
and Everest data, and ran the sentences through our pro-
sodic phrase system for comparison with the human speak-
ers&apos; phrasing. Phrasing in the speech of the two human
speakers was almost identical; where the speakers failed to
match, we depended on the speaker with the more detailed
phrasing to obtain a single transcript for comparison. The
sentences with the phrase markings produced by the system
(S) and by the human speakers (H) are given in Appendix
A. In addition, we used the sentences of Grosjean et al.
(1979) to test our system; these were the same sentences
used by G &amp;G. They were produced by six subjects speak-
ing each sentence at five different speaking rates. We chose
these data both because they form an established, though
small, corpus and because their phrase markings, derived
by oscillographic tracings of pause duration, provide a
check against the possibility of error in human judgments
of pause location and salience. A comparison of these data
with the output of our system is given in Appendix B.
In comparing human and synthetic prosodic phrasing
with an eye on synthetic phrasings that are either mislead-
ing or unprocessable, errors in the assignment of primary
phrase boundaries are the most egregious. In the data in
Appendix A, the human speakers produced 31 intrasenten-
tial primary phrase boundaries, of which our system
matched 16 with its equivalent of a primary phrase bound-
ary. The other primary phrase boundaries in the human
productions were matched in 9 cases with a secondary
phrase boundary, and in 5 cases with a tertiary boundary.
The system thus missed 1 primary boundary, the one after
books in 17. In the absence of research on the relative
significance of different boundary types, we are assuming
that, with respect to the comprehensability and acceptabil-
ity of synthetic speech, the difference between a primary
and secondary phrase boundary is minimal. On the other
hand, the tertiary boundary produced by our system is
almost imperceptible and cannot be considered equivalent
to the primary boundary. The system thus matched, either
exactly or approximately, 80% of the primary boundaries.
In looking at the primary phrase boundaries that the
system failed to duplicate, we want to be sure that we avoid
difficult phrasings like that of 38 rather than match any
particular phrasing exactly. In sentences 9, 12, 17, and 21,
where our system produced a tertiary boundary at the
location of the human speakers&apos; primary phrase boundary,
comprehensibility has not been diminished. The listener is
misled only in sentence 17, where our system generated a
boundary at a location different from that of the human
speakers. In the system&apos;s phrasing of 17, the boundary
before books corresponds to an interpretation of the utter-
ance in which the books are written by her uncle, which,
while it is a possible phrasing, presumes a specific discourse
setting.
A comparison of the secondary phrase boundaries in
Appendix A shows similar correspondences. The human
speakers produced 26 secondary phrase boundaries. The
</bodyText>
<figure confidence="0.98388">
V-phph
V-phph
PP-phph
NP-phph
PP-phph
for+several days
</figure>
<page confidence="0.917194">
166 Computational Linguistics Volume 16, Number 3, September 1990
</page>
<note confidence="0.707647">
J. Bachenko and E. Fitzpatrick Discourse-Neutral Prosodic Phrasing in English
</note>
<bodyText confidence="0.99992614">
system matched 11 exactly and 12 with a primary or
tertiary boundary. It thus failed to match 3 secondary
boundaries, in sentences 9, 18, and 20, but only in sentence
18 is the absence of the boundary misleading.
To sum up, there are 2 boundaries out of the 57 produced
by the human speakers whose absence in the system&apos;s
output is truly problematic. Evaluation of the prosodic
phrase system, however, must also consider cases of overgen-
eration. It is significant here that in the 21 sentences of
Appendix A, the system never generated a primary phrase
boundary that did not correspond to a boundary in the
human productions, although the system overgenerated
secondary phrase boundaries at 7 locations. (We ignore the
overgeneration of tertiary boundaries as perceptually insig-
nificant.) Three of these secondary boundaries are problem-
atic. Those in sentences 17 and 18 were discussed above as
resulting from the misplacement of a boundary. The other
unwanted secondary boundary occurs after was in sentence
10 and results in an utterance that, like 38, is difficult to
process.
A comparison of our system&apos;s output with G &amp;G&apos;s produc-
tions, given in Appendix B, shows similar results. Of the 14
primary phrase boundaries in G&amp;G&apos;s sentences, the system
matched 12 exactly. There were 2 primary boundaries,
however, that the system missed completely. Both of these
errors were due to the presence of a sentential subject. For
sentence 6, no parse was produced, but otherwise the
inability of our system to generate the correct result here
stems from the fact that the system discards the syntactic
sentence node in the derivation of the prosodic phrasing.15
With respect to overgeneration of phrase boundaries, the
system overgenerated seriously only once, in sentence 4,
where the subject is sentential.
We find these results encouraging; with respect to match-
ing, there were only four significant problems in the two
corpora, and overgeneration of a primary boundary oc-
curred only once. The suitability of our system for speech
applications will depend on future tests to determine whether
listeners prefer &amp;quot;prosodized speech&amp;quot; that is imperfect, i.e.,
speech that will have some phrasing errors, to the relatively
&amp;quot;flat&amp;quot; speech of systems that lack our phrasing rules. The
weak link in our current system is the parser: most prob-
lems with phrasing arise from parsing errors; in particular,
incorrect part of speech assignment, incorrect analysis of
pre-head modifiers, and failure to recognize idiomatic or
semi-idiomatic expressions. Problems with the prosody rules
come mainly from phenomena that we have not adequately
studied, e.g. the proper treatment of material on the left
periphery of a prosodic verb phrase and the status of
complements to nouns and adjectives.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.999961" genericHeader="conclusions">
4 CONCLUSIONS
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999987769230769">
We have discussed the notion of discourse neutral prosodic
phrasing in English and presented an analysis that charac-
terizes this phrasing in terms of constituency, adjacency,
and length. In our analysis, the contribution of syntax to
discourse-neutral phrasing consists of lexical categoriza-
tion; NP, PP, and AdjP constituency; and syntactic head
identification. Length is an independent phonological fac-
tor. Because they refer to both syntactic and phonological
information, phrasing rules are free to generate prosodic
structures that may or may not resemble syntactic struc-
tures. Hence, in speech, it is possible but not expected that
phrase boundaries will co-occur with major syntactic bound-
aries.
Our results suggest that, in an implemented system, the
parsing requirements for speech systems are quite different
from those for systems providing information retrieval,
machine translation, or text generation. In particular, there
seems to be no need for a parser to identify VP and S
constituents, nor to specify predicate-argument relations.
The distribution of the phrasing of clause-final PPs given
in Figure 4 may indicate the extent of the relation between
the discourse neutral phrasing and the phrasing imposed by
discourse. We assume that discourse phrasing may shift
neutral boundaries in order to reflect, for example, empha-
sis, contrast, parallelism, coreference, and the particular
structure of the discourse. The exact connection between
the level of phrasing we describe and discourse-dependent
phrasing is a question for future research. We need to know
what aspects of the discourse are relevant for phrasing, as
well as how the discourse information and the phrasing
specifications should be related. For example, it is not clear
whether the discourse-neutral phrasing represents a set of
pre-determined values that are reset when necessary by
discourse features or whether this is a true default situation
in which the discourse neutral phrasing is inserted when
discourse phrasing is underspecified. Any contribution in
this area will greatly enhance our understanding of the
relation between the various components of the grammar—
syntactic, semantic, and phonological.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.996162" genericHeader="acknowledgments">
ACKNOWLEDGMENTS
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999931142857143">
We are grateful to Francois Grosjean and Terry Langendoen for their
comments on an earlier version of this paper, and to Jack Lacy for his
invaluable assistance with the implementation and testing of the system.
Special thanks go to two anonymous Computational Linguistics reviewers
whose comments have greatly helped us improve the original manuscript.
None of those mentioned is responsible for any shortcomings of the work
described here.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.999122" genericHeader="references">
REFERENCES
</sectionHeader>
<reference confidence="0.984265632653062">
Allen, G. 1975 Speech Rhythm: Its Relation to Performance Universals
and Articulatory Timing. Journal of Phonetics 3: 75-86.
Allen, J. 1976 Synthesis of Speech from Unrestricted Text. Proceedings
of the IEEE 4: 433-442.
Bachenko, J.; Hindle, D.; and Fitzpatrick, E. 1983 Constraining a Deter-
ministic Parser. Proceedings of the National Conference on Artificial
Intelligence (AAAI-83).
Bachenko, J.; Fitzpatrick, E.; and Wright, C. E. 1986 The Contribution of
Parsing to Prosodic Phrasing in an Experimental Text-to-Speech Sys-
tem. Proceedings of the 24th Annual Meeting of the Association for
Computational Linguistics, 145-153.
Computational Linguistics Volume 16, Number 3, September 1990 167
J. Bachenko and E. Fitzpatrick Discourse-Neutral Prosodic Phrasing in English
Bierwisch, M. 1966 Regeln fur die Intonation deutscher Satze. In: Bier-
wisch, M. (ed.), Studia Grammatica VII: Untersuchungen uber Akzent
und Intonation im Deutschen. Akademie-Verlag, Berlin: 99-201.
Bing, J. 1985 Aspects of Prosody. Garland Press, New York, New York.
Cahn, J. 1988 From Sad to Glad: Emotional Computer Voices. Proceed-
ings of Speech Tech &apos;88: 35-36.
Chomsky, N. 1965 Aspects of the Theory of Syntax. MIT Press, Cam-
bridge, MA.
Chomsky, N. and Halle, M. 1968 The Sound Pattern of English. Harper
&amp; Row, New York, New York.
Church, K. 1988 A Stochastic Parts Program and Noun Phrase Parser for
Unrestricted Text. Proceedings of the Second Conference on Applied
Natural Language Processing (ACL): 136-143.
Cooper, W. E. 1976 Syntactic Control of Timing in Speech Production: A
Study of Complement Clauses. Journal of Phonetics 4: 151-171.
Cooper, W. and Paccia-Cooper, J. 1980 Syntax and Speech. Harvard
University Press, Cambridge, MA.
Crystal, D. 1969 Prosodic Systems and Intonation in English. Cambridge
University Press, Cambridge, U.K.
Dommergues, J.-Y. and Grosjean, F. 1981 Performance Structures in the
Recall of Sentences. Memory and Cognition 9: 478-486.
Downing, B. 1970 Syntactic Structure and Phonological Phrasing in
English. Ph.D. Dissertation, University of Texas, Austin, TX.
Elovitz, H.; Johnson, R.; McHugh, A.; and Shore, J. E. 1976 Letter-to-
Sound Rules for Automatic Translation of English Text to Phonetics.
IEEE Transactions on Acoustics, Speech, and Signal Processing 6: 446-
459.
Emorine, 0. M. and Martin, P. M. 1988 The Multivoc Text-to-Speech
System. Proceedings of the Second Conference on Applied Natural
Language Processing (ACL): 115-120.
Fitzpatrick, E. 1989 The Preferred Prosodic Phrasing of Prepositional
Phrases. Unpublished data.
Fitzpatrick, E. and Bachenko, J. 1989 Parsing for Prosody: What a
Text-to-Speech System Needs from Syntax. Proceedings of IEEE
Artificial Intelligence Systems in Government (AISIG) &apos;89.
Gee, J. P. and Grosjean, F. 1983 Performance Structures: A Psycholinguis-
tic and Linguistic Appraisal. Cognitive Psychology 15:411-458.
Grosjean, F. and Gee, J. P. 1987 Prosodic Structure and Spoken Word
Recognition. Cognition 25: 135-155.
Grosjean, F.; Grosjean, L.; and Lane, H. 1979 The Patterns of Silence:
Performance Structures in Sentence Production. Cognitive Psychology
11:58-81.
Hillinger, M.; James, C. T.; Zell, D. L.; and Prato, L. M. 1976 The
Influence of Prescriptive and Subjective Phrase Markers on Retrieval
Latencies. Bulletin of the Psychonomic Society 8: 353-355.
Hindle, D. 1983 User Manual for Fidditch, a Deterministic Parser. NRL
Technical Memorandum #7590-142.
Hirschberg, J. and Litman, D. 1987 Now Let&apos;s Talk About Now: Identify-
ing Cue Phrases Intonationally. Proceedings of the 25th Annual Meet-
ing of the Association for Computational Linguistics, 163-171
Klatt, D. H. 1987 Review of Text-to-Speech Conversion for English.
Journal of the Acoustic Society of America 82: 737-793.
Klatt, D. H. 1975 Vowel Lengthening Is Syntactically Determined in
Connected Discourse. Journal of Phonetics 3: 129-140.
Koster, Jan. 1978 Why Subject Ss Don&apos;t Exist. In: Keyser, Samuel J.
Recent Transformational Studies in European Languages. Linguistic
Inquiry Monograph 3. MIT Press, Cambridge, MA.
Langendoen, D. T. 1975 Finite-State Parsing of Phrase-Structure Lan-
guages and the Status of Readjustment Rules in Grammar. Linguistic
Inquiry 6: 533-554.
Litman, D. and Hirschberg, J. 1990. Disambiguating Cue Phrases in Text
and Speech. Proceedings of the 13th International Conference on
Computational Linguistics (COLING).
Liberman, M. Y. and Prince, A. 1977 On Stress and Linguistic Rhythm.
Linguistic Inquiry 8: 249-336.
Luce, P. A.; Feustel, T. C.; and Pisoni, D. B. 1983 Capacity Demands in
Short-Term Memory for Synthetic and Natural Speech. Human Fac-
tors 25: 17-32.
Martin. E. 1970 Toward an Analysis of Subjective Phrase Structure.
Psychological Bulletin 74: 153-166.
Nespor., M. and Vogel, I. 1986 Prosodic Phonology. Foris Publications,
Dordrecht, The Netherlands.
Olive, S. P. and Liberman, M. Y. 1985 Text-to-Speech-An Overview.
Journal of the Acoustic Society of America, Supplement 1: 78, S6.
O&apos;Shaughnessy, D. D. 1989 Parsing with a Small Dictionary for Applica-
tions st.ch as Text-to-Speech. Computational Linguistics 15: 97-108.
Pierrehurnbert, J. B. 1980 The Phonetics and Phonology of English
Intonation. Ph.D. Dissertation, MIT, Cambridge, MA.
Selkirk, E. 0. 1984 Phonology and Syntax: The Relation between Sound
and Structure. MIT Press, Cambridge, MA.
Sproat, R. W. and Liberman, M. Y. 1987 Toward Treating English
Nominals Correctly. Proceedings of the 25th Annual Meeting of the
Association for Computational Linguistics, 140-146.
Streeter, L. A. 1978 Acoustic Determinants of Boundary Perception.
Journal of the Acoustical Society of America 64: 1582-1592.
</reference>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.830409" genericHeader="references">
APPENDIX A
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.416931333333333">
Human (H) and system (S) productions of syntactically
varied sentences. Primary boundaries are marked by &amp;quot;I&amp;quot;,
secondary by &amp;quot;I &amp;quot;, tertiary by &amp;quot;!&amp;quot;.
</bodyText>
<listItem confidence="0.5020052">
1. H: The name I of the character II is not pronounced.
S: The name! of the character I is not pronounced.
2. H: The left-hand power unit ! on each shelf I in the
forty-eight channel module ll operates! the echo cancel-
lers.
</listItem>
<construct confidence="0.983255428571429">
S: The left-hand power unit I on each shelf I in the
forty-eight channel module II operates I the echo can-
cellers.
3. 1-1: Phoneme characters II give more control II over the
particular sounds il that are generated.
S: Phoneme characters I give! more control I over the
particular sounds II that are generated.
</construct>
<reference confidence="0.974421541666667">
4. H: The connection must be determined II for the left-
hand power unit II on each shelf
S: The connection ! must be determined I for the
left-hand power unit Ion each shelf
5. H: I need a man II to fix the sink.
S: I need a man I to fix ! the sink.
6. H: The techniques I that we had implemented II were
tested I on a larger computer.
S: The techniques I that we had implemented II were
tested I on a larger! computer.
7. H: Everyone I who had participated I in the attempt II
was considerably affected.
S: Everyone I who had participated! in the attempt II
was considerably affected.
8. H: The method I by which one converts a word I into
phonemes II is provided I in chapter seven.
S: The method I by which one converts ! a word I into
phonemes II is provided! in chapter seven.
9. FL In these instances II it may be desirable I to use
phonemic characters!! each time I that it appears II on
the input text.
S: In these ! instances I it may be ! desirable!! to use!
phonemic characters II each time that it appears ! on
the input text.
</reference>
<page confidence="0.844837">
168 Computational Linguistics Volume 16, Number 3, September 1990
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.851105">
J. Bachenko and E. Fitzpatrick Discourse-Neutral Prosodic Phrasing in English
Test sentences used by G&amp;G with their prosodic marking
converted to our notation. S represents our system&apos;s produc-
tions, G&amp;G represents the human productions.
</bodyText>
<figure confidence="0.940546">
10. H: The thrust I was now from the south II which
Mallory had deemed impossible.
S: The thrust I was I now ! from the south II which
Mallory I had deemed! impossible.
11. H: The destruction I of the good name I of his fatherll
bothered him.
S: The destruction I of the good name ! of his fatheril
bothered him.
12. H: Every event I of that dreadful time II is seared Ii into
my memory.
S: Every! event I of that! dreadful time II is seared!
into my memory.
13. H: Everest was discovered II during a survey of India II
in 1852.
S: Everest was discovered II during a survey! of India I
in 1852.
14. H: He told the director II to give the names I of the
characters to Ivan.
S: He told ! the director II to give I the names ! of the
characters I to Ivan.
15. H: It may be impossible II to give that machine II the
proper workout.
S: It may be ! impossible II to give that machine I the
proper workout.
16. H: Eventually I he will realize II that his cigars are
botheringli the other passengers.
S: Eventually II he will realize ! that his cigars I are
bothering! the other passengers.
17. H: She was given I more difficult booksilby her uncle.
S: She was given! more difficult I books by her uncle.
18. H: You could easily I break that vase II if you aren&apos;t 1
careful.
S: You could easily break I that! vase II if you aren&apos;t
careful.
19. H: The president I asked the group II what they were
capable I of doing.
S: The president I asked! the groupilwhat they were I
capable! of doing.
20. H: What book I on the subjectilwould you recommend
I to the group?
S: What book ! on the subjectilwould you recommend
to the group?
21. H: I can usually read I a lot faster II than Roger.
S: I can usually read I a lot faster! than Roger.
</figure>
<figureCaption confidence="0.5793655">
1. S: When the new lawyer I called up ! Reynolds lithe
plan! was discussed! thoroughly.
G&amp;G: When the new lawyer! called up Reynoldsli the
plan! was discussed I thoroughly.
2. S: In addition! to his filesil the lawyer! brought I the
office&apos;s best adding machine.
</figureCaption>
<figure confidence="0.8219320625">
APPENDIX B
G&amp;G: In addition! to his files lithe lawyer brought I
the office&apos;s! best! adding machine.
3. S: By making! his plan I known ii he brought out I the
objections! of everyone.
G&amp;G: By making! his plan known!! he brought out I
the objections ! of everyone.
4. S: That a solution II couldn&apos;t be found seemed I quite
clear II to them.
G&amp;G: That a solution ! couldn&apos;t be found II seemed!
quite clear I to them.
5. S: Not quite all! of the recent files II were examined I
that ! day.
G&amp;G: Not quite ! all I of the recent ! files II were
examined! that day.
6. S: Too many parse problems
</figure>
<figureCaption confidence="0.59055025">
G&amp;G: That! the matter! was dealt with I so fast was
a shock! to him.
7. S: John ! asked I the strange ! young! man ii to be!
quick II on the task.
</figureCaption>
<bodyText confidence="0.725594302325582">
G&amp;G: John! asked! the
quick I on the task.
8. S: Closing ! his client&apos;s ! book lithe young expert I
wondered! about this! extraordinary story.
G&amp;G: Closing his client&apos;s book lithe young expert I
wondered about! this ! extraordinary story.
9. S: Parse problems with wh trace in infinitival relatives;
change wording slightly: The expert I who didn&apos;t know
! what to tell us II sat back! in despair.
G&amp;G: The expert I who couldn&apos;t see! what to criticize
II sat back! in despair.
0. S: After the cold winter! of that year II most people I
were! totally fed up.
G&amp;G: After the cold winter
people! were totally !fed up.
11. S: The agent I consulted! the agency&apos;s book ii in which
they offered! numerous tours.
G&amp;G: The agent I consulted! the agency&apos;s book II in
which! they offered numerous tours.
12. S: Parse problems with surprisingly and the main verb;
change wording slightly: She discussed I the pros and
cons to overcome I surprisingly apprehensive feel-
ings.
G&amp;G: She discussed! the pros and cons II to get over
her surprisingly I apprehensive! feelings.
13. S: Our disappointed woman I lost ! her optimism ii
since the prospects! were too limited.
G&amp;G: Our disappointed woman I lost her! optimism Ii
since the prospects! were too limited.
14. S: Since she was ! indecisive ! that day II her friend I
asked her to wait.
G&amp;G: Since ! she was I indecisive I that day II her
friend! asked her to wait.
1. Bachenko et al. (1983) outlines the main features of the syntactic
framework we assume. Any syntactic approach that provides the
NOTES
strange young man II to be
I of that year II most
Computational Linguistics Volume 16, Number 3, September 1990 169
J. Bachenko and E. Fitzpatrick Discourse-Neutral Prosodic Phrasing in English
lexical and constituent information discussed in Section 2 should be
sufficient for the phrasing analysis we present, but this idea remains
to be explored.
</bodyText>
<reference confidence="0.999563137254902">
2. e.g. Cooper (1976), Cooper and Paccia-Cooper (1980), Klatt (1975),
and Streeter (1978). Downing (1970), like Langendoen, explicitly
assumes a direct connection between syntax and prosodic phrasing
with &amp;quot;some aspects at least of surface structure . . . determined
exclusively by the necessity of providing input to the phonological
rules that specify prosodic features&amp;quot; (p. 204).
3. In characterizing this phrasing as discourse-neutral, we are assum-
ing, contra Bing, that length is independent of discourse.
4. Both examples are from Martin (1970). Bierwisch (1966) also
includes length, in terms of stressed syllable count, as a factor in the
prosodic phrasing of German auxiliary + verb strings. Length as a
factor in prosodic phrasing is mentioned in Selkirk (1984) and
Nespor and Vogel (1986), but without any systematic account of its
effects.
5. G &amp;G&apos;s test corpus consists of 14 sentences that were originally used
in Grosjean et al. (1979).
6. A more accurate account of adjunction, such as that in Selkirk
(1984), would limit the list of adjoinable words to those that have
both a strong and a weak form. For example, the word him in see
him may be realized as the strong form [him], where the vowel
carries stress, or it may take the weak unstressed form [m]. This
word is therefore a candidate for adjunction. In contrast, a preposi-
tion such as among has no weak form and would be nonadjoinable.
Results that we discuss below support this approach. Our current
system, however, relies solely on lexical category and tree structure
to identify adjunction possibilities.
7. These are essentially the phi phrases of G &amp;G.
8. Below, in the discussion of constituent length, we will claim that
word count should actually be stressed syllable count. In the current
system, however, length depends on phonological word count.
9. Problems with final phrase boundaries are discussed in more detail
in Bachenko et al. (1986), where the analysis presented assumes the
version of final bundling proposed in G &amp;G. We return to this type of
example below.
10. Prosodic events finer than the pause were marked but ignored for
this study. A stress foot contains one stressed syllable and zero or
more unstressed syllables. In our current implementation, length is
measured by phonological word count, since stress foot information
is not readily available to us.
11. Conjunctions of lexical items, e.g. some subtle and horrible crime,
these windows and shutters, are rarely split into two phrases.
12. Klatt (1987) presents a useful review of text-to-speech technology
and performance.
13. Fitzpatrick and Bachenko (1989) provide a more detailed discussion
of the differences between parsing for speech and parsing for text
understanding.
14. Hindle (1983); lexical lookup and category disambiguation are done
by the stochastic parser described in Church (1988).
15. We have as yet no account of pre-verbal embedded sentences,
though an analysis that does not involve an embedded S node is
available (Koster, 1978).
</reference>
<page confidence="0.879962">
170 Computational Linguistics Volume 16, Number 3, September 1990
</page>
</variant>
</algorithm>
<algorithm name="ParsHed" version="110505">
<variant no="0" confidence="0.971766">
<title confidence="0.9919355">A COMPUTATIONAL GRAMMAR OF DISCOURSE-NEUTRAL PHRASING IN ENGLISH</title>
<author confidence="0.999992">J Bachenko</author>
<author confidence="0.999992">E Fitzpatrick</author>
<affiliation confidence="0.996392">AT &amp; T Bell</affiliation>
<address confidence="0.999661">Murray Hill, NJ 07974</address>
<abstract confidence="0.9984665">We describe an experimental text-to-speech system that uses information about syntactic constituency, adjacency to a verb, and constituent length to determine prosodic phrasing for synthetic speech. A central goal of our work has been to characterize &amp;quot;discourse neutral&amp;quot; phrasing, i.e. sentence-level phrasing patterns that are independent of discourse semantics. Our account builds on Bachenko et al. (1986), but differs in its treatment of clausal structure and predicate-argument relations. Results so far indicate that the current system performs well when measured against a corpus of judgments of prosodic phrasing.</abstract>
</variant>
</algorithm>
<algorithm name="ParsCit" version="110505">
<citationList>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>G Allen</author>
</authors>
<title>Speech Rhythm: Its Relation to Performance Universals and Articulatory Timing.</title>
<date>1975</date>
<journal>Journal of Phonetics</journal>
<volume>3</volume>
<pages>75--86</pages>
<contexts>
<context position="16618" citStr="Allen (1975)" startWordPosition="2645" endWordPosition="2646">d we found only 14 percent of the phrases to be discourse-determined. The identification of a preferred phrasing that is independent of discourse also aids us in identifying and characterizing the discourse features that impinge on prosodic phrasing. Several well-known discourse phenomena—coreference, contrast, and parallelism—affected the phrasing of the clause final prepositional phrases in our corpus. We are left with three or four unexplained cases that are suggestive of a discourse explanation. 2.1.3 PHONOLOGICAL LENGTH AND PROSODIC PHRASING The psycholinguistic studies of Martin (1970), Allen (1975), Hillinger et al. (1976), Grosjean et al. (1979), Dommergues and Grosjean (1983), and Gee and Grosjean (1983), responding to the idea of readjusted syntax as the source of prosodic phrasing, show that grammatical structure, even if readjusted, is not in itself a reliable predictor of prosodic phrasing: mismatches between syntax and prosody occur often and systematically, and can be related to specific nonsyntactic factors such as length and word frequency. For example, although prosodic boundaries between subject and verb do occur, there also exist prosodic patterns in which the boundary come</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Allen, 1975</marker>
<rawString>Allen, G. 1975 Speech Rhythm: Its Relation to Performance Universals and Articulatory Timing. Journal of Phonetics 3: 75-86.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>J Allen</author>
</authors>
<title>Synthesis of Speech from Unrestricted Text.</title>
<date>1976</date>
<journal>Proceedings of the IEEE</journal>
<volume>4</volume>
<pages>433--442</pages>
<contexts>
<context position="47094" citStr="Allen 1976" startWordPosition="7806" endWordPosition="7807">e and Liberman 1985). Two concerns motivated our implementation. First, we hoped the system would provide us with a research tool for testing our ideas about syntax and phrasing against a large unrestricted collection of sentences. Second, we wished to investigate how well our approach would work for determining prosodic phrasing in a text-to-speech synthesizer. Existing text-to-speech systems perform well on word pronunciation and short sentences,12 but when it comes to long sentences and paragraphs, synthetic speech tends to be difficult to listen to and understand. Many investigators (e.g. Allen 1976; Elowitz et al. 1976; Luce et al. 1983; Cahn 1988) have suggested that the poor prosody of synthetic speech, in comparison with natural speech, is the primary factor leading to difficulties in the comprehension of fluent synthetic speech. And while researchers in text-tospeech synthesis have adopted a variety of approaches to prosodic phrase generation—from the simple punctuationbased rules and function word listings of existing commercial systems to the sophisticated prosodic heuristics described in Emorine and Martin (1988) and O&apos;Shaughnessy (1989)--the generation of appropriate prosodic ph</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Allen, 1976</marker>
<rawString>Allen, J. 1976 Synthesis of Speech from Unrestricted Text. Proceedings of the IEEE 4: 433-442.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>J Bachenko</author>
<author>D Hindle</author>
<author>E Fitzpatrick</author>
</authors>
<title>Constraining a Deterministic Parser.</title>
<date>1983</date>
<booktitle>Proceedings of the National Conference on Artificial Intelligence (AAAI-83).</booktitle>
<marker>Bachenko, Hindle, Fitzpatrick, 1983</marker>
<rawString>Bachenko, J.; Hindle, D.; and Fitzpatrick, E. 1983 Constraining a Deterministic Parser. Proceedings of the National Conference on Artificial Intelligence (AAAI-83).</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>J Bachenko</author>
<author>E Fitzpatrick</author>
<author>C E Wright</author>
</authors>
<title>The Contribution of Parsing to Prosodic Phrasing in an Experimental Text-to-Speech System.</title>
<date>1986</date>
<booktitle>Proceedings of the 24th Annual Meeting of the Association for Computational Linguistics,</booktitle>
<pages>145--153</pages>
<contexts>
<context position="828" citStr="Bachenko et al. 1986" startWordPosition="116" endWordPosition="119">uses information about syntactic constituency, adjacency to a verb, and constituent length to determine prosodic phrasing for synthetic speech. A central goal of our work has been to characterize &amp;quot;discourse neutral&amp;quot; phrasing, i.e. sentence-level phrasing patterns that are independent of discourse semantics. Our account builds on Bachenko et al. (1986), but differs in its treatment of clausal structure and predicate-argument relations. Results so far indicate that the current system performs well when measured against a corpus of judgments of prosodic phrasing. 1 INTRODUCTION In previous work (Bachenko et al. 1986), we described an experimental text-to-speech system that determined prosodic phrasing for the Olive—Liberman synthesizer (Olive and Liberman 1985). The system generated phrase boundaries using information derived from the syntactic structure of a sentence. While we saw significant improvements in the resulting synthesized speech, we also observed problems with the system. Often these stemmed from our assumptions that both clausal structure and predicateargument relations were important in determining prosodic phrasing. This paper reconsiders those assumptions and describes an analysis of phra</context>
<context position="12255" citStr="Bachenko et al. (1986)" startWordPosition="1946" endWordPosition="1949">sodic phrase boundary determination. 2.1.2 SEMANTICS AND PROSODIC PHRASING The syntax/prosody misalignment may be viewed as resulting in part from semantic considerations. Both predicateargument relations and discourse factors have been examined for their possible input to prosodic phrasing. Crystal (1969) claims that prosodic phrase boundaries will co-occur with grammatical functions such as subject, predicate, modifier, and adjunct. Selkirk (1984) and Nespor and Vogel (1986) take a similar approach, but within a different theoretical framework. Previous versions of our work, as described in Bachenko et al. (1986) also assume that phrasing is dependent on predicate-argument structure. The problem here is that the phrasing in observed data often ignores the argument status of constituents. In 17a—f, for example, the phrasing makes no distinction between arguments and adjuncts. All of the sentences have the same X(VY) pattern even though Y is a complement in the first case (the first serious attempt) and an adjunct in the others. (The complement in 17a and the adjuncts in 17b—f are italicized.) 17. a. A British expedition il launched the first serious attempt. b. A single bright light II shone out from t</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Bachenko, Fitzpatrick, Wright, 1986</marker>
<rawString>Bachenko, J.; Fitzpatrick, E.; and Wright, C. E. 1986 The Contribution of Parsing to Prosodic Phrasing in an Experimental Text-to-Speech System. Proceedings of the 24th Annual Meeting of the Association for Computational Linguistics, 145-153.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>J Bachenko</author>
<author>E</author>
</authors>
<title>Fitzpatrick Discourse-Neutral Prosodic Phrasing</title>
<date>1990</date>
<volume>16</volume>
<institution>Computational Linguistics</institution>
<note>in English</note>
<marker>Bachenko, E, 1990</marker>
<rawString>Computational Linguistics Volume 16, Number 3, September 1990 167 J. Bachenko and E. Fitzpatrick Discourse-Neutral Prosodic Phrasing in English</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>M Bierwisch</author>
</authors>
<title>Regeln fur die Intonation deutscher Satze.</title>
<date>1966</date>
<booktitle>Studia Grammatica VII: Untersuchungen uber Akzent und Intonation im Deutschen.</booktitle>
<pages>99--201</pages>
<editor>In: Bierwisch, M. (ed.),</editor>
<publisher>Akademie-Verlag,</publisher>
<location>Berlin:</location>
<marker>Bierwisch, 1966</marker>
<rawString>Bierwisch, M. 1966 Regeln fur die Intonation deutscher Satze. In: Bierwisch, M. (ed.), Studia Grammatica VII: Untersuchungen uber Akzent und Intonation im Deutschen. Akademie-Verlag, Berlin: 99-201.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>J Bing</author>
</authors>
<title>Aspects of Prosody.</title>
<date>1985</date>
<publisher>Garland Press,</publisher>
<location>New York, New York.</location>
<contexts>
<context position="13199" citStr="Bing (1985)" startWordPosition="2115" endWordPosition="2116"> a complement in the first case (the first serious attempt) and an adjunct in the others. (The complement in 17a and the adjuncts in 17b—f are italicized.) 17. a. A British expedition il launched the first serious attempt. b. A single bright light II shone out from the darkness. c. There were several little changes II carried out about that time. d. Were there any gypsies II camping in the plantation. . . . e. . . like the claws of a crab II thrown out on each side. f. Two years II have passed since then. The relation between discourse and prosodic phrasing has been examined in some detail by Bing (1985), who argues that each noun phrase in an utterance constitutes a separate prosodic phrase unless it is destressed because of reference to previous discourse. Bing also observes that constituents that refer to items newly introduced into a discourse tend to be longer. This may be the reason that word count and syllable count play a prominent role in prosodic phrasing (see Section 2.1.3.). To our knowledge, no work has explicitly explored the relation between the length of a constituent and its status in the discourse. Hirschberg and Litman (1987) and Litman and Hirschberg (1990) also examine th</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Bing, 1985</marker>
<rawString>Bing, J. 1985 Aspects of Prosody. Garland Press, New York, New York.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>J Cahn</author>
</authors>
<title>From Sad to Glad: Emotional Computer Voices.</title>
<date>1988</date>
<journal>Proceedings of Speech Tech</journal>
<volume>88</volume>
<pages>35--36</pages>
<contexts>
<context position="47145" citStr="Cahn 1988" startWordPosition="7816" endWordPosition="7817">plementation. First, we hoped the system would provide us with a research tool for testing our ideas about syntax and phrasing against a large unrestricted collection of sentences. Second, we wished to investigate how well our approach would work for determining prosodic phrasing in a text-to-speech synthesizer. Existing text-to-speech systems perform well on word pronunciation and short sentences,12 but when it comes to long sentences and paragraphs, synthetic speech tends to be difficult to listen to and understand. Many investigators (e.g. Allen 1976; Elowitz et al. 1976; Luce et al. 1983; Cahn 1988) have suggested that the poor prosody of synthetic speech, in comparison with natural speech, is the primary factor leading to difficulties in the comprehension of fluent synthetic speech. And while researchers in text-tospeech synthesis have adopted a variety of approaches to prosodic phrase generation—from the simple punctuationbased rules and function word listings of existing commercial systems to the sophisticated prosodic heuristics described in Emorine and Martin (1988) and O&apos;Shaughnessy (1989)--the generation of appropriate prosodic phrasing in unrestricted text has remained a problem.</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Cahn, 1988</marker>
<rawString>Cahn, J. 1988 From Sad to Glad: Emotional Computer Voices. Proceedings of Speech Tech &apos;88: 35-36.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>N Chomsky</author>
</authors>
<title>Aspects of the Theory of Syntax.</title>
<date>1965</date>
<publisher>MIT Press,</publisher>
<location>Cambridge, MA.</location>
<contexts>
<context position="7083" citStr="Chomsky (1965)" startWordPosition="1114" endWordPosition="1115">e below, that a sequence of words dominated by the same syntactic node cohere more closely than a sequence of words dominated by two different nodes. This observation has led some researchers, e.g., Cooper and Paccia-Cooper (1980), to claim a direct mapping between the syntactic phrase and the prosodic phrase. However, this claim is controversial because of the misa:ignments that occur between the two levels of phrasing. For example, in considering the connection between syntax and phrasing, the linguistic literature most often refers to examples of embedded sentences. Sentences like 12, from Chomsky (1965), are frequently cited. (Square brackets mark off the NP constituents that contain embedded sentences.) 12. This is [Nip the cat that caught [NI, the rat that stole [NI, the cheese] ] ] In such cases, the syntactic constituency indicated by bracketing is not in alignment with the prosodic phrasing. Instead, 12 has the prosodic phrasing in 13a. The phrasing in 13b, which most closely matches constituency, is strange at best. (In these and other examples, the most prominent prosodic boundaries are marked by vertical bars.) 13. a. This is the cat il that caught the rat II that stole the cheese, b</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Chomsky, 1965</marker>
<rawString>Chomsky, N. 1965 Aspects of the Theory of Syntax. MIT Press, Cambridge, MA.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>N Chomsky</author>
<author>M Halle</author>
</authors>
<title>The Sound Pattern of English.</title>
<date>1968</date>
<publisher>Harper &amp; Row,</publisher>
<location>New York, New York.</location>
<contexts>
<context position="8036" citStr="Chomsky and Halle (1968)" startWordPosition="1272" endWordPosition="1275">phrasing in 13a. The phrasing in 13b, which most closely matches constituency, is strange at best. (In these and other examples, the most prominent prosodic boundaries are marked by vertical bars.) 13. a. This is the cat il that caught the rat II that stole the cheese, b. ??This is lithe cat that caught lithe rat that stole il he cheese. To account for such mismatches, &amp;quot;readjustment rules&amp;quot; that change constituent structure by adjoining each embedded sentence to the node dominating it have been posited. The result is a flattened structure that more accurately reflects the prosodic phrasing. In Chomsky and Halle (1968), this flattening process is not part of the grammar. Rather, it is viewed as &amp;quot;. . a performance factor, related to the difficulty of producing right branching structures such as [12]&amp;quot; (p. 372). Thus phrasing, in their approach, is only indirectly related to syntax, since readjustment is done by special rules outside the grammar proper. Langendoen (1975) proposes readjustment rules similar to those of Chomsky and Halle, but he claims that the readjustment of structure is part of the grammar, not part of the performance model. He thus makes explicit what is often a tacit assumption in both the </context>
</contexts>
<marker>Chomsky, Halle, 1968</marker>
<rawString>Chomsky, N. and Halle, M. 1968 The Sound Pattern of English. Harper &amp; Row, New York, New York.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>K Church</author>
</authors>
<title>A Stochastic Parts Program and Noun Phrase Parser for Unrestricted Text.</title>
<date>1988</date>
<booktitle>Proceedings of the Second Conference on Applied Natural Language Processing (ACL):</booktitle>
<pages>136--143</pages>
<marker>Church, 1988</marker>
<rawString>Church, K. 1988 A Stochastic Parts Program and Noun Phrase Parser for Unrestricted Text. Proceedings of the Second Conference on Applied Natural Language Processing (ACL): 136-143.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>W E Cooper</author>
</authors>
<title>Syntactic Control of Timing in Speech Production: A Study of Complement Clauses.</title>
<date>1976</date>
<journal>Journal of Phonetics</journal>
<volume>4</volume>
<pages>151--171</pages>
<marker>Cooper, 1976</marker>
<rawString>Cooper, W. E. 1976 Syntactic Control of Timing in Speech Production: A Study of Complement Clauses. Journal of Phonetics 4: 151-171.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>W Cooper</author>
<author>J Paccia-Cooper</author>
</authors>
<title>Syntax and Speech.</title>
<date>1980</date>
<publisher>Harvard University Press,</publisher>
<location>Cambridge, MA.</location>
<contexts>
<context position="6699" citStr="Cooper and Paccia-Cooper (1980)" startWordPosition="1054" endWordPosition="1057"> segment quality. For example, the vowel in the preposition to is normally weak, as in 10. But if a gap like the one that is associated with the question word who in 11 follows the preposition, the vowel of to is strong. 10 We spoke to John. (to pronounced/t/) 11. Who did you speak to? (to pronounced /tu/) When it comes to sentence-level prosody, especially phrasing, it is often true, as we will see below, that a sequence of words dominated by the same syntactic node cohere more closely than a sequence of words dominated by two different nodes. This observation has led some researchers, e.g., Cooper and Paccia-Cooper (1980), to claim a direct mapping between the syntactic phrase and the prosodic phrase. However, this claim is controversial because of the misa:ignments that occur between the two levels of phrasing. For example, in considering the connection between syntax and phrasing, the linguistic literature most often refers to examples of embedded sentences. Sentences like 12, from Chomsky (1965), are frequently cited. (Square brackets mark off the NP constituents that contain embedded sentences.) 12. This is [Nip the cat that caught [NI, the rat that stole [NI, the cheese] ] ] In such cases, the syntactic c</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Cooper, Paccia-Cooper, 1980</marker>
<rawString>Cooper, W. and Paccia-Cooper, J. 1980 Syntax and Speech. Harvard University Press, Cambridge, MA.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>D Crystal</author>
</authors>
<title>Prosodic Systems and Intonation in English.</title>
<date>1969</date>
<publisher>Cambridge University Press,</publisher>
<location>Cambridge, U.K.</location>
<contexts>
<context position="11940" citStr="Crystal (1969)" startWordPosition="1901" endWordPosition="1902">tituents often cohere. Where misalignments between the syntactic and the prosodic phrasing occur, however, the notion of readjusting the syntax to fit the prosody is problematic and, we believe, compares unfavorably with an approach that views the semantic and phonological components as contributing to prosodic phrase boundary determination. 2.1.2 SEMANTICS AND PROSODIC PHRASING The syntax/prosody misalignment may be viewed as resulting in part from semantic considerations. Both predicateargument relations and discourse factors have been examined for their possible input to prosodic phrasing. Crystal (1969) claims that prosodic phrase boundaries will co-occur with grammatical functions such as subject, predicate, modifier, and adjunct. Selkirk (1984) and Nespor and Vogel (1986) take a similar approach, but within a different theoretical framework. Previous versions of our work, as described in Bachenko et al. (1986) also assume that phrasing is dependent on predicate-argument structure. The problem here is that the phrasing in observed data often ignores the argument status of constituents. In 17a—f, for example, the phrasing makes no distinction between arguments and adjuncts. All of the senten</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Crystal, 1969</marker>
<rawString>Crystal, D. 1969 Prosodic Systems and Intonation in English. Cambridge University Press, Cambridge, U.K.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>J-Y Dommergues</author>
<author>F Grosjean</author>
</authors>
<title>Performance Structures in the Recall of Sentences.</title>
<date>1981</date>
<journal>Memory and Cognition</journal>
<volume>9</volume>
<pages>478--486</pages>
<marker>Dommergues, Grosjean, 1981</marker>
<rawString>Dommergues, J.-Y. and Grosjean, F. 1981 Performance Structures in the Recall of Sentences. Memory and Cognition 9: 478-486.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>B Downing</author>
</authors>
<title>Syntactic Structure and Phonological Phrasing in</title>
<date>1970</date>
<institution>English. Ph.D. Dissertation, University of Texas,</institution>
<location>Austin, TX.</location>
<marker>Downing, 1970</marker>
<rawString>Downing, B. 1970 Syntactic Structure and Phonological Phrasing in English. Ph.D. Dissertation, University of Texas, Austin, TX.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>H Elovitz</author>
<author>R Johnson</author>
<author>A McHugh</author>
<author>J E Shore</author>
</authors>
<title>Letter-toSound Rules for Automatic Translation of English Text to Phonetics.</title>
<date>1976</date>
<journal>IEEE Transactions on Acoustics, Speech, and Signal Processing</journal>
<volume>6</volume>
<pages>446--459</pages>
<marker>Elovitz, Johnson, McHugh, Shore, 1976</marker>
<rawString>Elovitz, H.; Johnson, R.; McHugh, A.; and Shore, J. E. 1976 Letter-toSound Rules for Automatic Translation of English Text to Phonetics. IEEE Transactions on Acoustics, Speech, and Signal Processing 6: 446-459.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>M</author>
<author>P M Martin</author>
</authors>
<title>The Multivoc Text-to-Speech System.</title>
<date>1988</date>
<booktitle>Proceedings of the Second Conference on Applied Natural Language Processing (ACL):</booktitle>
<pages>115--120</pages>
<marker>M, Martin, 1988</marker>
<rawString>Emorine, 0. M. and Martin, P. M. 1988 The Multivoc Text-to-Speech System. Proceedings of the Second Conference on Applied Natural Language Processing (ACL): 115-120.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>E Fitzpatrick</author>
</authors>
<title>The Preferred Prosodic Phrasing of Prepositional Phrases.</title>
<date>1989</date>
<note>Unpublished data.</note>
<marker>Fitzpatrick, 1989</marker>
<rawString>Fitzpatrick, E. 1989 The Preferred Prosodic Phrasing of Prepositional Phrases. Unpublished data.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>E Fitzpatrick</author>
<author>J Bachenko</author>
</authors>
<title>Parsing for Prosody: What a Text-to-Speech System Needs from Syntax.</title>
<date>1989</date>
<booktitle>Proceedings of IEEE Artificial Intelligence Systems in Government (AISIG) &apos;89.</booktitle>
<marker>Fitzpatrick, Bachenko, 1989</marker>
<rawString>Fitzpatrick, E. and Bachenko, J. 1989 Parsing for Prosody: What a Text-to-Speech System Needs from Syntax. Proceedings of IEEE Artificial Intelligence Systems in Government (AISIG) &apos;89.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>J P Gee</author>
<author>F Grosjean</author>
</authors>
<title>Performance Structures: A Psycholinguistic and Linguistic Appraisal.</title>
<date>1983</date>
<journal>Cognitive Psychology</journal>
<pages>15--411</pages>
<contexts>
<context position="16728" citStr="Gee and Grosjean (1983)" startWordPosition="2661" endWordPosition="2664">rred phrasing that is independent of discourse also aids us in identifying and characterizing the discourse features that impinge on prosodic phrasing. Several well-known discourse phenomena—coreference, contrast, and parallelism—affected the phrasing of the clause final prepositional phrases in our corpus. We are left with three or four unexplained cases that are suggestive of a discourse explanation. 2.1.3 PHONOLOGICAL LENGTH AND PROSODIC PHRASING The psycholinguistic studies of Martin (1970), Allen (1975), Hillinger et al. (1976), Grosjean et al. (1979), Dommergues and Grosjean (1983), and Gee and Grosjean (1983), responding to the idea of readjusted syntax as the source of prosodic phrasing, show that grammatical structure, even if readjusted, is not in itself a reliable predictor of prosodic phrasing: mismatches between syntax and prosody occur often and systematically, and can be related to specific nonsyntactic factors such as length and word frequency. For example, although prosodic boundaries between subject and verb do occur, there also exist prosodic patterns in which the boundary comes between the verb and object, i.e., the data reveal both X(VY) and (XV)Y groupings. Grosjean et al. (1979) cl</context>
<context position="18144" citStr="Gee and Grosjean (1983)" startWordPosition="2878" endWordPosition="2881">ch when the major constituents of a sentence are roughly equal in length; for example, the main prosodic phrase break corresponds to the subject-predicate boundary in Waiters who remember well II serve orders correctly. Discrepancies in length throw constituents off balance, and so prosodic phrasing will cross constituent boundaries in order to give the phrases similar lengths; this is the case in Chickens were eating II the remaining green vegetables, where the subject-predicate boundary finds no prosodic correspondent.4 The most explicit version of this approach is the analysis presented in Gee and Grosjean (1983) (henceforth G&amp;G). Drawing on the psycholinguistic studies mentioned above and on aspects of the grammar of prosody outlined in Selkirk (1984), G&amp;G propose an algorithm for mapping syntactic structure onto a hierarchical representation of phrasing; the rules they present accomplish this by integrating syntactic information (e.g. constituent structure, left-toright ordering) with information about constituent length. We have found that their rules, which are described in detail, provide a productive model for investigations of phrasing, and in what follows we shall frequently refer to their ana</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Gee, Grosjean, 1983</marker>
<rawString>Gee, J. P. and Grosjean, F. 1983 Performance Structures: A Psycholinguistic and Linguistic Appraisal. Cognitive Psychology 15:411-458.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>F Grosjean</author>
<author>J P Gee</author>
</authors>
<title>Prosodic Structure and Spoken Word Recognition.</title>
<date>1987</date>
<journal>Cognition</journal>
<volume>25</volume>
<pages>135--155</pages>
<contexts>
<context position="22413" citStr="Grosjean and Gee (1987)" startWordPosition="3545" endWordPosition="3548">nd we will mention the third rule class only in passing. 2.2.1 BOUNDARY LOCATION RULES V NP PP We+saw spring+up among+the+trees The location rules identify possible boundary sites by first deriving phonological words from the lexical items in a parse tree, and then grouping the phonological words into larger phonological phrases. The boundaries that separate phonological phrases are the candidates for prosodic phrase boundaries, since the prosodic phrases of speech consist of one or more phonological phrases. Our rules for phonological word formation are adopted, for the most part, from G &amp;G, Grosjean and Gee (1987), and the account of monosyllabic destressing in Selkirk (1984). Thus in our analysis, rules of phonological word formation apply to the non-null terminal nodes in a syntax tree. If the terminal is a content word, i.e. noun, verb, adjective, or adverb, then this terminal may have the status of a phonological word on its own. Otherwise the word combines with one or more orthographically distinct words to form a single phonological word that has no internal word or phrase boundaries. This is accomplished by adjoining a word to its left or right neighbor depending on its lexical category and its </context>
</contexts>
<marker>Grosjean, Gee, 1987</marker>
<rawString>Grosjean, F. and Gee, J. P. 1987 Prosodic Structure and Spoken Word Recognition. Cognition 25: 135-155.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>F Grosjean</author>
<author>L Grosjean</author>
<author>H Lane</author>
</authors>
<title>The Patterns of Silence: Performance Structures in Sentence Production.</title>
<date>1979</date>
<pages>11--58</pages>
<publisher>Cognitive Psychology</publisher>
<contexts>
<context position="2296" citStr="Grosjean et al. (1979)" startWordPosition="332" endWordPosition="335">on and relative strength of prosodic phrase boundaries. Our current analysis rests on two ideas. First, it is possible to describe a level of prosodic phrasing that is independent of discourse semantics. Second, this discourseneutral phrasing depends on a mix of syntactic and nonsyntactic factors; chiefly, syntactic constituency, left-to-right word order, and constituent length. There is no necessary fit between syntactic structure and phrasing, since prosodic phrasing may ignore major syntactic boundaries in order to satisfy the constraints on phrase length. Our approach thus follows that of Grosjean et al. (1979), namely, that phrasing reflects &amp;quot;. . . two (sometimes conflicting) demands on the speaker: the need to respect the linguistic structure of the sentence and the need to balance the length of the constituents in the output&amp;quot; (p. 75). Section 2 will outline our analysis, focusing on the relationship between syntactic and prosodic structure. The analysis is developed within the framework of generative grammar, but we believe it is consistent with other approaches to syntactic description.&apos; Our main point will be that the syntax plays a necessary but not sufficient role in determining phrasing, its</context>
<context position="16667" citStr="Grosjean et al. (1979)" startWordPosition="2651" endWordPosition="2654">es to be discourse-determined. The identification of a preferred phrasing that is independent of discourse also aids us in identifying and characterizing the discourse features that impinge on prosodic phrasing. Several well-known discourse phenomena—coreference, contrast, and parallelism—affected the phrasing of the clause final prepositional phrases in our corpus. We are left with three or four unexplained cases that are suggestive of a discourse explanation. 2.1.3 PHONOLOGICAL LENGTH AND PROSODIC PHRASING The psycholinguistic studies of Martin (1970), Allen (1975), Hillinger et al. (1976), Grosjean et al. (1979), Dommergues and Grosjean (1983), and Gee and Grosjean (1983), responding to the idea of readjusted syntax as the source of prosodic phrasing, show that grammatical structure, even if readjusted, is not in itself a reliable predictor of prosodic phrasing: mismatches between syntax and prosody occur often and systematically, and can be related to specific nonsyntactic factors such as length and word frequency. For example, although prosodic boundaries between subject and verb do occur, there also exist prosodic patterns in which the boundary comes between the verb and object, i.e., the data rev</context>
<context position="55691" citStr="Grosjean et al. (1979)" startWordPosition="9189" endWordPosition="9192">es, had them read by two speakers, marked the prosodic phrase boundaries as we had done with the Holmes and Everest data, and ran the sentences through our prosodic phrase system for comparison with the human speakers&apos; phrasing. Phrasing in the speech of the two human speakers was almost identical; where the speakers failed to match, we depended on the speaker with the more detailed phrasing to obtain a single transcript for comparison. The sentences with the phrase markings produced by the system (S) and by the human speakers (H) are given in Appendix A. In addition, we used the sentences of Grosjean et al. (1979) to test our system; these were the same sentences used by G &amp;G. They were produced by six subjects speaking each sentence at five different speaking rates. We chose these data both because they form an established, though small, corpus and because their phrase markings, derived by oscillographic tracings of pause duration, provide a check against the possibility of error in human judgments of pause location and salience. A comparison of these data with the output of our system is given in Appendix B. In comparing human and synthetic prosodic phrasing with an eye on synthetic phrasings that ar</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Grosjean, Grosjean, Lane, 1979</marker>
<rawString>Grosjean, F.; Grosjean, L.; and Lane, H. 1979 The Patterns of Silence: Performance Structures in Sentence Production. Cognitive Psychology 11:58-81.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>M Hillinger</author>
<author>C T James</author>
<author>D L Zell</author>
<author>L M Prato</author>
</authors>
<title>The Influence of Prescriptive and Subjective Phrase Markers on Retrieval Latencies.</title>
<date>1976</date>
<journal>Bulletin of the Psychonomic Society</journal>
<volume>8</volume>
<pages>353--355</pages>
<contexts>
<context position="16643" citStr="Hillinger et al. (1976)" startWordPosition="2647" endWordPosition="2650">y 14 percent of the phrases to be discourse-determined. The identification of a preferred phrasing that is independent of discourse also aids us in identifying and characterizing the discourse features that impinge on prosodic phrasing. Several well-known discourse phenomena—coreference, contrast, and parallelism—affected the phrasing of the clause final prepositional phrases in our corpus. We are left with three or four unexplained cases that are suggestive of a discourse explanation. 2.1.3 PHONOLOGICAL LENGTH AND PROSODIC PHRASING The psycholinguistic studies of Martin (1970), Allen (1975), Hillinger et al. (1976), Grosjean et al. (1979), Dommergues and Grosjean (1983), and Gee and Grosjean (1983), responding to the idea of readjusted syntax as the source of prosodic phrasing, show that grammatical structure, even if readjusted, is not in itself a reliable predictor of prosodic phrasing: mismatches between syntax and prosody occur often and systematically, and can be related to specific nonsyntactic factors such as length and word frequency. For example, although prosodic boundaries between subject and verb do occur, there also exist prosodic patterns in which the boundary comes between the verb and ob</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Hillinger, James, Zell, Prato, 1976</marker>
<rawString>Hillinger, M.; James, C. T.; Zell, D. L.; and Prato, L. M. 1976 The Influence of Prescriptive and Subjective Phrase Markers on Retrieval Latencies. Bulletin of the Psychonomic Society 8: 353-355.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>D Hindle</author>
</authors>
<title>User Manual for Fidditch, a Deterministic Parser.</title>
<date>1983</date>
<tech>NRL Technical Memorandum #7590-142.</tech>
<marker>Hindle, 1983</marker>
<rawString>Hindle, D. 1983 User Manual for Fidditch, a Deterministic Parser. NRL Technical Memorandum #7590-142.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>J Hirschberg</author>
<author>D Litman</author>
</authors>
<title>Now Let&apos;s Talk About Now: Identifying Cue Phrases Intonationally.</title>
<date>1987</date>
<booktitle>Proceedings of the 25th Annual Meeting of the Association for Computational Linguistics,</booktitle>
<pages>163--171</pages>
<contexts>
<context position="13750" citStr="Hirschberg and Litman (1987)" startWordPosition="2202" endWordPosition="2205">scourse and prosodic phrasing has been examined in some detail by Bing (1985), who argues that each noun phrase in an utterance constitutes a separate prosodic phrase unless it is destressed because of reference to previous discourse. Bing also observes that constituents that refer to items newly introduced into a discourse tend to be longer. This may be the reason that word count and syllable count play a prominent role in prosodic phrasing (see Section 2.1.3.). To our knowledge, no work has explicitly explored the relation between the length of a constituent and its status in the discourse. Hirschberg and Litman (1987) and Litman and Hirschberg (1990) also examine the relation between discourse and prosodic phrasing. Their work succeeds in distinguishing the use of items like now, so, and well as discourse cues from their denotative lexical use on the basis of a complex combination of pitch accent type and phrasing. The Hirschberg and Litman studies identify a specific discourse distinction that relates to phrasing. These studies are not intended to give a picture of the extent to which discourse relates to phrasing. On the other hand, Bing&apos;s work gives a broader picture of the relation between discourse an</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Hirschberg, Litman, 1987</marker>
<rawString>Hirschberg, J. and Litman, D. 1987 Now Let&apos;s Talk About Now: Identifying Cue Phrases Intonationally. Proceedings of the 25th Annual Meeting of the Association for Computational Linguistics, 163-171</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>D H Klatt</author>
</authors>
<title>Review of Text-to-Speech Conversion for English.</title>
<date>1987</date>
<journal>Journal of the Acoustic Society of America</journal>
<volume>82</volume>
<pages>737--793</pages>
<marker>Klatt, 1987</marker>
<rawString>Klatt, D. H. 1987 Review of Text-to-Speech Conversion for English. Journal of the Acoustic Society of America 82: 737-793.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>D H Klatt</author>
</authors>
<title>Vowel Lengthening Is Syntactically Determined in Connected Discourse.</title>
<date>1975</date>
<journal>Journal of Phonetics</journal>
<volume>3</volume>
<pages>129--140</pages>
<marker>Klatt, 1975</marker>
<rawString>Klatt, D. H. 1975 Vowel Lengthening Is Syntactically Determined in Connected Discourse. Journal of Phonetics 3: 129-140.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Jan Koster</author>
</authors>
<title>Why Subject Ss Don&apos;t Exist. In: Keyser, Samuel J. Recent Transformational Studies in European Languages. Linguistic Inquiry Monograph 3.</title>
<date>1978</date>
<publisher>MIT Press,</publisher>
<location>Cambridge, MA.</location>
<marker>Koster, 1978</marker>
<rawString>Koster, Jan. 1978 Why Subject Ss Don&apos;t Exist. In: Keyser, Samuel J. Recent Transformational Studies in European Languages. Linguistic Inquiry Monograph 3. MIT Press, Cambridge, MA.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>D T Langendoen</author>
</authors>
<title>Finite-State Parsing of Phrase-Structure Languages and the Status of Readjustment Rules in Grammar.</title>
<date>1975</date>
<journal>Linguistic Inquiry</journal>
<volume>6</volume>
<pages>533--554</pages>
<contexts>
<context position="8392" citStr="Langendoen (1975)" startWordPosition="1333" endWordPosition="1334">matches, &amp;quot;readjustment rules&amp;quot; that change constituent structure by adjoining each embedded sentence to the node dominating it have been posited. The result is a flattened structure that more accurately reflects the prosodic phrasing. In Chomsky and Halle (1968), this flattening process is not part of the grammar. Rather, it is viewed as &amp;quot;. . a performance factor, related to the difficulty of producing right branching structures such as [12]&amp;quot; (p. 372). Thus phrasing, in their approach, is only indirectly related to syntax, since readjustment is done by special rules outside the grammar proper. Langendoen (1975) proposes readjustment rules similar to those of Chomsky and Halle, but he claims that the readjustment of structure is part of the grammar, not part of the performance model. He thus makes explicit what is often a tacit assumption in both the linguistic and psycholinguistic literature2—that there is a direct connection between syntactic constituency and prosodic phrasing, with apparent misalignments readjusted before syntax interfaces with prosodic phonology. Langendoen&apos;s proposal works well for sentences such as 12 because it predicts that important prosodic phrase boundaries will coincide w</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Langendoen, 1975</marker>
<rawString>Langendoen, D. T. 1975 Finite-State Parsing of Phrase-Structure Languages and the Status of Readjustment Rules in Grammar. Linguistic Inquiry 6: 533-554.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>D Litman</author>
<author>J Hirschberg</author>
</authors>
<title>Disambiguating Cue Phrases in Text and Speech.</title>
<date>1990</date>
<booktitle>Proceedings of the 13th International Conference on Computational Linguistics (COLING).</booktitle>
<contexts>
<context position="13783" citStr="Litman and Hirschberg (1990)" startWordPosition="2207" endWordPosition="2211"> been examined in some detail by Bing (1985), who argues that each noun phrase in an utterance constitutes a separate prosodic phrase unless it is destressed because of reference to previous discourse. Bing also observes that constituents that refer to items newly introduced into a discourse tend to be longer. This may be the reason that word count and syllable count play a prominent role in prosodic phrasing (see Section 2.1.3.). To our knowledge, no work has explicitly explored the relation between the length of a constituent and its status in the discourse. Hirschberg and Litman (1987) and Litman and Hirschberg (1990) also examine the relation between discourse and prosodic phrasing. Their work succeeds in distinguishing the use of items like now, so, and well as discourse cues from their denotative lexical use on the basis of a complex combination of pitch accent type and phrasing. The Hirschberg and Litman studies identify a specific discourse distinction that relates to phrasing. These studies are not intended to give a picture of the extent to which discourse relates to phrasing. On the other hand, Bing&apos;s work gives a broader picture of the relation between discourse and phrasing, but it deals only wit</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Litman, Hirschberg, 1990</marker>
<rawString>Litman, D. and Hirschberg, J. 1990. Disambiguating Cue Phrases in Text and Speech. Proceedings of the 13th International Conference on Computational Linguistics (COLING).</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>M Y Liberman</author>
<author>A Prince</author>
</authors>
<title>On Stress and Linguistic Rhythm.</title>
<date>1977</date>
<journal>Linguistic Inquiry</journal>
<volume>8</volume>
<pages>249--336</pages>
<contexts>
<context position="15154" citStr="Liberman and Prince (1977)" startWordPosition="2424" endWordPosition="2427"> a complement to some more basic set of determinants, syntactic and/or phonological. In other words, when prosodic features that reflect facts of the discourse are removed, is there a residual, neutral phrasing? Our work on the prosodic phrase status of clause final prepositional phrases, which we discuss below, suggests the existence of a discourse-neutral phrasing that depends on syntactic constituency mediated by string adjacency and length of a potential prosodic phrase.3 Such phrasing provides us with a typical phrasing pattern analogous to the typical phrasal stress patterns examined in Liberman and Prince (1977), which &amp;quot;are often overwhelmed by the chiaroscuro of highlight and background in discourse, but retain the status of null-hypothesis patterns that emerge when Computational Linguistics Volume 16, Number 3, September 1990 157 J. Bachenko and E. Fitzpatrick Discourse-Neutral Prosodic Phrasing in English there is no good reason to take some other option&amp;quot; (p. 251). This approach to prosodic phrase boundary determination brings us closer to a framework in which phonological, syntactic, and discourse features all contribute to prosodic phrasing. The possibility of a discourse-neutral prosodic phrasi</context>
<context position="50300" citStr="Liberman and Prince (1977)" startWordPosition="8304" endWordPosition="8307">ondon for several days. Figure 7 Syntactic Input to Phrasing Rules. NP V NP NP AUX viNG A iN he me last night he was coming P NP to PNP for DET N 164 Computational Linguistics Volume 16, Number 3, September 1990 J. Bachenko and E. Fitzpatrick Discourse-Neutral Prosodic Phrasing in English branches that are unnecessary for prosodic phrase determination. 3.2 PROSODIC PHRASE REPRESENTATION Following G&amp;G, we require that the prosody rules build a binary tree whose terminals are phonological words and whose node labels are indices that mark boundary salience. An alternative representation based on Liberman and Prince (1977) is presented in Selkirk (1984), which contends that prosody, including prosodic phrasing, is more properly represented as a grid instead of a tree. Although a grid may be more descriptively suitable for some aspects of prosody (for example, Sproat and Liberman (1987) use the grid representation for their implementation of stress assignment in compound nominals), we are not aware of any evidence for or against a grid representation of discourseneutral phrasing. Figure 8 shows the phonological phrase tree that is built from the syntactic structure of Figure 7. The rules for building this tree a</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Liberman, Prince, 1977</marker>
<rawString>Liberman, M. Y. and Prince, A. 1977 On Stress and Linguistic Rhythm. Linguistic Inquiry 8: 249-336.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>P A Luce</author>
<author>T C Feustel</author>
<author>D B Pisoni</author>
</authors>
<title>Capacity Demands in Short-Term Memory for Synthetic and Natural Speech.</title>
<date>1983</date>
<journal>Human Factors</journal>
<volume>25</volume>
<pages>17--32</pages>
<contexts>
<context position="47133" citStr="Luce et al. 1983" startWordPosition="7812" endWordPosition="7815">s motivated our implementation. First, we hoped the system would provide us with a research tool for testing our ideas about syntax and phrasing against a large unrestricted collection of sentences. Second, we wished to investigate how well our approach would work for determining prosodic phrasing in a text-to-speech synthesizer. Existing text-to-speech systems perform well on word pronunciation and short sentences,12 but when it comes to long sentences and paragraphs, synthetic speech tends to be difficult to listen to and understand. Many investigators (e.g. Allen 1976; Elowitz et al. 1976; Luce et al. 1983; Cahn 1988) have suggested that the poor prosody of synthetic speech, in comparison with natural speech, is the primary factor leading to difficulties in the comprehension of fluent synthetic speech. And while researchers in text-tospeech synthesis have adopted a variety of approaches to prosodic phrase generation—from the simple punctuationbased rules and function word listings of existing commercial systems to the sophisticated prosodic heuristics described in Emorine and Martin (1988) and O&apos;Shaughnessy (1989)--the generation of appropriate prosodic phrasing in unrestricted text has remaine</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Luce, Feustel, Pisoni, 1983</marker>
<rawString>Luce, P. A.; Feustel, T. C.; and Pisoni, D. B. 1983 Capacity Demands in Short-Term Memory for Synthetic and Natural Speech. Human Factors 25: 17-32.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>E</author>
</authors>
<title>Toward an Analysis of Subjective Phrase Structure.</title>
<date>1970</date>
<journal>Psychological Bulletin</journal>
<volume>74</volume>
<pages>153--166</pages>
<marker>E, 1970</marker>
<rawString>Martin. E. 1970 Toward an Analysis of Subjective Phrase Structure. Psychological Bulletin 74: 153-166.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>M Nespor</author>
<author>I Vogel</author>
</authors>
<title>Prosodic Phonology.</title>
<date>1986</date>
<publisher>Foris Publications,</publisher>
<location>Dordrecht, The Netherlands.</location>
<contexts>
<context position="12114" citStr="Nespor and Vogel (1986)" startWordPosition="1923" endWordPosition="1927"> problematic and, we believe, compares unfavorably with an approach that views the semantic and phonological components as contributing to prosodic phrase boundary determination. 2.1.2 SEMANTICS AND PROSODIC PHRASING The syntax/prosody misalignment may be viewed as resulting in part from semantic considerations. Both predicateargument relations and discourse factors have been examined for their possible input to prosodic phrasing. Crystal (1969) claims that prosodic phrase boundaries will co-occur with grammatical functions such as subject, predicate, modifier, and adjunct. Selkirk (1984) and Nespor and Vogel (1986) take a similar approach, but within a different theoretical framework. Previous versions of our work, as described in Bachenko et al. (1986) also assume that phrasing is dependent on predicate-argument structure. The problem here is that the phrasing in observed data often ignores the argument status of constituents. In 17a—f, for example, the phrasing makes no distinction between arguments and adjuncts. All of the sentences have the same X(VY) pattern even though Y is a complement in the first case (the first serious attempt) and an adjunct in the others. (The complement in 17a and the adjun</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Nespor, Vogel, 1986</marker>
<rawString>Nespor., M. and Vogel, I. 1986 Prosodic Phonology. Foris Publications, Dordrecht, The Netherlands.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>S P Olive</author>
<author>M Y Liberman</author>
</authors>
<title>Text-to-Speech-An Overview.</title>
<date>1985</date>
<journal>Journal of the Acoustic Society of America, Supplement</journal>
<volume>1</volume>
<pages>97--108</pages>
<contexts>
<context position="975" citStr="Olive and Liberman 1985" startWordPosition="135" endWordPosition="138">A central goal of our work has been to characterize &amp;quot;discourse neutral&amp;quot; phrasing, i.e. sentence-level phrasing patterns that are independent of discourse semantics. Our account builds on Bachenko et al. (1986), but differs in its treatment of clausal structure and predicate-argument relations. Results so far indicate that the current system performs well when measured against a corpus of judgments of prosodic phrasing. 1 INTRODUCTION In previous work (Bachenko et al. 1986), we described an experimental text-to-speech system that determined prosodic phrasing for the Olive—Liberman synthesizer (Olive and Liberman 1985). The system generated phrase boundaries using information derived from the syntactic structure of a sentence. While we saw significant improvements in the resulting synthesized speech, we also observed problems with the system. Often these stemmed from our assumptions that both clausal structure and predicateargument relations were important in determining prosodic phrasing. This paper reconsiders those assumptions and describes an analysis of phrasing that we believe corrects many of the problems of the earlier version. Like the earlier version, it has been implemented in a text-to-speech sy</context>
<context position="46504" citStr="Olive and Liberman 1985" startWordPosition="7715" endWordPosition="7718"> prosodic verb phrases; length rules, which apply to the material on the right of a prosodic verb phrase; and final bundling, which collects phrases built up by the previous rules into a binary tree (see Figure 3). Location and salience rules are both subject to a left corner constraint on their application. In the following section, we discuss how the rules work in an experimental text-to-speech system. 3 AN EXPERIMENTAL TEXT-TO-SPEECH SYSTEM We have built an experimental text-to-speech system that uses our analysis of prosody to generate phrase boundaries for the Olive–Liberman synthesizer (Olive and Liberman 1985). Two concerns motivated our implementation. First, we hoped the system would provide us with a research tool for testing our ideas about syntax and phrasing against a large unrestricted collection of sentences. Second, we wished to investigate how well our approach would work for determining prosodic phrasing in a text-to-speech synthesizer. Existing text-to-speech systems perform well on word pronunciation and short sentences,12 but when it comes to long sentences and paragraphs, synthetic speech tends to be difficult to listen to and understand. Many investigators (e.g. Allen 1976; Elowitz </context>
</contexts>
<marker>Olive, Liberman, 1985</marker>
<rawString>Olive, S. P. and Liberman, M. Y. 1985 Text-to-Speech-An Overview. Journal of the Acoustic Society of America, Supplement 1: 78, S6. O&apos;Shaughnessy, D. D. 1989 Parsing with a Small Dictionary for Applications st.ch as Text-to-Speech. Computational Linguistics 15: 97-108.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>J B Pierrehurnbert</author>
</authors>
<title>The Phonetics and Phonology of English Intonation.</title>
<date>1980</date>
<location>Ph.D. Dissertation, MIT, Cambridge, MA.</location>
<marker>Pierrehurnbert, 1980</marker>
<rawString>Pierrehurnbert, J. B. 1980 The Phonetics and Phonology of English Intonation. Ph.D. Dissertation, MIT, Cambridge, MA.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>E Selkirk</author>
</authors>
<title>Phonology and Syntax: The Relation between Sound and Structure.</title>
<date>1984</date>
<publisher>MIT Press,</publisher>
<location>Cambridge, MA.</location>
<contexts>
<context position="12086" citStr="Selkirk (1984)" startWordPosition="1920" endWordPosition="1921"> fit the prosody is problematic and, we believe, compares unfavorably with an approach that views the semantic and phonological components as contributing to prosodic phrase boundary determination. 2.1.2 SEMANTICS AND PROSODIC PHRASING The syntax/prosody misalignment may be viewed as resulting in part from semantic considerations. Both predicateargument relations and discourse factors have been examined for their possible input to prosodic phrasing. Crystal (1969) claims that prosodic phrase boundaries will co-occur with grammatical functions such as subject, predicate, modifier, and adjunct. Selkirk (1984) and Nespor and Vogel (1986) take a similar approach, but within a different theoretical framework. Previous versions of our work, as described in Bachenko et al. (1986) also assume that phrasing is dependent on predicate-argument structure. The problem here is that the phrasing in observed data often ignores the argument status of constituents. In 17a—f, for example, the phrasing makes no distinction between arguments and adjuncts. All of the sentences have the same X(VY) pattern even though Y is a complement in the first case (the first serious attempt) and an adjunct in the others. (The com</context>
<context position="18286" citStr="Selkirk (1984)" startWordPosition="2901" endWordPosition="2902">ate boundary in Waiters who remember well II serve orders correctly. Discrepancies in length throw constituents off balance, and so prosodic phrasing will cross constituent boundaries in order to give the phrases similar lengths; this is the case in Chickens were eating II the remaining green vegetables, where the subject-predicate boundary finds no prosodic correspondent.4 The most explicit version of this approach is the analysis presented in Gee and Grosjean (1983) (henceforth G&amp;G). Drawing on the psycholinguistic studies mentioned above and on aspects of the grammar of prosody outlined in Selkirk (1984), G&amp;G propose an algorithm for mapping syntactic structure onto a hierarchical representation of phrasing; the rules they present accomplish this by integrating syntactic information (e.g. constituent structure, left-toright ordering) with information about constituent length. We have found that their rules, which are described in detail, provide a productive model for investigations of phrasing, and in what follows we shall frequently refer to their analysis. But, as we will show, G&amp;G fall short of providing a comprehensive theory. Their rules are too limited and their syntax too underspecifi</context>
<context position="19671" citStr="Selkirk (1984)" startWordPosition="3121" endWordPosition="3122">een to develop a theory of syntax/prosody relations that we could test in an experimental text-tospeech system. We approached the problem with the assumption that there is a level of prosodic phrase determination that does not include discourse factors, and that aiming for this level would yield an appropriate phrasing for a sentence. Both the output of the system and our preliminary findings, which show that discourse factors influence just a small part of the phrasings that follow a verb, indicate that this approach is feasible. The analysis that we arrived at takes G&amp;G and, to some extent, Selkirk (1984) as its starting point. Hence we are assuming that there is no necessary match between syntactic structure and prosodic phrasing. Prosody rules refer to syntactic structure, but they are not obliged to preserve it; independent principles of prosodic well-formedness, in particular length calculations, may create entirely different structures that appear at odds with the syntax. Here we shall describe the main features of our analysis and then go on to a description of the implementation. Our prosody rules are intended to account for two aspects of phrasing: boundary location and boundary salien</context>
<context position="22476" citStr="Selkirk (1984)" startWordPosition="3556" endWordPosition="3557">LOCATION RULES V NP PP We+saw spring+up among+the+trees The location rules identify possible boundary sites by first deriving phonological words from the lexical items in a parse tree, and then grouping the phonological words into larger phonological phrases. The boundaries that separate phonological phrases are the candidates for prosodic phrase boundaries, since the prosodic phrases of speech consist of one or more phonological phrases. Our rules for phonological word formation are adopted, for the most part, from G &amp;G, Grosjean and Gee (1987), and the account of monosyllabic destressing in Selkirk (1984). Thus in our analysis, rules of phonological word formation apply to the non-null terminal nodes in a syntax tree. If the terminal is a content word, i.e. noun, verb, adjective, or adverb, then this terminal may have the status of a phonological word on its own. Otherwise the word combines with one or more orthographically distinct words to form a single phonological word that has no internal word or phrase boundaries. This is accomplished by adjoining a word to its left or right neighbor depending on its lexical category and its position in the tree. Function words, e.g. auxiliary verbs, art</context>
<context position="24747" citStr="Selkirk (1984)" startWordPosition="3936" endWordPosition="3937">he preposition is a sister of the verb in the syntax tree), filled + in is a phonological word. Hence the boundary will follow the preposition. Adj a+sudden light Figure 1 Phonological Word Formation. 20. a. Holmes waited I in + the + dimly lit room. b.. . .and filled + in I a few of the gaps.6 Rules of phonological phrase formation now build the next level of prosodic constituents.&apos; Each phonological phrase consists of a syntactic head and the material that intervenes between it and a preceding head (usually, the pre-head modifiers, e.g. pre-nominal adjectives, pre-verbal adverbs). Following Selkirk (1984), we have limited the eligible head categories to noun, verb, adjective, and adverb (although adjectives and adverbs do not count if they directly precede and modify another head). Examples 21a–b illustrate the results of phonological phrase formation. In each case, the phonological phrase is created by a left-toright process that collects material up to and including the head of a syntactic constituent. Every phonological phrase boundary thus marks a syntactic head as well as the site of a possible prosodic boundary in speech. (The sequences with + are words formed by adjunction; I stands for</context>
<context position="50331" citStr="Selkirk (1984)" startWordPosition="8311" endWordPosition="8312">Input to Phrasing Rules. NP V NP NP AUX viNG A iN he me last night he was coming P NP to PNP for DET N 164 Computational Linguistics Volume 16, Number 3, September 1990 J. Bachenko and E. Fitzpatrick Discourse-Neutral Prosodic Phrasing in English branches that are unnecessary for prosodic phrase determination. 3.2 PROSODIC PHRASE REPRESENTATION Following G&amp;G, we require that the prosody rules build a binary tree whose terminals are phonological words and whose node labels are indices that mark boundary salience. An alternative representation based on Liberman and Prince (1977) is presented in Selkirk (1984), which contends that prosody, including prosodic phrasing, is more properly represented as a grid instead of a tree. Although a grid may be more descriptively suitable for some aspects of prosody (for example, Sproat and Liberman (1987) use the grid representation for their implementation of stress assignment in compound nominals), we are not aware of any evidence for or against a grid representation of discourseneutral phrasing. Figure 8 shows the phonological phrase tree that is built from the syntactic structure of Figure 7. The rules for building this tree apply from left to right, follow</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Selkirk, 1984</marker>
<rawString>Selkirk, E. 0. 1984 Phonology and Syntax: The Relation between Sound and Structure. MIT Press, Cambridge, MA.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>R W Sproat</author>
<author>M Y Liberman</author>
</authors>
<title>Toward Treating English Nominals Correctly.</title>
<date>1987</date>
<booktitle>Proceedings of the 25th Annual Meeting of the Association for Computational Linguistics,</booktitle>
<pages>140--146</pages>
<contexts>
<context position="50568" citStr="Sproat and Liberman (1987)" startWordPosition="8346" endWordPosition="8349">c Phrasing in English branches that are unnecessary for prosodic phrase determination. 3.2 PROSODIC PHRASE REPRESENTATION Following G&amp;G, we require that the prosody rules build a binary tree whose terminals are phonological words and whose node labels are indices that mark boundary salience. An alternative representation based on Liberman and Prince (1977) is presented in Selkirk (1984), which contends that prosody, including prosodic phrasing, is more properly represented as a grid instead of a tree. Although a grid may be more descriptively suitable for some aspects of prosody (for example, Sproat and Liberman (1987) use the grid representation for their implementation of stress assignment in compound nominals), we are not aware of any evidence for or against a grid representation of discourseneutral phrasing. Figure 8 shows the phonological phrase tree that is built from the syntactic structure of Figure 7. The rules for building this tree apply from left to right, following the analysis we described in the preceding section. Figures 9-11. show the prosodic phrase derivation. Numbered nodes refer to salience values, with higher numbers indicating greater salience. The index is assigned according to phono</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Sproat, Liberman, 1987</marker>
<rawString>Sproat, R. W. and Liberman, M. Y. 1987 Toward Treating English Nominals Correctly. Proceedings of the 25th Annual Meeting of the Association for Computational Linguistics, 140-146.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>L A Streeter</author>
</authors>
<title>Acoustic Determinants of Boundary Perception.</title>
<date>1978</date>
<journal>Journal of the Acoustical Society of America</journal>
<volume>64</volume>
<pages>1582--1592</pages>
<marker>Streeter, 1978</marker>
<rawString>Streeter, L. A. 1978 Acoustic Determinants of Boundary Perception. Journal of the Acoustical Society of America 64: 1582-1592.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="false">
<authors>
<author>H</author>
</authors>
<title>The connection must be determined II for the lefthand power unit II on each shelf S: The connection ! must be determined I for the left-hand power unit Ion each shelf 5. H: I need a man II to fix the sink. S: I need a man I to fix ! the sink.</title>
<marker>H, </marker>
<rawString>4. H: The connection must be determined II for the lefthand power unit II on each shelf S: The connection ! must be determined I for the left-hand power unit Ion each shelf 5. H: I need a man II to fix the sink. S: I need a man I to fix ! the sink.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="false">
<authors>
<author>H</author>
</authors>
<title>The techniques I that we had implemented II were tested I on a larger computer. S: The techniques I that we had implemented II were tested I on a larger! computer.</title>
<marker>H, </marker>
<rawString>6. H: The techniques I that we had implemented II were tested I on a larger computer. S: The techniques I that we had implemented II were tested I on a larger! computer.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="false">
<authors>
<author>H</author>
</authors>
<title>Everyone I who had participated I in the attempt II was considerably affected. S: Everyone I who had participated! in the attempt II was considerably affected.</title>
<marker>H, </marker>
<rawString>7. H: Everyone I who had participated I in the attempt II was considerably affected. S: Everyone I who had participated! in the attempt II was considerably affected.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="false">
<authors>
<author>H</author>
</authors>
<title>The method I by which one converts a word I into phonemes II is provided I in chapter seven. S: The method I by which one converts ! a word I into phonemes II is provided! in chapter seven.</title>
<marker>H, </marker>
<rawString>8. H: The method I by which one converts a word I into phonemes II is provided I in chapter seven. S: The method I by which one converts ! a word I into phonemes II is provided! in chapter seven.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="false">
<title>FL In these instances II it may be desirable I to use phonemic characters!! each time I that it appears II on the input text.</title>
<marker></marker>
<rawString>9. FL In these instances II it may be desirable I to use phonemic characters!! each time I that it appears II on the input text.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="false">
<title>S: In these ! instances I it may be ! desirable!! to use! phonemic characters II each time that it appears ! on the input text.</title>
<marker></marker>
<rawString>S: In these ! instances I it may be ! desirable!! to use! phonemic characters II each time that it appears ! on the input text.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>e g Cooper</author>
</authors>
<title>Cooper and Paccia-Cooper</title>
<date>1976</date>
<pages>204</pages>
<location>Klatt</location>
<marker>Cooper, 1976</marker>
<rawString>2. e.g. Cooper (1976), Cooper and Paccia-Cooper (1980), Klatt (1975), and Streeter (1978). Downing (1970), like Langendoen, explicitly assumes a direct connection between syntax and prosodic phrasing with &amp;quot;some aspects at least of surface structure . . . determined exclusively by the necessity of providing input to the phonological rules that specify prosodic features&amp;quot; (p. 204).</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="false">
<title>In characterizing this phrasing as discourse-neutral, we are assuming, contra Bing, that length is independent of discourse.</title>
<marker></marker>
<rawString>3. In characterizing this phrasing as discourse-neutral, we are assuming, contra Bing, that length is independent of discourse.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<title>Both examples are from Martin</title>
<date>1970</date>
<contexts>
<context position="16604" citStr="(1970)" startWordPosition="2644" endWordPosition="2644"> examined we found only 14 percent of the phrases to be discourse-determined. The identification of a preferred phrasing that is independent of discourse also aids us in identifying and characterizing the discourse features that impinge on prosodic phrasing. Several well-known discourse phenomena—coreference, contrast, and parallelism—affected the phrasing of the clause final prepositional phrases in our corpus. We are left with three or four unexplained cases that are suggestive of a discourse explanation. 2.1.3 PHONOLOGICAL LENGTH AND PROSODIC PHRASING The psycholinguistic studies of Martin (1970), Allen (1975), Hillinger et al. (1976), Grosjean et al. (1979), Dommergues and Grosjean (1983), and Gee and Grosjean (1983), responding to the idea of readjusted syntax as the source of prosodic phrasing, show that grammatical structure, even if readjusted, is not in itself a reliable predictor of prosodic phrasing: mismatches between syntax and prosody occur often and systematically, and can be related to specific nonsyntactic factors such as length and word frequency. For example, although prosodic boundaries between subject and verb do occur, there also exist prosodic patterns in which the</context>
</contexts>
<marker>1970</marker>
<rawString>4. Both examples are from Martin (1970). Bierwisch (1966) also includes length, in terms of stressed syllable count, as a factor in the prosodic phrasing of German auxiliary + verb strings. Length as a factor in prosodic phrasing is mentioned in Selkirk (1984) and Nespor and Vogel (1986), but without any systematic account of its effects.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>G</author>
</authors>
<title>G&apos;s test corpus consists of 14 sentences that were originally used in Grosjean et</title>
<date>1979</date>
<marker>G, 1979</marker>
<rawString>5. G &amp;G&apos;s test corpus consists of 14 sentences that were originally used in Grosjean et al. (1979).</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="false">
<title>A more accurate account of adjunction, such as that in Selkirk</title>
<date>1984</date>
<journal>G &amp;G.</journal>
<contexts>
<context position="12086" citStr="(1984)" startWordPosition="1921" endWordPosition="1921"> prosody is problematic and, we believe, compares unfavorably with an approach that views the semantic and phonological components as contributing to prosodic phrase boundary determination. 2.1.2 SEMANTICS AND PROSODIC PHRASING The syntax/prosody misalignment may be viewed as resulting in part from semantic considerations. Both predicateargument relations and discourse factors have been examined for their possible input to prosodic phrasing. Crystal (1969) claims that prosodic phrase boundaries will co-occur with grammatical functions such as subject, predicate, modifier, and adjunct. Selkirk (1984) and Nespor and Vogel (1986) take a similar approach, but within a different theoretical framework. Previous versions of our work, as described in Bachenko et al. (1986) also assume that phrasing is dependent on predicate-argument structure. The problem here is that the phrasing in observed data often ignores the argument status of constituents. In 17a—f, for example, the phrasing makes no distinction between arguments and adjuncts. All of the sentences have the same X(VY) pattern even though Y is a complement in the first case (the first serious attempt) and an adjunct in the others. (The com</context>
<context position="18286" citStr="(1984)" startWordPosition="2902" endWordPosition="2902">dary in Waiters who remember well II serve orders correctly. Discrepancies in length throw constituents off balance, and so prosodic phrasing will cross constituent boundaries in order to give the phrases similar lengths; this is the case in Chickens were eating II the remaining green vegetables, where the subject-predicate boundary finds no prosodic correspondent.4 The most explicit version of this approach is the analysis presented in Gee and Grosjean (1983) (henceforth G&amp;G). Drawing on the psycholinguistic studies mentioned above and on aspects of the grammar of prosody outlined in Selkirk (1984), G&amp;G propose an algorithm for mapping syntactic structure onto a hierarchical representation of phrasing; the rules they present accomplish this by integrating syntactic information (e.g. constituent structure, left-toright ordering) with information about constituent length. We have found that their rules, which are described in detail, provide a productive model for investigations of phrasing, and in what follows we shall frequently refer to their analysis. But, as we will show, G&amp;G fall short of providing a comprehensive theory. Their rules are too limited and their syntax too underspecifi</context>
<context position="19671" citStr="(1984)" startWordPosition="3122" endWordPosition="3122">evelop a theory of syntax/prosody relations that we could test in an experimental text-tospeech system. We approached the problem with the assumption that there is a level of prosodic phrase determination that does not include discourse factors, and that aiming for this level would yield an appropriate phrasing for a sentence. Both the output of the system and our preliminary findings, which show that discourse factors influence just a small part of the phrasings that follow a verb, indicate that this approach is feasible. The analysis that we arrived at takes G&amp;G and, to some extent, Selkirk (1984) as its starting point. Hence we are assuming that there is no necessary match between syntactic structure and prosodic phrasing. Prosody rules refer to syntactic structure, but they are not obliged to preserve it; independent principles of prosodic well-formedness, in particular length calculations, may create entirely different structures that appear at odds with the syntax. Here we shall describe the main features of our analysis and then go on to a description of the implementation. Our prosody rules are intended to account for two aspects of phrasing: boundary location and boundary salien</context>
<context position="22476" citStr="(1984)" startWordPosition="3557" endWordPosition="3557"> RULES V NP PP We+saw spring+up among+the+trees The location rules identify possible boundary sites by first deriving phonological words from the lexical items in a parse tree, and then grouping the phonological words into larger phonological phrases. The boundaries that separate phonological phrases are the candidates for prosodic phrase boundaries, since the prosodic phrases of speech consist of one or more phonological phrases. Our rules for phonological word formation are adopted, for the most part, from G &amp;G, Grosjean and Gee (1987), and the account of monosyllabic destressing in Selkirk (1984). Thus in our analysis, rules of phonological word formation apply to the non-null terminal nodes in a syntax tree. If the terminal is a content word, i.e. noun, verb, adjective, or adverb, then this terminal may have the status of a phonological word on its own. Otherwise the word combines with one or more orthographically distinct words to form a single phonological word that has no internal word or phrase boundaries. This is accomplished by adjoining a word to its left or right neighbor depending on its lexical category and its position in the tree. Function words, e.g. auxiliary verbs, art</context>
<context position="24747" citStr="(1984)" startWordPosition="3937" endWordPosition="3937">sition is a sister of the verb in the syntax tree), filled + in is a phonological word. Hence the boundary will follow the preposition. Adj a+sudden light Figure 1 Phonological Word Formation. 20. a. Holmes waited I in + the + dimly lit room. b.. . .and filled + in I a few of the gaps.6 Rules of phonological phrase formation now build the next level of prosodic constituents.&apos; Each phonological phrase consists of a syntactic head and the material that intervenes between it and a preceding head (usually, the pre-head modifiers, e.g. pre-nominal adjectives, pre-verbal adverbs). Following Selkirk (1984), we have limited the eligible head categories to noun, verb, adjective, and adverb (although adjectives and adverbs do not count if they directly precede and modify another head). Examples 21a–b illustrate the results of phonological phrase formation. In each case, the phonological phrase is created by a left-toright process that collects material up to and including the head of a syntactic constituent. Every phonological phrase boundary thus marks a syntactic head as well as the site of a possible prosodic boundary in speech. (The sequences with + are words formed by adjunction; I stands for</context>
<context position="50331" citStr="(1984)" startWordPosition="8312" endWordPosition="8312"> Phrasing Rules. NP V NP NP AUX viNG A iN he me last night he was coming P NP to PNP for DET N 164 Computational Linguistics Volume 16, Number 3, September 1990 J. Bachenko and E. Fitzpatrick Discourse-Neutral Prosodic Phrasing in English branches that are unnecessary for prosodic phrase determination. 3.2 PROSODIC PHRASE REPRESENTATION Following G&amp;G, we require that the prosody rules build a binary tree whose terminals are phonological words and whose node labels are indices that mark boundary salience. An alternative representation based on Liberman and Prince (1977) is presented in Selkirk (1984), which contends that prosody, including prosodic phrasing, is more properly represented as a grid instead of a tree. Although a grid may be more descriptively suitable for some aspects of prosody (for example, Sproat and Liberman (1987) use the grid representation for their implementation of stress assignment in compound nominals), we are not aware of any evidence for or against a grid representation of discourseneutral phrasing. Figure 8 shows the phonological phrase tree that is built from the syntactic structure of Figure 7. The rules for building this tree apply from left to right, follow</context>
</contexts>
<marker>1984</marker>
<rawString>6. A more accurate account of adjunction, such as that in Selkirk (1984), would limit the list of adjoinable words to those that have both a strong and a weak form. For example, the word him in see him may be realized as the strong form [him], where the vowel carries stress, or it may take the weak unstressed form [m]. This word is therefore a candidate for adjunction. In contrast, a preposition such as among has no weak form and would be nonadjoinable. Results that we discuss below support this approach. Our current system, however, relies solely on lexical category and tree structure to identify adjunction possibilities. 7. These are essentially the phi phrases of G &amp;G.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="false">
<authors>
<author>Below</author>
</authors>
<title>in the discussion of constituent length, we will claim that word count should actually be stressed syllable count. In the current system, however, length depends on phonological word count.</title>
<marker>Below, </marker>
<rawString>8. Below, in the discussion of constituent length, we will claim that word count should actually be stressed syllable count. In the current system, however, length depends on phonological word count.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<title>Problems with final phrase boundaries are discussed in more detail in Bachenko et al.</title>
<date>1986</date>
<contexts>
<context position="12114" citStr="(1986)" startWordPosition="1927" endWordPosition="1927"> we believe, compares unfavorably with an approach that views the semantic and phonological components as contributing to prosodic phrase boundary determination. 2.1.2 SEMANTICS AND PROSODIC PHRASING The syntax/prosody misalignment may be viewed as resulting in part from semantic considerations. Both predicateargument relations and discourse factors have been examined for their possible input to prosodic phrasing. Crystal (1969) claims that prosodic phrase boundaries will co-occur with grammatical functions such as subject, predicate, modifier, and adjunct. Selkirk (1984) and Nespor and Vogel (1986) take a similar approach, but within a different theoretical framework. Previous versions of our work, as described in Bachenko et al. (1986) also assume that phrasing is dependent on predicate-argument structure. The problem here is that the phrasing in observed data often ignores the argument status of constituents. In 17a—f, for example, the phrasing makes no distinction between arguments and adjuncts. All of the sentences have the same X(VY) pattern even though Y is a complement in the first case (the first serious attempt) and an adjunct in the others. (The complement in 17a and the adjun</context>
</contexts>
<marker>1986</marker>
<rawString>9. Problems with final phrase boundaries are discussed in more detail in Bachenko et al. (1986), where the analysis presented assumes the version of final bundling proposed in G &amp;G. We return to this type of example below.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="false">
<title>Prosodic events finer than the pause were marked but ignored for this study. A stress foot contains one stressed syllable and zero or more unstressed syllables. In our current implementation, length is measured by phonological word count, since stress foot information is not readily available to us.</title>
<marker></marker>
<rawString>10. Prosodic events finer than the pause were marked but ignored for this study. A stress foot contains one stressed syllable and zero or more unstressed syllables. In our current implementation, length is measured by phonological word count, since stress foot information is not readily available to us.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="false">
<title>Conjunctions of lexical items, e.g. some subtle and horrible crime, these windows and shutters, are rarely split into two phrases.</title>
<marker></marker>
<rawString>11. Conjunctions of lexical items, e.g. some subtle and horrible crime, these windows and shutters, are rarely split into two phrases.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Klatt</author>
</authors>
<title>presents a useful review of text-to-speech technology and performance.</title>
<date>1987</date>
<marker>Klatt, 1987</marker>
<rawString>12. Klatt (1987) presents a useful review of text-to-speech technology and performance.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Fitzpatrick</author>
<author>Bachenko</author>
</authors>
<title>provide a more detailed discussion of the differences between parsing for speech and parsing for text understanding.</title>
<date>1989</date>
<marker>Fitzpatrick, Bachenko, 1989</marker>
<rawString>13. Fitzpatrick and Bachenko (1989) provide a more detailed discussion of the differences between parsing for speech and parsing for text understanding.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Hindle</author>
</authors>
<title>lexical lookup and category disambiguation are done by the stochastic parser described in Church</title>
<date>1983</date>
<marker>Hindle, 1983</marker>
<rawString>14. Hindle (1983); lexical lookup and category disambiguation are done by the stochastic parser described in Church (1988).</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<title>We have as yet no account of pre-verbal embedded sentences, though an analysis that does not involve an embedded S node is available</title>
<date>1978</date>
<location>Koster,</location>
<marker>1978</marker>
<rawString>15. We have as yet no account of pre-verbal embedded sentences, though an analysis that does not involve an embedded S node is available (Koster, 1978).</rawString>
</citation>
</citationList>
</algorithm>
</algorithms>