<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<algorithms version="110505">
<algorithm name="SectLabel" version="110505">
<variant no="0" confidence="0.000000">
<title confidence="0.92814">
A SYNCHRONIZATION STRUCTURE OF SSTC AND ITS
APPLICATIONS IN MACHINE TRANSLATION
</title>
<author confidence="0.91918">
MOSLEH H. AL-ADHAILEH
</author>
<affiliation confidence="0.919981">
Computer Aided Translation Unit
School of Computer Sciences
Universiti Sains Malaysia
</affiliation>
<address confidence="0.914586">
11800 PENANG, MALAYSIA
</address>
<email confidence="0.99821">
mosleh@cs.usm.my, mosleh@hotmail.com
</email>
<author confidence="0.582046">
TANG ENYA KONG
</author>
<affiliation confidence="0.87337">
Computer Aided Translation Unit
School of Computer Sciences
Universiti Sains Malaysia
</affiliation>
<address confidence="0.91337">
11800 PENANG, MALAYSIA
</address>
<email confidence="0.99682">
enyakong@cs.usm.my
</email>
<author confidence="0.559093">
ZAHARIN YUSOFF
</author>
<affiliation confidence="0.877404">
Computer Aided Translation Unit
School of Computer Sciences
Universiti Sains Malaysia
</affiliation>
<address confidence="0.913632">
11800 PENANG, MALAYSIA
</address>
<email confidence="0.997332">
zarin@cs.usm.my
</email>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.99548" genericHeader="abstract">
ABSTRACT
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9760415">
In this paper, a flexible annotation schema called (SSTC) is introduced. In order to describe the correspondence
between different languages, we propose a variant of SSTC called synchronous SSTC (S-SSTC). We will also
describe how S-SSTC provides the flexibility to treat some of the non-standard cases, which are problematic to
other synchronous formalisms. The proposed S-SSTC schema is well suited to describe the correspondence
between different languages, in particular, relating a language with its translation in another language (i.e. in
Machine Translation). Also it can be used as annotation for translation systems that automatically extract transfer
mappings (rules or examples) from bilingual corpora. The S-SSTC is very well suited for the construction of a
Bilingual Knowledge Bank (BKB), where the examples are kept in form of S-SSTCs.
</bodyText>
<keyword confidence="0.8373755">
KEYWORDS: parallel text, Structured String-Tree Correspondence (SSTC), Synchronous SSTC, Bilingual
Knowledge Bank (BKB), Tree Bank Annotation Schema.
</keyword>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.999705" genericHeader="keywords">
1. INTRODUCTION
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.99993051724138">
There is now a consensus about the fact that natural
language should be described as correspondences
between different levels of representation. Much of
theoretical linguistics can be formulated in a very
natural manner as stating correspondences
(translations) between layers of representation
structures (Rambow &amp; Satta, 1996).
In this paper, a flexible annotation schema called
Structured String-Tree Correspondence (SSTC)
(Boitet &amp; Zaharin, 1988) will be introduced to
capture a natural language text, its corresponding
abstract linguistic representation and the mapping
(correspondence) between these two. The
correspondence between the string and its associated
representation tree structure is defined in terms of the
sub-correspondence between parts of the string
(substrings) and parts of the tree structure (subtrees),
which can be interpreted for both analysis and
generation. Such correspondence is defined in a way
that is able to handle some non-standard cases (e.g.
non-projective correspondence).
While synchronous systems are becoming more and
more popular, there is therefore a great need for
formal models of corresponding different levels of
representation structures. Existing synchronous
systems face a problem of handling, in a
computationally attractive way, some non-standard
phenomena exist between NLs. Therefore there is a
need for a flexible annotation schema to realize
additional power and flexibility in expressing the
desired structural correspondences between languages
(representation structures).
Many problems in Machine Translation (MT), in
particular transfer-rules extraction, EBMT, etc., can
be expressed via correspondences. We will define a
variant of SSTC called synchronous SSTC (S-SSTC).
S-SSTC consists of two SSTCs that are related by a
synchronization relation. The use of S-SSTC is
motivated by the desire to describe not only the
correspondence between the text and its
representation structure for each language (i.e. SSTC)
but also the correspondence between two languages
(synchronous correspondence). For instance, between
a language and its translation in other language in the
case of MT. The S-SSTC will be used to relate
expression of a natural language to its associated
translation in another language. The interface
between the two languages is made precise via a
synchronization relation between two SSTCs, which
is totally non-directional.
In this paper, we will present the proposed S-SSTC –
a schema well suited to describe the correspondence
between two languages. The synchronous SSTC is
flexible and able to handle the non-standard
correspondence cases exist between different
languages. It can also be used to facilitate automatic
extraction of transfer mappings (rules or examples)
from bilingual corpora.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.998051" genericHeader="introduction">
2. STRUCTURED STRING-TREE
CORRESPONDENCE (SSTC)
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999838242424243">
From the Meaning-Text Theory (MTT)1 point of
view, Natural Language (NL) is considered as a
correspondence between meanings and texts (Kahane,
2001). The MTT point of view, even if it has been
introduced in different formulations, is more or less
accepted by the whole linguistic community.
In this section, we stress on the fact that in order to
describe Natural Language (NL) in a natural manner,
three distinct components need to be expressed by the
linguistic formalisms; namely, the text, its
corresponding abstract linguistic representation and
the mapping (correspondence) between these two.
Actually, NL is not only a correspondence between
different representation levels, as stressed by MTT
postulates, but also a sub-correspondence between
them. For instance, between the string in a language
and its representation tree structure, it is important to
specify the sub-correspondences between parts of the
string (substrings) and parts of the tree structure
(subtrees), which can be interpreted for both analysis
and generation in NLP. It is well known that many
linguistic constructions are not projective (e.g.
scrambling, cross serial dependencies, etc.). Hence, it
is very much desired to define the correspondence in
a way to be able to handle the non-standard cases
(e.g. non-projective correspondence), see Figure 1.
Towards this aim, a flexible annotation structure
called Structured String-Tree Correspondence (SSTC)
was introduced in Boitet &amp; Zaharin (1988) to record
the string of terms, its associated representation
structure and the mapping between the two, which is
expressed by the sub-correspondences recorded as
part of a SSTC.
</bodyText>
<footnote confidence="0.59036125">
1 The Meaning-Text Theory (MTT) was put forward in (Zolkovski &amp;
Mel&apos;cuk (1965), in the framework of research in Machine translation.
More presentations of MTT can be found in (Mel&apos;cuk, 1997) and
(Mili&amp;evi6, 2001).
</footnote>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.927329">
2.1 The SSTC Annotation Structure
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.987410545454545">
The SSTC is a general structure that can associate an
arbitrary tree structure to string in a language as
desired by the annotator to be the interpretation
structure of the string, and more importantly is the
facility to specify the correspondence between the
string and the associated tree which can be non-
projective (Boitet &amp; Zaharin, 1988). These features
are very much desired in the design of an annotation
scheme, in particular for the treatment of linguistic
phenomena, which are non-standard, e.g. crossed
dependencies (Tang &amp; Zaharin, 1995).
</bodyText>
<note confidence="0.363431">
Definitions2:
</note>
<construct confidence="0.995674291666667">
- An SSTC is a general structure, which is a string in a
language associated with an arbitrary tree structure;
i.e. its interpretation structure, and the correspondence
between the string and its associated tree, which can be
non-projective; i.e. SSTC is a triple (st, tr, co), where st
is a string in one language, tr is its associated
representation tree structure and co is the
correspondence between st and tr.
- The correspondence co between a string and its
representation tree is made of two interrelated
correspondences:
a) Between nodes and substrings (possibly
discontinuous).
b) Between (possibly incomplete) subtrees and
(possibly discontinuous) substrings.
- The correspondence can be encoded on the tree by
attaching to each node N in the representation tree two
sequences of INTERVALS called SNODE(N) and
STREE(N).
- SNODE(N): An interval of the substring in the string
that corresponds to the node N in the tree.
STREE(N): An interval of the substring in the string
that corresponds to the subtree having the node N as
root.
</construct>
<figureCaption confidence="0.939447333333333">
Figure 2: An SSTC recording the sentence “John picks the box up”
and its dependency tree together with the correspondences between
substrings of the sentence and subtrees of the tree.
</figureCaption>
<bodyText confidence="0.7650966">
Figure 2 illustrates the sentence “John picks the box
up” with its corresponding SSTC. It contains a non-
projective correspondence. An interval is assigned to
each word in the sentence, i.e. (0-1) for “John”, (1-2)
for “picks”, (2-3) for “the&amp;quot;, (3-4) for “box” and (4-5)
for “up”. A substring in the sentence that corresponds
to a node in the representation tree is denoted by
assigning the interval of the substring to SNODE of
2 These definitions are based on the discussion in (Tang, 1994) and
Boitet &amp; Zaharin (1988).
</bodyText>
<figure confidence="0.999347666666667">
John
John
box
the.box
the
NP
the.box
the box
VP
V
pick up
picks.up
</figure>
<figureCaption confidence="0.99495825">
Figure 1: The correspondence between the string “he picks the
box up” and its representation tree (dependency tree and phrase-
structure tree), together with the sub-correspondences between the
substrings and subtrees.
</figureCaption>
<figure confidence="0.97296238">
Tree
pick up
John box
the
String
John picks the box up
S
Tree
NP VP
John
V NP
pick up the box
String
John picks the box up
NP
John
John
pick up
picks.up
picks[v] up[p]
String
the[det]
(2-3/2-3)
0John
1picks2
1picks2
the3box u5
4up5
( 12+45
1-2+4-5
Tree
/0-5)
John[n]
(0-1/0-1)
box [n]
(3-4/2-4)
String
the[det]
(2-3/2-3)
Tree
picks[v] up[p]
(1-2+4-5/
0-5
0-5 )
John[n]
(0-1/0-1)
box [n]
(3-4/2-4)
0n1picks2the3box4up5the3box4 up5
0John1picks 2
</figure>
<bodyText confidence="0.999834666666667">
the node, e.g. the node “picks up” with SNODE
intervals (1-2+4-5) corresponds to the words “picks”
and &amp;quot;up&amp;quot; in the string with the similar intervals.The
correspondence between subtrees and substrings are
denoted by the interval assigned to the STREE of
each node, e.g. the subtree rooted at node “picks up”
with STREE interval (0-5) corresponds to the whole
sentence “John picks the box up”.
The case depicted in Figure 2, describes how the
SSTC structure treats some non-standard linguistic
phenomena. The particle &amp;quot;up&amp;quot; is featurised into the
verb &amp;quot;pick&amp;quot; and in discontinuous manner (e.g. &amp;quot;up&amp;quot;
(4-5) in &amp;quot;pick-up&amp;quot; (1-2+4-5)) in the sentence &amp;quot;He
picks the box up&amp;quot;. For more details on the
proprieties of SSTC, see Boitet &amp; Zaharin (1988).
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.995511" genericHeader="method">
3. SYNCHRONOUS SSTC STRUCTURE
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.997780833333334">
Much of theoretical linguistics can be formulated in a
very natural manner as stating correspondences
(translations) between layers of representation
structures (Rambow &amp; Satta, 1996), such as the
relation between syntax and semantic. An analogous
problem is to be defined in such a way that expresses
the correspondence between a language and its
translations in other languages. Therefore the
synchronization of two adequate linguistic
formalisms seems to be an appropriate representation
for that.
The idea of parallelized formalisms is widely used
one, and one which has been applied in many
different ways. The use of synchronous formalisms is
motivated by the desire to describe two languages that
are closely related to each other but that do not have
the same structures. For example, synchronous Tree
Adjoining Grammar (S-TAG) can be used to relate
TAGs for two different languages, for example, for
the purpose of immediate structural translation in
machine translation (Abeill6 et al.,1990), (Harbusch
&amp; Poller,1996), or for relating a syntactic TAG and
semantic one for the same language (Shieber &amp;
Schabes,1990). S-TAG is a variant of Tree Adjoining
Grammar (TAG) introduced by (Shieber &amp;
Schabes,1990) to characterize correspondences
between tree adjoining languages. Considering the
original definition of S-TAGs, one can see that it does
not restrict the structures that can be produced in the
source and target languages. It allows the construction
of a non-TAL (Shieber, 1994), (Harbusch &amp; Poller,
2000). As a result, Shieber (1994) propose a restricted
definition for S-TAG, namely, the IS-TAG for
isomorphic S-TAG. In this case only TAL can be
formed in each component. This isomorphism
requirement is formally attractive, but for practical
applications somewhat too strict. Also contrastive
well-known translation phenomena exist in different
languages, which cannot be expressed by IS-TAG,
Figure 3 illustrates some examples (Shieber, 1994).
Similar limitations also appear in synchronous CFGs
(Harbusch &amp; Poller,1994).
</bodyText>
<figureCaption confidence="0.9971635">
Figure 3: Kinds of relations between different
languages, which are not isomorphic.
</figureCaption>
<bodyText confidence="0.9997850625">
Due to these limitations, instead of investigating into
the synchronization of two grammars, we propose a
flexible annotation schema (i.e. Synchronous
Structured String-Tree Correspondence (S-SSTC)) to
realize additional power and flexibility in expressing
structural correspondences at the level of language
sentence pairs. For example, such schema can serve
as a mean to represent translation examples, or find
structural correspondences for the purpose of transfer
grammar learning (Menezes &amp; Richardson, 2001),
(Aramaki et al., 2001), (Watanabe et al., 2000),
(Meyers et al., 2000), (Matsumoto et al., 1993), (kaji
et al., 1992), and example-base machine translation
EBMT3 (Sato &amp; Nagao, 1990), (Sato, 1991),
(Richardson et al., 2001), (Al-Adhaileh &amp; Tang,
1999).
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.998866">
3.1 The Synchronous SSTC
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999813888888889">
In this section, we will discuss the definition and the
formal properties of S-SSTC. A S-SSTC consists of a
pair of SSTCs with an additional synchronization
relation between them. The use of S-SSTC is
motivated by the desire to describe not only the
correspondence between the text and its
representation structure in one language (i.e. SSTC)
but also the correspondence between two languages
(synchronous correspondence).
</bodyText>
<construct confidence="0.909324166666667">
Definitions:
- Let each of S and T be SSTC which consists of a
triple (st, tr, co), where st is a string in one
language, tr is its associated representation tree
structure and co is the correspondence between st
and tr, as defined in Section 2.1.
- A synchronous SSTC Ssyn is defined as a triple (S, T,
g(S,T )), where g(S,T ) is a set of links defining the
synchronization correspondence between S and T at
different internal levels of the two SSTC structures.
- A link i E g(S,T) can be either of type t or t
sn st
</construct>
<bodyText confidence="0.6158638">
which defines the synchronous correspondences
between nodes of tr in S, and nodes of tr in T.
■ t records the synchronous correspondences at
sn
level of nodes in S and T (i.e. lexical
</bodyText>
<figure confidence="0.8722355">
correspondences between specified nodes), and
3 for a comprehensive overview about EBMT, see Somers(1999)
Many-to-one
mapping
Elimination of
dominance
Inversion of
dominance
sn
A from the second SSTC as defined below:
st
■ A = { i1_j1 +...+ ik_jk +...+ ip_jp }  |ik_jk
st
t
</figure>
<construct confidence="0.975279666666667">
EY:STREE correspondence in co of the second
SSTC or (ik_jk) = (ik_jk) - (iu_jv) |iu &gt; ik ∧ jv &lt;_jh :
i.e. (iu_jv)C (ik_jk) which corresponds to an
incomplete subtree.
- The synchronous correspondence between terminal
nodes with X:SNODE = Y:STREE will be of both
</construct>
<bodyText confidence="0.90599875">
Note: The synchronous correspondences can be between
SSTCs that contain non-standard phenomena; i.e.
featursiation and discontinuity (crossed dependency). In
these cases the synchronous correspondence is strait
forward (following the above definitions); e.g. see Figure 4
and Figure 6.
The S-SSTC will be used to relate expressions of a
natural language to its associated translation in
another language. For convenience, we will call the
two languages source and target languages, although
S-SSTC is non-directional. S-SSTC is defined to
make such relation explicit. Figure 4 depicts a S-
SSTC for the English source sentence “John picks
the heavy box up” and its translation in the Malay
target sentence “John kutip kotak berat itu”. The
gray arrows indicate the correspondence between the
string and it representation tree within each of the
SSTCs, and the dot-gray arrows indicate the relations
(i.e. synchronous correspondence) of synchronization
between linguistic units of the source SSTC and the
target SSTC.
Synchronous (1-2+5-6,1-2) (0-6,0-5) (0-1,0-1)
correspondence t (0-1,0-1) (4-5,2-3) t (2-5,2-5) (2-3,4-5)
sn (3-4,3-4) (2-3,4-5) s t (3-4,3-4)
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.481041333333333">
snA
) t*(1-2+5-6,1-2) under the f synchronous
s t sn
</equation>
<bodyText confidence="0.997467">
correspondence. Whereas, the fact that “John picks
the heavy box up” is corresponds to “John kutip
</bodyText>
<figure confidence="0.996438844036697">
A = (X1, X2), where X1 and X2 are
normally
A or
A .
st
of type
sn
A ,
sn
s
sn
t
A ), where
- Ais a pair(
sn
A is from the first SSTC
sn
s
A is from the second SSTC .
and
sn
sequences of SNODE correspondences in co,
which may be empty.
A records the synchronous correspondences at
■
st
level of subtrees in S and T (i.e. structural
correspondences between subtrees), and normally
A = (Y1, Y2), where Y1 and Y2 are sequences of
st
STREE correspondences in co, which may be
empty.
- A synchronous correspondence link i E 41(S,T) can be
A,
st
s
st
t
A ), where
- Ais a pair(
st
A from the first SSTC and
st
s
t
- Ais represented by sets of intervals such that:
sn
■ A = { i1_j1 +...+ ik_jk +...+ ip_jp }  |ik_jk E
sn
s
X:SNODE correspondence in co of the first SSTC.
■ A = { i1_j1 +...+ ik_jk +...+ ip_jp }  |ik_jk E
sn
t
X:SNODE correspondence in co of the second
SSTC.
A = { i1_j1 +...+ ik_jk +...+ ip_jp }  |ik_jk
st
s
EY:STREE correspondence in co of the first
SSTC or (ik_jk) = (ik_jk) - (iu_jv) |iu &gt; ik ∧ jv &lt;_jh :
i.e. (iu_jv)C (ik_jk) which corresponds to an
incomplete subtree.
t
■
A and A correspondence such that
sn st sn st
A .
A =
Tree
picks[v] up[p]
(1-2+5-6/0-6)
John[n]
(0-1/0-1)
box[n]
(4-5/2-5)
the[det]
(2-3/2-3)
heavy[adj]
(3-4/3-4)
Tree
kutip[v]
( 1-2 /0-5)
kotak[n]
(2-3/ 2-5)
John[n]
(0-1/0-1)
berat[adj]
(3-4/3-4)
itu[det]
(4-5/4-5)
String
0John1kutip2kotak3berat4itu5
String
0John1picks2the3heavy4box5up6
A ,
st
of (
A ), where
st
A is STREE interval/s from the
st
s
t
s
source SSTC and
A is STREE interval/s from the
st
t
</figure>
<figureCaption confidence="0.993432">
Figure 4: A synchronous SSTC for the sentence “John picks the
heavy box up” and its Malay translation “John kutip kotak berat
itu”, together with the synchronous correspondence between them.
</figureCaption>
<bodyText confidence="0.751774428571429">
Based on the notation used in S-SSTC, Figure 4
illustrates the S-SSTC for the English sentence “John
picks the heavy box up” and its translation in the
Malay language “John kutip kotak berat itu”, with
the synchronous correspondence between them. The
synchronous correspondence is denoted in terms of
SNODE pairs for f and STREE pairs for ( . For
</bodyText>
<figure confidence="0.662041714285714">
sn st
f each pair is of (
sn
A ), where
sn
t
sn Ais SNODE
s
A is SNODE
sn
t
interval/s from the source SSTC and
interval/s from the target SSTC. As for f each pair is
st
target SSTC. For instance, as depicted in Figure 5,
the fact that “picks up” in the source corresponds to
“kutip” in the target is expressed by the pair
A ,
sn
s
( A ,
sn
kotak berat itu” is expressed by (
under the f synchronous correspondence. Also the
st
fact that “box” in the source corresponds to “kotak”
in the target under the pair (
s
( synchronous correspondence. Whereas, the phrase
sn“the heavy box” is corresponds to the phrase “kotak
berat itu” in the target is expressed by ( ( , ( ) ⇔(2-
st st
s t
5,2-5) under the ( synchronous correspondence.
st
</figure>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.9977865" genericHeader="method">
4. HANDLING NON-STANDARD CASES
WITH S-SSTC
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999390192307692">
As mentioned earlier, there are some non-standard
phenomena exist between different languages, that
cause challenges for synchronized formalisms. In this
Section, we will describe some example cases, which
are drawn from the problem of using synchronous
formalisms to define translations between languages
(e.g. Shieber (1994) cases). Due to lack of space we
will only brief on some of these non-standard cases
without going into the details.
Figure 4 illustrates a case where the English sentence
has non-standard cases of featurisation, crossed
dependency and a many-to-one synchronous
correspondence in “picks up”. Another case is
reordering of words in the phrases, which is clear in
the phrase “thedet heavyadj boxn” and it corresponding
phrase “kotakn beratadj itudet” in the target.
Figure 5, shows two non-standard cases between
languages; e.g. French and English. First, the case of
many-to-one correspondence, where a word (single
node) in one language corresponds to a phrase
(subtree) in the other, namely, the adverbial
“hopefully” is translated into the French phrase “On
esp6re que”. Second, a case of argument swap
(reordering of subtrees) in the English “Kim misses
Dale” and its corresponding translation “Dale
manqu6 a Kim” in French.
</bodyText>
<figureCaption confidence="0.857500909090909">
Figure 5: Many-to-one correspondence and arguments swapping corres-
pondence in the French sentence “On esp6re que Dale manqu6 a Kim”
and its corresponding English sentence “Hopefully Kim misses Dale”.
Figure 6 describes the cases of clitic climbing in
French and the non-projective correspondence (i.e.
crossed dependency). It shows the flexibility of SSTC
and the proposed S-SSTC in handling such popular
cases.
Figure 6: Cliticized sentence: the French sentence “Pierre ne l ‘a pas
vu” and its corresponding English sentence “Peter has not seen it”.
Figure 7 exemplifies a case where the number of
</figureCaption>
<bodyText confidence="0.740584375">
nodes in the synchronized SSTCs or subSSTCs is the
same, but they exhibit different structures. Nodes
participating in the domination relationship in one
SSTC may be mapped to nodes neither of which
dominates the other (i.e. elimination of dominance).
Another even more extreme relationship between the
synchronized pair involving inverted correspondences
is exemplified in Figure 8.
</bodyText>
<figureCaption confidence="0.992931">
Figure 7: Elimination of dominance, in the French sentence
“le docteur lui soign6 les dents” and its corresponding
English sentence “the doctor treats his teeth”.
Figure 8: Inversion of dominance in the French sentence
“Jean monte la rue en courant” and its corresponding
English sentence “John runs up the street”.
</figureCaption>
<figure confidence="0.984367112903226">
Tree
manqué a[v]
(4-5/0-6)
Tree
misses[v]
(2-3/0-4)
espére[v]
(1-2/ 0-3)
Dale[n]
(3-4 /3-4)
Kim[n]
(5-6 /5-6)
hopefully [adv]
(0-1/ 0-1)
(1-2/1-2) (3-4/3-4)
Kim[n] Dale[n]
on[n] que [c]
(0-1/0-1) (2-3/2-3)
String
String
0On1 espere2 que3 Dale4 manqu6 a5
Kim6
0Hopefully1 Kim2misses3Dale4
Synchronous
correspondence
(4-5,2-3)
(5-6,1-2)
(0-6,0-4) (0-3,0-1)
(3-4,3-4)
f
sn
(5-6,1-2)
t
s t
(3-4,3-4)
Synchronous
correspondence
(0-6,0-5)
(0-1+2-4+5-6,0-2+3-5)
(2-3,4-5)
�
sn
(3-4+5-6,1-2+3-4)
(1-2+4-5,2-3)
(0-1,0-1)
t
s t
(2-3,4-5) (0-1,0-1)
String
Tree
0Pierre1ne2 l’3a4pas5 vu
a vu [v]
(3-4+5-6/0-1+2-4+5-6)
Pierre[n]
(0-1/0-1)
ne pas [neg]
(1-2+4-5/0-6)
l’ [n]
(2-3/2-3)
6
String
Tree
0Peter1has2not3seen4it5
Peter[n]
(0-1/0-1)
has seen[v]
(1-2+3-4/0-2+3-5)
not [neg]
( 2-3/0-5)
(4-5/4-5)
it[n]
Synchronous
correspondence
(3-4,2-3)
t
(2-3,3-4)
(5-6,4-5)
sn
t s t
(2-6,2-5)
(2-3+4-6,3-5)
String
Tree
...2lui3soign64les5dents6
lui[pr] dents [n]
(2-3/2-3) (5-6/4-6)
soigné [v]
(3-4/2-6)
les[det]
(4-5/4-6)
Tree
String
...2treats3 his4 teeth5
treats[v]
(2-3/2-5)
teeth[n]
(4-5/3-5)
his [pr]
(3-4/3-4)
Synchronous t (1-2,2-3) � (1-2+4-6,1-3)
correspondence sn st
(4-6,1-2)
Tree
runs[v]
(1-2/1-3)
up[p]
(2-3/2-3)
Tree
monte[v]
(1-2/1-2+4-6)
en courant[adv]
(4-6/4-6)
String
...1monte2...4en5courant6
String
... 1runs2 up3 ...
st( ) ⇔(0-6,0-5)
t
( ,
st
s
� ,
sn
sn�
</figure>
<equation confidence="0.8304585">
) ⇔(4-5,2-3) in the
t
</equation>
<bodyText confidence="0.979109125">
Figure 9, depicts the case when partial subtree/s from
the first SSTC has/ve a synchronous correspondence
with partial subtree/s in the second SSTC. The
German word “beschenkte” corresponds to the
English phrase “give present” which is a partial
subtree from the tree rooted by the word “give” in the
English SSTC. This synchronous correspondence is
recorded under the f where the operation (-: minus)
</bodyText>
<figure confidence="0.944906142857143">
st
is used to calculate the Y:STREE interval/s for the
partial subtree/s.
Tree [v] Tree
(1-2/0-4)
beschenkte
give[v] -6)
(1-2/0
Er [n] reichlich[adj] He [n]
(0-1/0-1)
present [n]
(0-1/0-1) (3-4/3-4) John [n] (5-6/3-6)
Hans [n] (2-3/2-3)
(2-3/2-3) an[det] expansive[adj]
(3-4/3-4) (4-5/4-5)
String String
0Er1beschenkte2Hans3reichlich4 0He1gave2John3an4expansive5
5present6
Synchronous Q (0-1,0-1) (0-4,0-6)(3-4,4-5) (0-1,0-1)
correspondence �!, (2-3,2-3) (2-3,2-3) (0-4 - 0-1 - 2-3 - 3-
sn(3-4,4-5) st 4, 0-6 - 0-1 - 2-3 - 3-4 - 4-5)
</figure>
<figureCaption confidence="0.993025">
Figure 9: Partial subtree/s correspondence: the German sentence “Er
beschenkte Hans reichlich” and its corresponding English sentence
“He gave John an expensive present”; i.e. the use of (-) operation to
calculate the Y:STREE interval.
</figureCaption>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.999054333333333" genericHeader="method">
5. SYNCHRONOUS CORRESPOND-
ENCE CONSTRAINTS BETWEEN
NATURAL LANGUAGES (NLs)
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999855625">
As we mentioned in Section 2, in the SSTC the
correspondences between the surface text and the
associated representation tree structure are ensured by
means of intervals; i.e. (X:SNODE, Y:STREE). This
explicitly indicates which word/s of the text
correspond/s to which node in the tree. For describing
a NL using SSTC, a set of constraints were defined to
govern such correspondences (Lepage, 1994):
</bodyText>
<listItem confidence="0.9297949">
- X:SNODE and Y:STREE intervals are governed by the
following constraints:
i) Global correspondence: an entire tree corresponds to
an entire sentence.
ii) Inclusion: a subtree which is part of another subtree
T, must correspond to a substring in the substring
corresponding to T.
iii) Membership: a node in a subtree T, must correspond
to a word which is member of the substring
corresponding to T.
</listItem>
<bodyText confidence="0.96177325">
In a similar manner, in order to describe the
synchronous correspondences between NLs using S-
SSTC, we define a set of constraints to govern the
synchronous correspondences between the different
NLs. These constraints will be used to make
explicitly the synchronous correspondences in a
natural manner.
- f and f are governed by the following constraints:
</bodyText>
<figure confidence="0.4285428">
sn st
■ Singleness: A node N which has a synchronization
correspondence, can participate in one and only one f
E A , and one and only one f E A . This means
sn st
</figure>
<construct confidence="0.4415675">
allowing one-to-one, one-to-many and many-to-many,
but the mappings do not overlap.
</construct>
<listItem confidence="0.567515">
■ Dominance: Given two subtrees S and T, there is a
</listItem>
<bodyText confidence="0.998381357142857">
Note that these constraints can be used to license only
the linguistically meaningful synchronous corr-
espondences between the two SSTCs of the S-SSTC
(i.e. between the two languages). For instance, when
building translation units in EBMT approaches
(Richardson et al., 2001), (Aramaki, 2001), (Al-
Adhaileh &amp;Tang, 1999), (Sato &amp; Nagao, 1990),
(Sato, 1991), (Sadler &amp; Vendelmans, 1990), etc.,
where S-SSTC can be used to represent the entries of
the BKB or when S-SSTC used as an annotation
schema to find the translation correspondences
(lexical and structural correspondences) for transfer-
rules’ extraction from parallel parsed corpus
(Menezes &amp; Richardson, 2001), (Watanabe et al.,
</bodyText>
<figure confidence="0.994717692307692">
A =
A correspondence pairs
■ Inclusion: Given two
1
st
st
A and
A C
A .
A C
inclusion constraint if and only if
st
st
st
st
1
2
s
s
t1
t2
A,
st
s
st
t
A )
■ Membership: Given two correspondence pairs (
A,
sn
E A and (
st
A ) E A , A and A satisfy the
sn sn sn st
s
t
A C
membership constraints if and only if
A and
st
s
sn
s
A,
st
s
st
t1
A,
st
s
A ),
st
t2
(
1
2
A = (
A ) and
A and
1
st
st
A satisfy the
2
2
st
A between S and T satisfy the
st
correspondence � E
A
st
dominance constraints if and only if b&apos; � CSTREE(S)
correspond to b&apos; � C STREE(T).
■ Globality: Given a S-SSTC, there must be A E
A )E
st
A,
st
only if (
A such that
st
A = STREE(Rs) :
st
s
t
s
A = STREE(Rt) :
st
t
INT(String) in the first SSTC, and
</figure>
<figureCaption confidence="0.540406142857143">
satisfies the globality constraints between the the root
node Rs of the entire tree in the first SSTC and the root
node Rt of the entire tree in the second SSTC, if and
INT(String) in the second SSTC. This mean the whole
tree in the first SSTC corresponds to the whole tree in
the second SSTC, and the whole string in the first SSTC
corresponds to the whole string in the second SSTC).
</figureCaption>
<figure confidence="0.77553225">
A C A . This means the lexical correspondences are
sn st
t t
always members in the structural correspondences.
</figure>
<bodyText confidence="0.997322333333333">
2000), (Meyers et al., 2000), (Matsumoto et al., 1993)
and (kaji et al., 1992). Note that the grammar
alignment rules used in (Menezes &amp; Richardson,
2001) can be reformulated using these constraints to
construct the transfer mappings from a synchronous
source-target example.
</bodyText>
<figureCaption confidence="0.656222">
Figure 10 shows an example from Menezes and
Richardson (2001), the logical form for the Spanish-
English pair: (“En Informacidn del hipervinculo, haga
clic en la direccidn del hipervinculo”, “Under
Hyperlink Information, click the hyperlink address”).
Figure 10: (a) the lexical correspondences, (b) the structural corres-
pondences after applying the constraints.
</figureCaption>
<bodyText confidence="0.999980816326531">
Recently, the development of machine translation
systems requires a substantial amount of translation
knowledge typically embodied in the bilingual
corpora. For instance, the development of translation
systems based on transfer mappings (rules or
examples) that automatically extracted from these
bilingual corpora. All these systems typically first
obtain a tree structures (normally a predicate-
argument or a dependency structure) for both the
source and target sentences. From the resulting
structures, lexical and structural correspondences
between the two structures are extracted, which are
then presented as a set of examples in a bilingual
knowledge bank (BKB) or transfer rules for
translation process.
However, what has so far been lacking is a schema or
a framework to annotate and express such extracted
lexical and structural correspondences in a flexible
and powerful manner. The proposed S-SSTC
annotation schema can fulfill this need, and it is
flexible enough to handle different type of relations
that may happen between different languages’
structures. S-SSTC very well suited for the
construction of a BKB, which is needed for the
EBMT applications. Al-Adhaileh and Tang (2001)
presented an approach for constructing a BKB based
on the S-SSTC.
In S-SSTC, the synchronous correspondence is
defined in a way to ensure a flexible representation
for both lexical and structural correspondences: i-
Node–to–node correspondence (lexical correspond-
ence), which is recorded in terms of pair of intervals
(Xs,Xt) where Xs and Xt is SNODE interval/s for the
source and the target SSTC respectively, ii- Subtree–
to–Subtree correspondence (structural correspond-
ence), which is very much needed for relating the two
different languages at a level higher than the lexical
level, a level of phrases. It is recorded in terms of
pair of intervals (Ys,Yt) where Ys and Yt is STREE
interval/s for the source and the target SSTC
respectively.
Furthermore, the SSTC structure can easily be
extended to keep multiple levels of linguistic
information, if they are considered important to
enhance the performance of the machine translation
system (i.e. Features transfer). For instance, each
node representing a word in the annotated tree
structure can be tagged with part of speech (POS),
semantic features and morphological features.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.999586" genericHeader="conclusions">
6. CONCLUSION
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.993587428571429">
The proposed S-SSTC is not limited for the case
discussed here (i.e. MT), any system need to describe
two language structures and the synchronization
relation between them, can used S-SSTC as
annotation schema for that. This is for example the
case for presenting the syntax-semantics interface
between different languages. S-SSTC is a flexible
schema, which is able to handle non-standard
phenomena that may occur between different
languages. We conclude this paper with some
interesting observations on the synchronous SSTC:
i- A natural way to put the representation trees (i.e. a
text and its translation) in a very fine-grained
correspondence.
ii- A natural way to specify bi-directional structural
transfer, as SSTC is used to specify structural
analyzers and generators (i.e. bi-directional).
iii- Synchronous SSTC can be easily extended to
record the correspondences between more than
two languages, hopefully with transitive property,
especially in constructing multilingual knowledge
banks (MKB) (i.e. synchronization between
multiple languages).
iv- Synchronous SSTC inherits from the SSTC the
independence from the choice of the tree structure
and linguistic theories. Also the ability of handling
the non-standard cases in Natural language and
between different languages.
</bodyText>
<figure confidence="0.999522808219178">
Informaci6n (en)
(0-2/0-2)
usted(Dsub)
(-,&apos;-) clic (Dobj)
(5-6/5-6)
Hacer
(4-5/0-11)
Hyperlink-
Information
(under)
(0-3/0-3)
address(Dobj)
(6-7/5-7)
Hyperlink(Mod)
(5-6/5-6)
Informaci6n (en)
(0-2/0-2)
Direcci6n(en la)
(6-9/6-11)
you(Dsub)
((D/(D)
Hipervinculo(de)
(9-11/9-11)
usted(Dsub)
(-,&apos;-) clic (Dobj)
(5-6/5-6)
Hipervinculo(de)
(2-4/2-4)
0En1Informaci6n2del3hipervinculo4haga5
clic6en7la8direcci6n9del10hipervinculo11
0Under1Hyperlink2Information3
click4 the5hyperlink6address7
Hacer
(4-5/0-11)
Hipervinculo(de)
(2-4/2-4)
0En1Informaci6n2del3hipervinculo4haga5
clic6en7la8direcci6n9del10hipervinculo11
Hyperlink-
Information
(under)
(0-3/0-3)
address(Dobj)
(6-7/5-7)
Hyperlink(Mod)
(5-6/5-6)
0Under1Hyperlink2Information3
click4 the5hyperlink6address7
Direcci6n(en la)
(6-9/6-11)
Hipervinculo(de)
(9-11/9-11)
Click
(3-4/0-7)
Click
(3-4/0-7)
you(Dsub)
((D/(D)
Synchronous
correspondence
(9-11,5-6)
(0-11,0-7)
(6-11,5-7)
(0-4,0-3)
(9-11,5-6)
�
sn
i
s t
(-, -)
(-, -)
(5-6,3-4)
(6-9,6-7)
</figure>
<bodyText confidence="0.9943157">
v- The transfer between two languages, such as
source and target languages in machine
translation, can be done by putting directly into
correspondence large elementary units without
going through some interlingual representation
and without major changes to the source and
target formalisms.
Also a GUI editor has been implemented for view,
edit, create and correct the S-SSTC components, as
illustrated in Figure 11.
</bodyText>
<figureCaption confidence="0.976585">
Figure 11: Synchronous SSTC Editor.
</figureCaption>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.999222" genericHeader="references">
REFERENCES
</sectionHeader>
<reference confidence="0.998917147058824">
Abeill6, A., Schabes, Y. and Joshi, A. (1990). Using
lexicalized TAGs for machine translation. In Proceedings of
the 13th International Conference on Computational
Linguistics (COLINGS’90), Helsinki, Finland, pp 1-6.
Al-Adhaileh, M.H. and Tang, E.K. (1999). Example-Based
Machine Translation Based on the Synchronous SSTC
Annotation Schema. In Proceedings of Machine Translation
Summit VII, Singapore, pp 244-249.
Al-Adhaileh, M.H. and Tang, E.K. (2001). Converting a
Bilingual Dictionary into a Bilingual Knowledge Bank
Based on the Synchronous SSTC Annotation Schema. In
Proceedings of Machine Translation Summit VIII. Spain, pp
351-356.
Boitet, C. and Zaharin, Y. (1988). Representation trees and
string-tree correspondences. In Proceedings of the 12th
International Conference on Computational Linguistics
(COLINGS-88), Budapest. Hungary, August, pp 59-64.
Harbusch, K. and Poller, P. (2000), Non-Isomorphic
Synchronous TAGs. In Abeill6 A. and Rambow O. (eds.).
Tree Adjoining Grammars: Formal Properties, Linguistic
Theory and Applications, CSLI, Stanford, California/USA,
2000.
Kahane, S. (2001). What is a Natural Language and How to
Describe It? Meaning-Text Approaches in Contrast with
Generative Approaches. In Proceedings of the 2nd
International conference of Computational Linguistics and
Intelligent Text Processing (CICLing), Mexico, pp 1-17.
Kaji H., Kida Y., and Morimoto Y. (1992), Learning
Translation Templates from Bilingual Text. In Proceedings
of the 14th International Conference on Computational
Linguistics (COLING-92), France, pp 672-678.
Lepage, Y. (1994). Texts and Structures – Pattern-matching
and Distances, ATR report TR-IT-0049, Kyoto, Japan.
Matsumoto, Y., Ishimoto H., and Utsuro, T. (1993). Structural
Matching of Parallel Texts. In Proceedings of the 31th
annual meeting of Association for Computational
Linguistics (ACL-93), pp 23-30.
Mel&apos;cuk T. (1997). Vers une Linguistique Sens-Texte. Legon
inaugurale au Coll�ge de France, Paris: Coll�ge de France.
Menezes, A. and Richardson, S. (2001). A Best-first
Algorithm for Automatic Extraction of Transfer Mappings
from Bilingual Corpora. In the workshop on Data-Driven
Machine Translation, at the 38th Annual Meeting of the
Association for Computational Linguistic (ACL 2001),
Toulouse, France.
Meyers A., Kosaka M., and Grishman R. (2000). Chart-based
Transfer Rule Application in Machine Translation. In
Proceedings of the 18th International Conference on
Computational Linguistics (COLING 2000). Saarbracken,
Germany / Luxembourg.
Meyers, A., Yangarber, R. and Grishman R. (1996).
Alignment of Shared Forests for Bilingual Corpora. In
Proceedings of the 16th International Conference on
Computational Linguistics (COLING-96), Copenhagen,
Denmark, pp 459-465.
Milicevic J. (2001). A short guide to the Meaning-Text
linguistic theory. In Alexander Gelbukh (ed.),
Computational Linguistics and Intelligent Text Processing,
Coleccion en Ciencias de Computacion, Fondo de Cultura
Economica- IPN - UNAM, Mexico.
Rambow, O. and Satta, G. (1996). Synchronous Models of
language. In Proceedings of the 34th Meeting of the
Association for Computational Linguistics (ACL-96), Santa
Cruz, CA, USA.
Richardson S., Dolan W., Menezes A. and Pinkham J. (2001).
Achieving commercial-quality translation with example-
based methods. In Proceedings of Machine Translation
SUMMIT VIII, Spain, pp 293-297.
Sadler V. and Vendelmans, R. (1990). Pilot Implementation of
a Bilingual Knowledge Bank. In Proceedings of the 13th
International Conference on Computational Linguistics
(COLING-90), Vol. 3, Helsinki, Finland, pp 449-451.
Sato S. and Nagao M. (1990). Towards Memory-based
Translation. In Proceedings of the 13th International
Conference on Computational Linguistics (COLING-90),
Vol. 3, Helsinki, Fenland, pp 247-252.
Sato, S. (1991). Example-Based Machine Translation. Ph.D.
thesis, Kyoto University, Japan.
Shieber, S. (1994). Restricting the Weak Generative Capacity
of Synchronous Tree Adjoining Grammar. Computational
Intelligence, 10(4): 371-385.
Shieber, S. and Schabes, Y. (1990). Synchronous Tree
Adjoining Grammars. In Proceedings of the 13th
International Conference on Computational Linguistics
(COLINGS-90), Helsinki, Finland, pp 253-258.
Somers, H. (1999). Review article: Example-based Machine
Translation, Machine Translation, 14: 113-157.
Tang E. K. (1994). Natural Language Analysis in Machine
Translation (MT) Based on the String-Tree Correspondence
Grammar (STCG). PhD. thesis, Universiti Sains Malaysia,
Penang, Malaysia.
Tang, E. K. and Zaharin, Y. (1995). Handling Crossed
Dependencies with the STCG. In Proceedings of
NLPRS’95, Seoul, Korea.
Watanabe H., Kurohashi S., and Aramaki E. (2000). Finding
Structural Correspondences from Bilingual Parsed Corpus
for Corpus-based Translation. In Proceedings of the 18th
International Conference on Computational Linguistics
(COLING 2000), Luxembourg/Saarbruecken, Germany.
Zolkovski, A. and Mel&apos;cuk, T. (1965). On a Possible Method
an Instruments for Semantic Synthesis (of texts). Scientific
and Technological Information, 6: 23-28.
</reference>
<figure confidence="0.996434">
Snode Correspondence: {(0-1)+(1-2),(0-1)} {(3-4),(1-2)} {(4-5),(2-3)} {(5-6),(3-4)}
{(6-7),(6-7)} {(7-8),(4-5)} {(8-9),(7-8)} {(9-11),(9-11)}
Stree Correspondence: {(0-11),(0-10)} {(2-4),(1-2)} {(4-11),(2-10)} {(5-11),(3-10)}
there[ex] fire[n]
there is a fire in a big hotel in
Pudu Road
a[det]
a[det]
is[va]
hotel[n]
in[prep]
big[a]
{(8-11),(7-11)} {(5-11)-(8-11),(3-10)-(7-10)}
in[prep]
Pudu Road[n]
yang besar di Jalan Pudu
ada kebakaran di sebuah hotel
sebuah[det]
kebakaran[n]
ada[va]
yang[det]
hotel[n]
di[prep]
besar[a]
Jalan Pudu[n]
di[prep]
</figure>
</variant>
</algorithm>
<algorithm name="ParsHed" version="110505">
<variant no="0" confidence="0.030269">
<title confidence="0.987135">A SYNCHRONIZATION STRUCTURE OF SSTC AND APPLICATIONS IN MACHINE TRANSLATION</title>
<author confidence="0.942207">H MOSLEH</author>
<affiliation confidence="0.966102333333333">Computer Aided Translation School of Computer Universiti Sains</affiliation>
<address confidence="0.938386">11800 PENANG,</address>
<email confidence="0.994775">mosleh@cs.usm.my,mosleh@hotmail.com</email>
<author confidence="0.789736">TANG ENYA</author>
<affiliation confidence="0.942526333333333">Computer Aided Translation School of Computer Universiti Sains</affiliation>
<address confidence="0.981881">11800 PENANG,</address>
<email confidence="0.952499">enyakong@cs.usm.my</email>
<affiliation confidence="0.81601625">ZAHARIN Computer Aided Translation School of Computer Universiti Sains</affiliation>
<address confidence="0.969541">11800 PENANG,</address>
<email confidence="0.912405">zarin@cs.usm.my</email>
<abstract confidence="0.999548555555556">In this paper, a flexible annotation schema called (SSTC) is introduced. In order to describe the correspondence between different languages, we propose a variant of SSTC called synchronous SSTC (S-SSTC). We will also describe how S-SSTC provides the flexibility to treat some of the non-standard cases, which are problematic to other synchronous formalisms. The proposed S-SSTC schema is well suited to describe the correspondence between different languages, in particular, relating a language with its translation in another language (i.e. in Machine Translation). Also it can be used as annotation for translation systems that automatically extract transfer mappings (rules or examples) from bilingual corpora. The S-SSTC is very well suited for the construction of a Bilingual Knowledge Bank (BKB), where the examples are kept in form of S-SSTCs.</abstract>
<note confidence="0.20847">text, Structured String-Tree Correspondence (SSTC), Synchronous SSTC, Bilingual Knowledge Bank (BKB), Tree Bank Annotation Schema.</note>
</variant>
</algorithm>
<algorithm name="ParsCit" version="110505">
<citationList>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>A Abeill6</author>
<author>Y Schabes</author>
<author>A Joshi</author>
</authors>
<title>Using lexicalized TAGs for machine translation.</title>
<date>1990</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the 13th International Conference on Computational Linguistics (COLINGS’90),</booktitle>
<pages>1--6</pages>
<location>Helsinki, Finland,</location>
<marker>Abeill6, Schabes, Joshi, 1990</marker>
<rawString>Abeill6, A., Schabes, Y. and Joshi, A. (1990). Using lexicalized TAGs for machine translation. In Proceedings of the 13th International Conference on Computational Linguistics (COLINGS’90), Helsinki, Finland, pp 1-6.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>M H Al-Adhaileh</author>
<author>E K Tang</author>
</authors>
<title>Example-Based Machine Translation Based on the Synchronous SSTC Annotation Schema.</title>
<date>1999</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of Machine Translation Summit VII, Singapore,</booktitle>
<pages>244--249</pages>
<contexts>
<context position="12985" citStr="Al-Adhaileh &amp; Tang, 1999" startWordPosition="1946" endWordPosition="1949">nchronous Structured String-Tree Correspondence (S-SSTC)) to realize additional power and flexibility in expressing structural correspondences at the level of language sentence pairs. For example, such schema can serve as a mean to represent translation examples, or find structural correspondences for the purpose of transfer grammar learning (Menezes &amp; Richardson, 2001), (Aramaki et al., 2001), (Watanabe et al., 2000), (Meyers et al., 2000), (Matsumoto et al., 1993), (kaji et al., 1992), and example-base machine translation EBMT3 (Sato &amp; Nagao, 1990), (Sato, 1991), (Richardson et al., 2001), (Al-Adhaileh &amp; Tang, 1999). 3.1 The Synchronous SSTC In this section, we will discuss the definition and the formal properties of S-SSTC. A S-SSTC consists of a pair of SSTCs with an additional synchronization relation between them. The use of S-SSTC is motivated by the desire to describe not only the correspondence between the text and its representation structure in one language (i.e. SSTC) but also the correspondence between two languages (synchronous correspondence). Definitions: - Let each of S and T be SSTC which consists of a triple (st, tr, co), where st is a string in one language, tr is its associated represe</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Al-Adhaileh, Tang, 1999</marker>
<rawString>Al-Adhaileh, M.H. and Tang, E.K. (1999). Example-Based Machine Translation Based on the Synchronous SSTC Annotation Schema. In Proceedings of Machine Translation Summit VII, Singapore, pp 244-249.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>M H Al-Adhaileh</author>
<author>E K Tang</author>
</authors>
<title>Converting a Bilingual Dictionary into a Bilingual Knowledge Bank Based on the Synchronous SSTC Annotation Schema.</title>
<date>2001</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of Machine Translation Summit VIII. Spain,</booktitle>
<pages>351--356</pages>
<contexts>
<context position="29202" citStr="Al-Adhaileh and Tang (2001)" startWordPosition="4635" endWordPosition="4638">s are extracted, which are then presented as a set of examples in a bilingual knowledge bank (BKB) or transfer rules for translation process. However, what has so far been lacking is a schema or a framework to annotate and express such extracted lexical and structural correspondences in a flexible and powerful manner. The proposed S-SSTC annotation schema can fulfill this need, and it is flexible enough to handle different type of relations that may happen between different languages’ structures. S-SSTC very well suited for the construction of a BKB, which is needed for the EBMT applications. Al-Adhaileh and Tang (2001) presented an approach for constructing a BKB based on the S-SSTC. In S-SSTC, the synchronous correspondence is defined in a way to ensure a flexible representation for both lexical and structural correspondences: iNode–to–node correspondence (lexical correspondence), which is recorded in terms of pair of intervals (Xs,Xt) where Xs and Xt is SNODE interval/s for the source and the target SSTC respectively, ii- Subtree– to–Subtree correspondence (structural correspondence), which is very much needed for relating the two different languages at a level higher than the lexical level, a level of ph</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Al-Adhaileh, Tang, 2001</marker>
<rawString>Al-Adhaileh, M.H. and Tang, E.K. (2001). Converting a Bilingual Dictionary into a Bilingual Knowledge Bank Based on the Synchronous SSTC Annotation Schema. In Proceedings of Machine Translation Summit VIII. Spain, pp 351-356.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>C Boitet</author>
<author>Y Zaharin</author>
</authors>
<title>Representation trees and string-tree correspondences.</title>
<date>1988</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the 12th International Conference on Computational Linguistics (COLINGS-88),</booktitle>
<pages>59--64</pages>
<location>Budapest. Hungary,</location>
<contexts>
<context position="2008" citStr="Boitet &amp; Zaharin, 1988" startWordPosition="270" endWordPosition="273">SSTCs. KEYWORDS: parallel text, Structured String-Tree Correspondence (SSTC), Synchronous SSTC, Bilingual Knowledge Bank (BKB), Tree Bank Annotation Schema. 1. INTRODUCTION There is now a consensus about the fact that natural language should be described as correspondences between different levels of representation. Much of theoretical linguistics can be formulated in a very natural manner as stating correspondences (translations) between layers of representation structures (Rambow &amp; Satta, 1996). In this paper, a flexible annotation schema called Structured String-Tree Correspondence (SSTC) (Boitet &amp; Zaharin, 1988) will be introduced to capture a natural language text, its corresponding abstract linguistic representation and the mapping (correspondence) between these two. The correspondence between the string and its associated representation tree structure is defined in terms of the sub-correspondence between parts of the string (substrings) and parts of the tree structure (subtrees), which can be interpreted for both analysis and generation. Such correspondence is defined in a way that is able to handle some non-standard cases (e.g. non-projective correspondence). While synchronous systems are becomin</context>
<context position="5859" citStr="Boitet &amp; Zaharin (1988)" startWordPosition="832" endWordPosition="835">rtant to specify the sub-correspondences between parts of the string (substrings) and parts of the tree structure (subtrees), which can be interpreted for both analysis and generation in NLP. It is well known that many linguistic constructions are not projective (e.g. scrambling, cross serial dependencies, etc.). Hence, it is very much desired to define the correspondence in a way to be able to handle the non-standard cases (e.g. non-projective correspondence), see Figure 1. Towards this aim, a flexible annotation structure called Structured String-Tree Correspondence (SSTC) was introduced in Boitet &amp; Zaharin (1988) to record the string of terms, its associated representation structure and the mapping between the two, which is expressed by the sub-correspondences recorded as part of a SSTC. 1 The Meaning-Text Theory (MTT) was put forward in (Zolkovski &amp; Mel&apos;cuk (1965), in the framework of research in Machine translation. More presentations of MTT can be found in (Mel&apos;cuk, 1997) and (Mili&amp;evi6, 2001). 2.1 The SSTC Annotation Structure The SSTC is a general structure that can associate an arbitrary tree structure to string in a language as desired by the annotator to be the interpretation structure of the </context>
<context position="8595" citStr="Boitet &amp; Zaharin (1988)" startWordPosition="1276" endWordPosition="1279">ncy tree together with the correspondences between substrings of the sentence and subtrees of the tree. Figure 2 illustrates the sentence “John picks the box up” with its corresponding SSTC. It contains a nonprojective correspondence. An interval is assigned to each word in the sentence, i.e. (0-1) for “John”, (1-2) for “picks”, (2-3) for “the&amp;quot;, (3-4) for “box” and (4-5) for “up”. A substring in the sentence that corresponds to a node in the representation tree is denoted by assigning the interval of the substring to SNODE of 2 These definitions are based on the discussion in (Tang, 1994) and Boitet &amp; Zaharin (1988). John John box the.box the NP the.box the box VP V pick up picks.up Figure 1: The correspondence between the string “he picks the box up” and its representation tree (dependency tree and phrasestructure tree), together with the sub-correspondences between the substrings and subtrees. Tree pick up John box the String John picks the box up S Tree NP VP John V NP pick up the box String John picks the box up NP John John pick up picks.up picks[v] up[p] String the[det] (2-3/2-3) 0John 1picks2 1picks2 the3box u5 4up5 ( 12+45 1-2+4-5 Tree /0-5) John[n] (0-1/0-1) box [n] (3-4/2-4) String the[det] (2-</context>
<context position="10061" citStr="Boitet &amp; Zaharin (1988)" startWordPosition="1516" endWordPosition="1519">e string with the similar intervals.The correspondence between subtrees and substrings are denoted by the interval assigned to the STREE of each node, e.g. the subtree rooted at node “picks up” with STREE interval (0-5) corresponds to the whole sentence “John picks the box up”. The case depicted in Figure 2, describes how the SSTC structure treats some non-standard linguistic phenomena. The particle &amp;quot;up&amp;quot; is featurised into the verb &amp;quot;pick&amp;quot; and in discontinuous manner (e.g. &amp;quot;up&amp;quot; (4-5) in &amp;quot;pick-up&amp;quot; (1-2+4-5)) in the sentence &amp;quot;He picks the box up&amp;quot;. For more details on the proprieties of SSTC, see Boitet &amp; Zaharin (1988). 3. SYNCHRONOUS SSTC STRUCTURE Much of theoretical linguistics can be formulated in a very natural manner as stating correspondences (translations) between layers of representation structures (Rambow &amp; Satta, 1996), such as the relation between syntax and semantic. An analogous problem is to be defined in such a way that expresses the correspondence between a language and its translations in other languages. Therefore the synchronization of two adequate linguistic formalisms seems to be an appropriate representation for that. The idea of parallelized formalisms is widely used one, and one whi</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Boitet, Zaharin, 1988</marker>
<rawString>Boitet, C. and Zaharin, Y. (1988). Representation trees and string-tree correspondences. In Proceedings of the 12th International Conference on Computational Linguistics (COLINGS-88), Budapest. Hungary, August, pp 59-64.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>K Harbusch</author>
<author>P Poller</author>
</authors>
<title>Non-Isomorphic Synchronous TAGs.</title>
<date>2000</date>
<booktitle>In Abeill6 A. and Rambow O. (eds.). Tree Adjoining Grammars: Formal Properties, Linguistic Theory and Applications, CSLI,</booktitle>
<location>Stanford, California/USA,</location>
<contexts>
<context position="11614" citStr="Harbusch &amp; Poller, 2000" startWordPosition="1752" endWordPosition="1755">xample, for the purpose of immediate structural translation in machine translation (Abeill6 et al.,1990), (Harbusch &amp; Poller,1996), or for relating a syntactic TAG and semantic one for the same language (Shieber &amp; Schabes,1990). S-TAG is a variant of Tree Adjoining Grammar (TAG) introduced by (Shieber &amp; Schabes,1990) to characterize correspondences between tree adjoining languages. Considering the original definition of S-TAGs, one can see that it does not restrict the structures that can be produced in the source and target languages. It allows the construction of a non-TAL (Shieber, 1994), (Harbusch &amp; Poller, 2000). As a result, Shieber (1994) propose a restricted definition for S-TAG, namely, the IS-TAG for isomorphic S-TAG. In this case only TAL can be formed in each component. This isomorphism requirement is formally attractive, but for practical applications somewhat too strict. Also contrastive well-known translation phenomena exist in different languages, which cannot be expressed by IS-TAG, Figure 3 illustrates some examples (Shieber, 1994). Similar limitations also appear in synchronous CFGs (Harbusch &amp; Poller,1994). Figure 3: Kinds of relations between different languages, which are not isomorp</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Harbusch, Poller, 2000</marker>
<rawString>Harbusch, K. and Poller, P. (2000), Non-Isomorphic Synchronous TAGs. In Abeill6 A. and Rambow O. (eds.). Tree Adjoining Grammars: Formal Properties, Linguistic Theory and Applications, CSLI, Stanford, California/USA, 2000.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>S Kahane</author>
</authors>
<title>What is a Natural Language and How to Describe It? Meaning-Text Approaches in Contrast with Generative Approaches.</title>
<date>2001</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the 2nd International conference of Computational Linguistics and Intelligent Text Processing (CICLing), Mexico,</booktitle>
<pages>1--17</pages>
<contexts>
<context position="4531" citStr="Kahane, 2001" startWordPosition="635" endWordPosition="636">wo SSTCs, which is totally non-directional. In this paper, we will present the proposed S-SSTC – a schema well suited to describe the correspondence between two languages. The synchronous SSTC is flexible and able to handle the non-standard correspondence cases exist between different languages. It can also be used to facilitate automatic extraction of transfer mappings (rules or examples) from bilingual corpora. 2. STRUCTURED STRING-TREE CORRESPONDENCE (SSTC) From the Meaning-Text Theory (MTT)1 point of view, Natural Language (NL) is considered as a correspondence between meanings and texts (Kahane, 2001). The MTT point of view, even if it has been introduced in different formulations, is more or less accepted by the whole linguistic community. In this section, we stress on the fact that in order to describe Natural Language (NL) in a natural manner, three distinct components need to be expressed by the linguistic formalisms; namely, the text, its corresponding abstract linguistic representation and the mapping (correspondence) between these two. Actually, NL is not only a correspondence between different representation levels, as stressed by MTT postulates, but also a sub-correspondence betwe</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Kahane, 2001</marker>
<rawString>Kahane, S. (2001). What is a Natural Language and How to Describe It? Meaning-Text Approaches in Contrast with Generative Approaches. In Proceedings of the 2nd International conference of Computational Linguistics and Intelligent Text Processing (CICLing), Mexico, pp 1-17.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>H Kaji</author>
<author>Y Kida</author>
<author>Y Morimoto</author>
</authors>
<title>Learning Translation Templates from Bilingual Text.</title>
<date>1992</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the 14th International Conference on Computational Linguistics (COLING-92),</booktitle>
<pages>672--678</pages>
<marker>Kaji, Kida, Morimoto, 1992</marker>
<rawString>Kaji H., Kida Y., and Morimoto Y. (1992), Learning Translation Templates from Bilingual Text. In Proceedings of the 14th International Conference on Computational Linguistics (COLING-92), France, pp 672-678.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Y Lepage</author>
</authors>
<date>1994</date>
<booktitle>Texts and Structures – Pattern-matching and Distances, ATR report TR-IT-0049,</booktitle>
<location>Kyoto, Japan.</location>
<contexts>
<context position="24415" citStr="Lepage, 1994" startWordPosition="3803" endWordPosition="3804">and its corresponding English sentence “He gave John an expensive present”; i.e. the use of (-) operation to calculate the Y:STREE interval. 5. SYNCHRONOUS CORRESPONDENCE CONSTRAINTS BETWEEN NATURAL LANGUAGES (NLs) As we mentioned in Section 2, in the SSTC the correspondences between the surface text and the associated representation tree structure are ensured by means of intervals; i.e. (X:SNODE, Y:STREE). This explicitly indicates which word/s of the text correspond/s to which node in the tree. For describing a NL using SSTC, a set of constraints were defined to govern such correspondences (Lepage, 1994): - X:SNODE and Y:STREE intervals are governed by the following constraints: i) Global correspondence: an entire tree corresponds to an entire sentence. ii) Inclusion: a subtree which is part of another subtree T, must correspond to a substring in the substring corresponding to T. iii) Membership: a node in a subtree T, must correspond to a word which is member of the substring corresponding to T. In a similar manner, in order to describe the synchronous correspondences between NLs using SSSTC, we define a set of constraints to govern the synchronous correspondences between the different NLs. </context>
</contexts>
<marker>Lepage, 1994</marker>
<rawString>Lepage, Y. (1994). Texts and Structures – Pattern-matching and Distances, ATR report TR-IT-0049, Kyoto, Japan.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Y Matsumoto</author>
<author>H Ishimoto</author>
<author>T Utsuro</author>
</authors>
<title>Structural Matching of Parallel Texts.</title>
<date>1993</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the 31th annual meeting of Association for Computational Linguistics (ACL-93),</booktitle>
<pages>23--30</pages>
<contexts>
<context position="12830" citStr="Matsumoto et al., 1993" startWordPosition="1923" endWordPosition="1926">isomorphic. Due to these limitations, instead of investigating into the synchronization of two grammars, we propose a flexible annotation schema (i.e. Synchronous Structured String-Tree Correspondence (S-SSTC)) to realize additional power and flexibility in expressing structural correspondences at the level of language sentence pairs. For example, such schema can serve as a mean to represent translation examples, or find structural correspondences for the purpose of transfer grammar learning (Menezes &amp; Richardson, 2001), (Aramaki et al., 2001), (Watanabe et al., 2000), (Meyers et al., 2000), (Matsumoto et al., 1993), (kaji et al., 1992), and example-base machine translation EBMT3 (Sato &amp; Nagao, 1990), (Sato, 1991), (Richardson et al., 2001), (Al-Adhaileh &amp; Tang, 1999). 3.1 The Synchronous SSTC In this section, we will discuss the definition and the formal properties of S-SSTC. A S-SSTC consists of a pair of SSTCs with an additional synchronization relation between them. The use of S-SSTC is motivated by the desire to describe not only the correspondence between the text and its representation structure in one language (i.e. SSTC) but also the correspondence between two languages (synchronous corresponden</context>
<context position="27423" citStr="Matsumoto et al., 1993" startWordPosition="4374" endWordPosition="4377">(Rs) : st s t s A = STREE(Rt) : st t INT(String) in the first SSTC, and satisfies the globality constraints between the the root node Rs of the entire tree in the first SSTC and the root node Rt of the entire tree in the second SSTC, if and INT(String) in the second SSTC. This mean the whole tree in the first SSTC corresponds to the whole tree in the second SSTC, and the whole string in the first SSTC corresponds to the whole string in the second SSTC). A C A . This means the lexical correspondences are sn st t t always members in the structural correspondences. 2000), (Meyers et al., 2000), (Matsumoto et al., 1993) and (kaji et al., 1992). Note that the grammar alignment rules used in (Menezes &amp; Richardson, 2001) can be reformulated using these constraints to construct the transfer mappings from a synchronous source-target example. Figure 10 shows an example from Menezes and Richardson (2001), the logical form for the SpanishEnglish pair: (“En Informacidn del hipervinculo, haga clic en la direccidn del hipervinculo”, “Under Hyperlink Information, click the hyperlink address”). Figure 10: (a) the lexical correspondences, (b) the structural correspondences after applying the constraints. Recently, the dev</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Matsumoto, Ishimoto, Utsuro, 1993</marker>
<rawString>Matsumoto, Y., Ishimoto H., and Utsuro, T. (1993). Structural Matching of Parallel Texts. In Proceedings of the 31th annual meeting of Association for Computational Linguistics (ACL-93), pp 23-30.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>T Mel&apos;cuk</author>
</authors>
<title>Vers une Linguistique Sens-Texte. Legon inaugurale au Coll�ge de France, Paris: Coll�ge de France.</title>
<date>1997</date>
<contexts>
<context position="6228" citStr="Mel&apos;cuk, 1997" startWordPosition="893" endWordPosition="894">a way to be able to handle the non-standard cases (e.g. non-projective correspondence), see Figure 1. Towards this aim, a flexible annotation structure called Structured String-Tree Correspondence (SSTC) was introduced in Boitet &amp; Zaharin (1988) to record the string of terms, its associated representation structure and the mapping between the two, which is expressed by the sub-correspondences recorded as part of a SSTC. 1 The Meaning-Text Theory (MTT) was put forward in (Zolkovski &amp; Mel&apos;cuk (1965), in the framework of research in Machine translation. More presentations of MTT can be found in (Mel&apos;cuk, 1997) and (Mili&amp;evi6, 2001). 2.1 The SSTC Annotation Structure The SSTC is a general structure that can associate an arbitrary tree structure to string in a language as desired by the annotator to be the interpretation structure of the string, and more importantly is the facility to specify the correspondence between the string and the associated tree which can be nonprojective (Boitet &amp; Zaharin, 1988). These features are very much desired in the design of an annotation scheme, in particular for the treatment of linguistic phenomena, which are non-standard, e.g. crossed dependencies (Tang &amp; Zaharin</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Mel&apos;cuk, 1997</marker>
<rawString>Mel&apos;cuk T. (1997). Vers une Linguistique Sens-Texte. Legon inaugurale au Coll�ge de France, Paris: Coll�ge de France.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>A Menezes</author>
<author>S Richardson</author>
</authors>
<title>A Best-first Algorithm for Automatic Extraction of Transfer Mappings from Bilingual Corpora.</title>
<date>2001</date>
<booktitle>In the workshop on Data-Driven Machine Translation, at the 38th Annual Meeting of the Association for Computational Linguistic (ACL</booktitle>
<location>Toulouse, France.</location>
<contexts>
<context position="27706" citStr="Menezes and Richardson (2001)" startWordPosition="4417" endWordPosition="4420"> mean the whole tree in the first SSTC corresponds to the whole tree in the second SSTC, and the whole string in the first SSTC corresponds to the whole string in the second SSTC). A C A . This means the lexical correspondences are sn st t t always members in the structural correspondences. 2000), (Meyers et al., 2000), (Matsumoto et al., 1993) and (kaji et al., 1992). Note that the grammar alignment rules used in (Menezes &amp; Richardson, 2001) can be reformulated using these constraints to construct the transfer mappings from a synchronous source-target example. Figure 10 shows an example from Menezes and Richardson (2001), the logical form for the SpanishEnglish pair: (“En Informacidn del hipervinculo, haga clic en la direccidn del hipervinculo”, “Under Hyperlink Information, click the hyperlink address”). Figure 10: (a) the lexical correspondences, (b) the structural correspondences after applying the constraints. Recently, the development of machine translation systems requires a substantial amount of translation knowledge typically embodied in the bilingual corpora. For instance, the development of translation systems based on transfer mappings (rules or examples) that automatically extracted from these bil</context>
<context position="12732" citStr="Menezes &amp; Richardson, 2001" startWordPosition="1907" endWordPosition="1910">FGs (Harbusch &amp; Poller,1994). Figure 3: Kinds of relations between different languages, which are not isomorphic. Due to these limitations, instead of investigating into the synchronization of two grammars, we propose a flexible annotation schema (i.e. Synchronous Structured String-Tree Correspondence (S-SSTC)) to realize additional power and flexibility in expressing structural correspondences at the level of language sentence pairs. For example, such schema can serve as a mean to represent translation examples, or find structural correspondences for the purpose of transfer grammar learning (Menezes &amp; Richardson, 2001), (Aramaki et al., 2001), (Watanabe et al., 2000), (Meyers et al., 2000), (Matsumoto et al., 1993), (kaji et al., 1992), and example-base machine translation EBMT3 (Sato &amp; Nagao, 1990), (Sato, 1991), (Richardson et al., 2001), (Al-Adhaileh &amp; Tang, 1999). 3.1 The Synchronous SSTC In this section, we will discuss the definition and the formal properties of S-SSTC. A S-SSTC consists of a pair of SSTCs with an additional synchronization relation between them. The use of S-SSTC is motivated by the desire to describe not only the correspondence between the text and its representation structure in on</context>
<context position="26132" citStr="Menezes &amp; Richardson, 2001" startWordPosition="4080" endWordPosition="4083">used to license only the linguistically meaningful synchronous correspondences between the two SSTCs of the S-SSTC (i.e. between the two languages). For instance, when building translation units in EBMT approaches (Richardson et al., 2001), (Aramaki, 2001), (AlAdhaileh &amp;Tang, 1999), (Sato &amp; Nagao, 1990), (Sato, 1991), (Sadler &amp; Vendelmans, 1990), etc., where S-SSTC can be used to represent the entries of the BKB or when S-SSTC used as an annotation schema to find the translation correspondences (lexical and structural correspondences) for transferrules’ extraction from parallel parsed corpus (Menezes &amp; Richardson, 2001), (Watanabe et al., A = A correspondence pairs ■ Inclusion: Given two 1 st st A and A C A . A C inclusion constraint if and only if st st st st 1 2 s s t1 t2 A, st s st t A ) ■ Membership: Given two correspondence pairs ( A, sn E A and ( st A ) E A , A and A satisfy the sn sn sn st s t A C membership constraints if and only if A and st s sn s A, st s st t1 A, st s A ), st t2 ( 1 2 A = ( A ) and A and 1 st st A satisfy the 2 2 st A between S and T satisfy the st correspondence � E A st dominance constraints if and only if b&apos; � CSTREE(S) correspond to b&apos; � C STREE(T). ■ Globality: Given a S-SSTC</context>
<context position="27523" citStr="Menezes &amp; Richardson, 2001" startWordPosition="4391" endWordPosition="4394">constraints between the the root node Rs of the entire tree in the first SSTC and the root node Rt of the entire tree in the second SSTC, if and INT(String) in the second SSTC. This mean the whole tree in the first SSTC corresponds to the whole tree in the second SSTC, and the whole string in the first SSTC corresponds to the whole string in the second SSTC). A C A . This means the lexical correspondences are sn st t t always members in the structural correspondences. 2000), (Meyers et al., 2000), (Matsumoto et al., 1993) and (kaji et al., 1992). Note that the grammar alignment rules used in (Menezes &amp; Richardson, 2001) can be reformulated using these constraints to construct the transfer mappings from a synchronous source-target example. Figure 10 shows an example from Menezes and Richardson (2001), the logical form for the SpanishEnglish pair: (“En Informacidn del hipervinculo, haga clic en la direccidn del hipervinculo”, “Under Hyperlink Information, click the hyperlink address”). Figure 10: (a) the lexical correspondences, (b) the structural correspondences after applying the constraints. Recently, the development of machine translation systems requires a substantial amount of translation knowledge typic</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Menezes, Richardson, 2001</marker>
<rawString>Menezes, A. and Richardson, S. (2001). A Best-first Algorithm for Automatic Extraction of Transfer Mappings from Bilingual Corpora. In the workshop on Data-Driven Machine Translation, at the 38th Annual Meeting of the Association for Computational Linguistic (ACL 2001), Toulouse, France.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>A Meyers</author>
<author>M Kosaka</author>
<author>R Grishman</author>
</authors>
<title>Chart-based Transfer Rule Application in Machine Translation.</title>
<date>2000</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the 18th International Conference on Computational Linguistics (COLING</booktitle>
<location>Saarbracken, Germany /</location>
<contexts>
<context position="12804" citStr="Meyers et al., 2000" startWordPosition="1919" endWordPosition="1922">nguages, which are not isomorphic. Due to these limitations, instead of investigating into the synchronization of two grammars, we propose a flexible annotation schema (i.e. Synchronous Structured String-Tree Correspondence (S-SSTC)) to realize additional power and flexibility in expressing structural correspondences at the level of language sentence pairs. For example, such schema can serve as a mean to represent translation examples, or find structural correspondences for the purpose of transfer grammar learning (Menezes &amp; Richardson, 2001), (Aramaki et al., 2001), (Watanabe et al., 2000), (Meyers et al., 2000), (Matsumoto et al., 1993), (kaji et al., 1992), and example-base machine translation EBMT3 (Sato &amp; Nagao, 1990), (Sato, 1991), (Richardson et al., 2001), (Al-Adhaileh &amp; Tang, 1999). 3.1 The Synchronous SSTC In this section, we will discuss the definition and the formal properties of S-SSTC. A S-SSTC consists of a pair of SSTCs with an additional synchronization relation between them. The use of S-SSTC is motivated by the desire to describe not only the correspondence between the text and its representation structure in one language (i.e. SSTC) but also the correspondence between two languages</context>
<context position="27397" citStr="Meyers et al., 2000" startWordPosition="4370" endWordPosition="4373"> such that st A = STREE(Rs) : st s t s A = STREE(Rt) : st t INT(String) in the first SSTC, and satisfies the globality constraints between the the root node Rs of the entire tree in the first SSTC and the root node Rt of the entire tree in the second SSTC, if and INT(String) in the second SSTC. This mean the whole tree in the first SSTC corresponds to the whole tree in the second SSTC, and the whole string in the first SSTC corresponds to the whole string in the second SSTC). A C A . This means the lexical correspondences are sn st t t always members in the structural correspondences. 2000), (Meyers et al., 2000), (Matsumoto et al., 1993) and (kaji et al., 1992). Note that the grammar alignment rules used in (Menezes &amp; Richardson, 2001) can be reformulated using these constraints to construct the transfer mappings from a synchronous source-target example. Figure 10 shows an example from Menezes and Richardson (2001), the logical form for the SpanishEnglish pair: (“En Informacidn del hipervinculo, haga clic en la direccidn del hipervinculo”, “Under Hyperlink Information, click the hyperlink address”). Figure 10: (a) the lexical correspondences, (b) the structural correspondences after applying the cons</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Meyers, Kosaka, Grishman, 2000</marker>
<rawString>Meyers A., Kosaka M., and Grishman R. (2000). Chart-based Transfer Rule Application in Machine Translation. In Proceedings of the 18th International Conference on Computational Linguistics (COLING 2000). Saarbracken, Germany / Luxembourg.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>A Meyers</author>
<author>R Yangarber</author>
<author>R Grishman</author>
</authors>
<title>Alignment of Shared Forests for Bilingual Corpora.</title>
<date>1996</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the 16th International Conference on Computational Linguistics (COLING-96),</booktitle>
<pages>459--465</pages>
<location>Copenhagen,</location>
<marker>Meyers, Yangarber, Grishman, 1996</marker>
<rawString>Meyers, A., Yangarber, R. and Grishman R. (1996). Alignment of Shared Forests for Bilingual Corpora. In Proceedings of the 16th International Conference on Computational Linguistics (COLING-96), Copenhagen, Denmark, pp 459-465.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>J Milicevic</author>
</authors>
<title>A short guide to the Meaning-Text linguistic theory.</title>
<date>2001</date>
<booktitle>Computational Linguistics and Intelligent Text Processing, Coleccion en Ciencias de Computacion, Fondo de Cultura Economica- IPN -</booktitle>
<editor>In Alexander Gelbukh (ed.),</editor>
<publisher>UNAM, Mexico.</publisher>
<marker>Milicevic, 2001</marker>
<rawString>Milicevic J. (2001). A short guide to the Meaning-Text linguistic theory. In Alexander Gelbukh (ed.), Computational Linguistics and Intelligent Text Processing, Coleccion en Ciencias de Computacion, Fondo de Cultura Economica- IPN - UNAM, Mexico.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>O Rambow</author>
<author>G Satta</author>
</authors>
<title>Synchronous Models of language.</title>
<date>1996</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the 34th Meeting of the Association for Computational Linguistics (ACL-96),</booktitle>
<location>Santa Cruz, CA, USA.</location>
<contexts>
<context position="1886" citStr="Rambow &amp; Satta, 1996" startWordPosition="254" endWordPosition="257"> is very well suited for the construction of a Bilingual Knowledge Bank (BKB), where the examples are kept in form of S-SSTCs. KEYWORDS: parallel text, Structured String-Tree Correspondence (SSTC), Synchronous SSTC, Bilingual Knowledge Bank (BKB), Tree Bank Annotation Schema. 1. INTRODUCTION There is now a consensus about the fact that natural language should be described as correspondences between different levels of representation. Much of theoretical linguistics can be formulated in a very natural manner as stating correspondences (translations) between layers of representation structures (Rambow &amp; Satta, 1996). In this paper, a flexible annotation schema called Structured String-Tree Correspondence (SSTC) (Boitet &amp; Zaharin, 1988) will be introduced to capture a natural language text, its corresponding abstract linguistic representation and the mapping (correspondence) between these two. The correspondence between the string and its associated representation tree structure is defined in terms of the sub-correspondence between parts of the string (substrings) and parts of the tree structure (subtrees), which can be interpreted for both analysis and generation. Such correspondence is defined in a way </context>
<context position="10276" citStr="Rambow &amp; Satta, 1996" startWordPosition="1545" endWordPosition="1548">5) corresponds to the whole sentence “John picks the box up”. The case depicted in Figure 2, describes how the SSTC structure treats some non-standard linguistic phenomena. The particle &amp;quot;up&amp;quot; is featurised into the verb &amp;quot;pick&amp;quot; and in discontinuous manner (e.g. &amp;quot;up&amp;quot; (4-5) in &amp;quot;pick-up&amp;quot; (1-2+4-5)) in the sentence &amp;quot;He picks the box up&amp;quot;. For more details on the proprieties of SSTC, see Boitet &amp; Zaharin (1988). 3. SYNCHRONOUS SSTC STRUCTURE Much of theoretical linguistics can be formulated in a very natural manner as stating correspondences (translations) between layers of representation structures (Rambow &amp; Satta, 1996), such as the relation between syntax and semantic. An analogous problem is to be defined in such a way that expresses the correspondence between a language and its translations in other languages. Therefore the synchronization of two adequate linguistic formalisms seems to be an appropriate representation for that. The idea of parallelized formalisms is widely used one, and one which has been applied in many different ways. The use of synchronous formalisms is motivated by the desire to describe two languages that are closely related to each other but that do not have the same structures. For</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Rambow, Satta, 1996</marker>
<rawString>Rambow, O. and Satta, G. (1996). Synchronous Models of language. In Proceedings of the 34th Meeting of the Association for Computational Linguistics (ACL-96), Santa Cruz, CA, USA.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>S Richardson</author>
<author>W Dolan</author>
<author>A Menezes</author>
<author>J Pinkham</author>
</authors>
<title>Achieving commercial-quality translation with examplebased methods.</title>
<date>2001</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of Machine Translation SUMMIT VIII,</booktitle>
<pages>293--297</pages>
<contexts>
<context position="12957" citStr="Richardson et al., 2001" startWordPosition="1942" endWordPosition="1945"> annotation schema (i.e. Synchronous Structured String-Tree Correspondence (S-SSTC)) to realize additional power and flexibility in expressing structural correspondences at the level of language sentence pairs. For example, such schema can serve as a mean to represent translation examples, or find structural correspondences for the purpose of transfer grammar learning (Menezes &amp; Richardson, 2001), (Aramaki et al., 2001), (Watanabe et al., 2000), (Meyers et al., 2000), (Matsumoto et al., 1993), (kaji et al., 1992), and example-base machine translation EBMT3 (Sato &amp; Nagao, 1990), (Sato, 1991), (Richardson et al., 2001), (Al-Adhaileh &amp; Tang, 1999). 3.1 The Synchronous SSTC In this section, we will discuss the definition and the formal properties of S-SSTC. A S-SSTC consists of a pair of SSTCs with an additional synchronization relation between them. The use of S-SSTC is motivated by the desire to describe not only the correspondence between the text and its representation structure in one language (i.e. SSTC) but also the correspondence between two languages (synchronous correspondence). Definitions: - Let each of S and T be SSTC which consists of a triple (st, tr, co), where st is a string in one language, </context>
<context position="25744" citStr="Richardson et al., 2001" startWordPosition="4022" endWordPosition="4025">f and f are governed by the following constraints: sn st ■ Singleness: A node N which has a synchronization correspondence, can participate in one and only one f E A , and one and only one f E A . This means sn st allowing one-to-one, one-to-many and many-to-many, but the mappings do not overlap. ■ Dominance: Given two subtrees S and T, there is a Note that these constraints can be used to license only the linguistically meaningful synchronous correspondences between the two SSTCs of the S-SSTC (i.e. between the two languages). For instance, when building translation units in EBMT approaches (Richardson et al., 2001), (Aramaki, 2001), (AlAdhaileh &amp;Tang, 1999), (Sato &amp; Nagao, 1990), (Sato, 1991), (Sadler &amp; Vendelmans, 1990), etc., where S-SSTC can be used to represent the entries of the BKB or when S-SSTC used as an annotation schema to find the translation correspondences (lexical and structural correspondences) for transferrules’ extraction from parallel parsed corpus (Menezes &amp; Richardson, 2001), (Watanabe et al., A = A correspondence pairs ■ Inclusion: Given two 1 st st A and A C A . A C inclusion constraint if and only if st st st st 1 2 s s t1 t2 A, st s st t A ) ■ Membership: Given two correspondenc</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Richardson, Dolan, Menezes, Pinkham, 2001</marker>
<rawString>Richardson S., Dolan W., Menezes A. and Pinkham J. (2001). Achieving commercial-quality translation with examplebased methods. In Proceedings of Machine Translation SUMMIT VIII, Spain, pp 293-297.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>V Sadler</author>
<author>R Vendelmans</author>
</authors>
<title>Pilot Implementation of a Bilingual Knowledge Bank.</title>
<date>1990</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the 13th International Conference on Computational Linguistics (COLING-90),</booktitle>
<volume>3</volume>
<pages>449--451</pages>
<location>Helsinki, Finland,</location>
<contexts>
<context position="25852" citStr="Sadler &amp; Vendelmans, 1990" startWordPosition="4038" endWordPosition="4041">n correspondence, can participate in one and only one f E A , and one and only one f E A . This means sn st allowing one-to-one, one-to-many and many-to-many, but the mappings do not overlap. ■ Dominance: Given two subtrees S and T, there is a Note that these constraints can be used to license only the linguistically meaningful synchronous correspondences between the two SSTCs of the S-SSTC (i.e. between the two languages). For instance, when building translation units in EBMT approaches (Richardson et al., 2001), (Aramaki, 2001), (AlAdhaileh &amp;Tang, 1999), (Sato &amp; Nagao, 1990), (Sato, 1991), (Sadler &amp; Vendelmans, 1990), etc., where S-SSTC can be used to represent the entries of the BKB or when S-SSTC used as an annotation schema to find the translation correspondences (lexical and structural correspondences) for transferrules’ extraction from parallel parsed corpus (Menezes &amp; Richardson, 2001), (Watanabe et al., A = A correspondence pairs ■ Inclusion: Given two 1 st st A and A C A . A C inclusion constraint if and only if st st st st 1 2 s s t1 t2 A, st s st t A ) ■ Membership: Given two correspondence pairs ( A, sn E A and ( st A ) E A , A and A satisfy the sn sn sn st s t A C membership constraints if and</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Sadler, Vendelmans, 1990</marker>
<rawString>Sadler V. and Vendelmans, R. (1990). Pilot Implementation of a Bilingual Knowledge Bank. In Proceedings of the 13th International Conference on Computational Linguistics (COLING-90), Vol. 3, Helsinki, Finland, pp 449-451.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>S Sato</author>
<author>M Nagao</author>
</authors>
<title>Towards Memory-based Translation.</title>
<date>1990</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the 13th International Conference on Computational Linguistics (COLING-90),</booktitle>
<volume>3</volume>
<pages>247--252</pages>
<location>Helsinki, Fenland,</location>
<contexts>
<context position="12916" citStr="Sato &amp; Nagao, 1990" startWordPosition="1936" endWordPosition="1939"> two grammars, we propose a flexible annotation schema (i.e. Synchronous Structured String-Tree Correspondence (S-SSTC)) to realize additional power and flexibility in expressing structural correspondences at the level of language sentence pairs. For example, such schema can serve as a mean to represent translation examples, or find structural correspondences for the purpose of transfer grammar learning (Menezes &amp; Richardson, 2001), (Aramaki et al., 2001), (Watanabe et al., 2000), (Meyers et al., 2000), (Matsumoto et al., 1993), (kaji et al., 1992), and example-base machine translation EBMT3 (Sato &amp; Nagao, 1990), (Sato, 1991), (Richardson et al., 2001), (Al-Adhaileh &amp; Tang, 1999). 3.1 The Synchronous SSTC In this section, we will discuss the definition and the formal properties of S-SSTC. A S-SSTC consists of a pair of SSTCs with an additional synchronization relation between them. The use of S-SSTC is motivated by the desire to describe not only the correspondence between the text and its representation structure in one language (i.e. SSTC) but also the correspondence between two languages (synchronous correspondence). Definitions: - Let each of S and T be SSTC which consists of a triple (st, tr, co</context>
<context position="25809" citStr="Sato &amp; Nagao, 1990" startWordPosition="4032" endWordPosition="4035"> A node N which has a synchronization correspondence, can participate in one and only one f E A , and one and only one f E A . This means sn st allowing one-to-one, one-to-many and many-to-many, but the mappings do not overlap. ■ Dominance: Given two subtrees S and T, there is a Note that these constraints can be used to license only the linguistically meaningful synchronous correspondences between the two SSTCs of the S-SSTC (i.e. between the two languages). For instance, when building translation units in EBMT approaches (Richardson et al., 2001), (Aramaki, 2001), (AlAdhaileh &amp;Tang, 1999), (Sato &amp; Nagao, 1990), (Sato, 1991), (Sadler &amp; Vendelmans, 1990), etc., where S-SSTC can be used to represent the entries of the BKB or when S-SSTC used as an annotation schema to find the translation correspondences (lexical and structural correspondences) for transferrules’ extraction from parallel parsed corpus (Menezes &amp; Richardson, 2001), (Watanabe et al., A = A correspondence pairs ■ Inclusion: Given two 1 st st A and A C A . A C inclusion constraint if and only if st st st st 1 2 s s t1 t2 A, st s st t A ) ■ Membership: Given two correspondence pairs ( A, sn E A and ( st A ) E A , A and A satisfy the sn sn </context>
</contexts>
<marker>Sato, Nagao, 1990</marker>
<rawString>Sato S. and Nagao M. (1990). Towards Memory-based Translation. In Proceedings of the 13th International Conference on Computational Linguistics (COLING-90), Vol. 3, Helsinki, Fenland, pp 247-252.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>S Sato</author>
</authors>
<title>Example-Based Machine Translation.</title>
<date>1991</date>
<tech>Ph.D. thesis,</tech>
<institution>Kyoto University,</institution>
<contexts>
<context position="12930" citStr="Sato, 1991" startWordPosition="1940" endWordPosition="1941">ose a flexible annotation schema (i.e. Synchronous Structured String-Tree Correspondence (S-SSTC)) to realize additional power and flexibility in expressing structural correspondences at the level of language sentence pairs. For example, such schema can serve as a mean to represent translation examples, or find structural correspondences for the purpose of transfer grammar learning (Menezes &amp; Richardson, 2001), (Aramaki et al., 2001), (Watanabe et al., 2000), (Meyers et al., 2000), (Matsumoto et al., 1993), (kaji et al., 1992), and example-base machine translation EBMT3 (Sato &amp; Nagao, 1990), (Sato, 1991), (Richardson et al., 2001), (Al-Adhaileh &amp; Tang, 1999). 3.1 The Synchronous SSTC In this section, we will discuss the definition and the formal properties of S-SSTC. A S-SSTC consists of a pair of SSTCs with an additional synchronization relation between them. The use of S-SSTC is motivated by the desire to describe not only the correspondence between the text and its representation structure in one language (i.e. SSTC) but also the correspondence between two languages (synchronous correspondence). Definitions: - Let each of S and T be SSTC which consists of a triple (st, tr, co), where st is</context>
<context position="25823" citStr="Sato, 1991" startWordPosition="4036" endWordPosition="4037">synchronization correspondence, can participate in one and only one f E A , and one and only one f E A . This means sn st allowing one-to-one, one-to-many and many-to-many, but the mappings do not overlap. ■ Dominance: Given two subtrees S and T, there is a Note that these constraints can be used to license only the linguistically meaningful synchronous correspondences between the two SSTCs of the S-SSTC (i.e. between the two languages). For instance, when building translation units in EBMT approaches (Richardson et al., 2001), (Aramaki, 2001), (AlAdhaileh &amp;Tang, 1999), (Sato &amp; Nagao, 1990), (Sato, 1991), (Sadler &amp; Vendelmans, 1990), etc., where S-SSTC can be used to represent the entries of the BKB or when S-SSTC used as an annotation schema to find the translation correspondences (lexical and structural correspondences) for transferrules’ extraction from parallel parsed corpus (Menezes &amp; Richardson, 2001), (Watanabe et al., A = A correspondence pairs ■ Inclusion: Given two 1 st st A and A C A . A C inclusion constraint if and only if st st st st 1 2 s s t1 t2 A, st s st t A ) ■ Membership: Given two correspondence pairs ( A, sn E A and ( st A ) E A , A and A satisfy the sn sn sn st s t A C </context>
</contexts>
<marker>Sato, 1991</marker>
<rawString>Sato, S. (1991). Example-Based Machine Translation. Ph.D. thesis, Kyoto University, Japan.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>S Shieber</author>
</authors>
<title>Restricting the Weak Generative Capacity of Synchronous Tree Adjoining Grammar.</title>
<date>1994</date>
<journal>Computational Intelligence,</journal>
<volume>10</volume>
<issue>4</issue>
<pages>371--385</pages>
<contexts>
<context position="11587" citStr="Shieber, 1994" startWordPosition="1750" endWordPosition="1751"> languages, for example, for the purpose of immediate structural translation in machine translation (Abeill6 et al.,1990), (Harbusch &amp; Poller,1996), or for relating a syntactic TAG and semantic one for the same language (Shieber &amp; Schabes,1990). S-TAG is a variant of Tree Adjoining Grammar (TAG) introduced by (Shieber &amp; Schabes,1990) to characterize correspondences between tree adjoining languages. Considering the original definition of S-TAGs, one can see that it does not restrict the structures that can be produced in the source and target languages. It allows the construction of a non-TAL (Shieber, 1994), (Harbusch &amp; Poller, 2000). As a result, Shieber (1994) propose a restricted definition for S-TAG, namely, the IS-TAG for isomorphic S-TAG. In this case only TAL can be formed in each component. This isomorphism requirement is formally attractive, but for practical applications somewhat too strict. Also contrastive well-known translation phenomena exist in different languages, which cannot be expressed by IS-TAG, Figure 3 illustrates some examples (Shieber, 1994). Similar limitations also appear in synchronous CFGs (Harbusch &amp; Poller,1994). Figure 3: Kinds of relations between different langu</context>
<context position="19164" citStr="Shieber (1994)" startWordPosition="3032" endWordPosition="3033">arget under the pair ( s ( synchronous correspondence. Whereas, the phrase sn“the heavy box” is corresponds to the phrase “kotak berat itu” in the target is expressed by ( ( , ( ) ⇔(2- st st s t 5,2-5) under the ( synchronous correspondence. st 4. HANDLING NON-STANDARD CASES WITH S-SSTC As mentioned earlier, there are some non-standard phenomena exist between different languages, that cause challenges for synchronized formalisms. In this Section, we will describe some example cases, which are drawn from the problem of using synchronous formalisms to define translations between languages (e.g. Shieber (1994) cases). Due to lack of space we will only brief on some of these non-standard cases without going into the details. Figure 4 illustrates a case where the English sentence has non-standard cases of featurisation, crossed dependency and a many-to-one synchronous correspondence in “picks up”. Another case is reordering of words in the phrases, which is clear in the phrase “thedet heavyadj boxn” and it corresponding phrase “kotakn beratadj itudet” in the target. Figure 5, shows two non-standard cases between languages; e.g. French and English. First, the case of many-to-one correspondence, where </context>
</contexts>
<marker>Shieber, 1994</marker>
<rawString>Shieber, S. (1994). Restricting the Weak Generative Capacity of Synchronous Tree Adjoining Grammar. Computational Intelligence, 10(4): 371-385.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>S Shieber</author>
<author>Y Schabes</author>
</authors>
<title>Synchronous Tree Adjoining Grammars.</title>
<date>1990</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the 13th International Conference on Computational Linguistics (COLINGS-90),</booktitle>
<pages>253--258</pages>
<location>Helsinki, Finland,</location>
<marker>Shieber, Schabes, 1990</marker>
<rawString>Shieber, S. and Schabes, Y. (1990). Synchronous Tree Adjoining Grammars. In Proceedings of the 13th International Conference on Computational Linguistics (COLINGS-90), Helsinki, Finland, pp 253-258.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>H Somers</author>
</authors>
<title>Review article: Example-based Machine Translation,</title>
<date>1999</date>
<journal>Machine Translation,</journal>
<volume>14</volume>
<pages>113--157</pages>
<marker>Somers, 1999</marker>
<rawString>Somers, H. (1999). Review article: Example-based Machine Translation, Machine Translation, 14: 113-157.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>E K Tang</author>
</authors>
<title>Natural Language Analysis in Machine Translation (MT) Based on the String-Tree Correspondence Grammar (STCG).</title>
<date>1994</date>
<tech>PhD. thesis,</tech>
<institution>Universiti Sains Malaysia, Penang, Malaysia.</institution>
<contexts>
<context position="8567" citStr="Tang, 1994" startWordPosition="1273" endWordPosition="1274"> and its dependency tree together with the correspondences between substrings of the sentence and subtrees of the tree. Figure 2 illustrates the sentence “John picks the box up” with its corresponding SSTC. It contains a nonprojective correspondence. An interval is assigned to each word in the sentence, i.e. (0-1) for “John”, (1-2) for “picks”, (2-3) for “the&amp;quot;, (3-4) for “box” and (4-5) for “up”. A substring in the sentence that corresponds to a node in the representation tree is denoted by assigning the interval of the substring to SNODE of 2 These definitions are based on the discussion in (Tang, 1994) and Boitet &amp; Zaharin (1988). John John box the.box the NP the.box the box VP V pick up picks.up Figure 1: The correspondence between the string “he picks the box up” and its representation tree (dependency tree and phrasestructure tree), together with the sub-correspondences between the substrings and subtrees. Tree pick up John box the String John picks the box up S Tree NP VP John V NP pick up the box String John picks the box up NP John John pick up picks.up picks[v] up[p] String the[det] (2-3/2-3) 0John 1picks2 1picks2 the3box u5 4up5 ( 12+45 1-2+4-5 Tree /0-5) John[n] (0-1/0-1) box [n] (</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Tang, 1994</marker>
<rawString>Tang E. K. (1994). Natural Language Analysis in Machine Translation (MT) Based on the String-Tree Correspondence Grammar (STCG). PhD. thesis, Universiti Sains Malaysia, Penang, Malaysia.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>E K Tang</author>
<author>Y Zaharin</author>
</authors>
<title>Handling Crossed Dependencies with the STCG.</title>
<date>1995</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of NLPRS’95, Seoul,</booktitle>
<contexts>
<context position="6835" citStr="Tang &amp; Zaharin, 1995" startWordPosition="987" endWordPosition="990">Mel&apos;cuk, 1997) and (Mili&amp;evi6, 2001). 2.1 The SSTC Annotation Structure The SSTC is a general structure that can associate an arbitrary tree structure to string in a language as desired by the annotator to be the interpretation structure of the string, and more importantly is the facility to specify the correspondence between the string and the associated tree which can be nonprojective (Boitet &amp; Zaharin, 1988). These features are very much desired in the design of an annotation scheme, in particular for the treatment of linguistic phenomena, which are non-standard, e.g. crossed dependencies (Tang &amp; Zaharin, 1995). Definitions2: - An SSTC is a general structure, which is a string in a language associated with an arbitrary tree structure; i.e. its interpretation structure, and the correspondence between the string and its associated tree, which can be non-projective; i.e. SSTC is a triple (st, tr, co), where st is a string in one language, tr is its associated representation tree structure and co is the correspondence between st and tr. - The correspondence co between a string and its representation tree is made of two interrelated correspondences: a) Between nodes and substrings (possibly discontinuous</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Tang, Zaharin, 1995</marker>
<rawString>Tang, E. K. and Zaharin, Y. (1995). Handling Crossed Dependencies with the STCG. In Proceedings of NLPRS’95, Seoul, Korea.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>H Watanabe</author>
<author>S Kurohashi</author>
<author>E Aramaki</author>
</authors>
<title>Finding Structural Correspondences from Bilingual Parsed Corpus for Corpus-based Translation.</title>
<date>2000</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the 18th International Conference on Computational Linguistics (COLING</booktitle>
<location>Luxembourg/Saarbruecken, Germany.</location>
<contexts>
<context position="12781" citStr="Watanabe et al., 2000" startWordPosition="1915" endWordPosition="1918">ions between different languages, which are not isomorphic. Due to these limitations, instead of investigating into the synchronization of two grammars, we propose a flexible annotation schema (i.e. Synchronous Structured String-Tree Correspondence (S-SSTC)) to realize additional power and flexibility in expressing structural correspondences at the level of language sentence pairs. For example, such schema can serve as a mean to represent translation examples, or find structural correspondences for the purpose of transfer grammar learning (Menezes &amp; Richardson, 2001), (Aramaki et al., 2001), (Watanabe et al., 2000), (Meyers et al., 2000), (Matsumoto et al., 1993), (kaji et al., 1992), and example-base machine translation EBMT3 (Sato &amp; Nagao, 1990), (Sato, 1991), (Richardson et al., 2001), (Al-Adhaileh &amp; Tang, 1999). 3.1 The Synchronous SSTC In this section, we will discuss the definition and the formal properties of S-SSTC. A S-SSTC consists of a pair of SSTCs with an additional synchronization relation between them. The use of S-SSTC is motivated by the desire to describe not only the correspondence between the text and its representation structure in one language (i.e. SSTC) but also the correspondenc</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Watanabe, Kurohashi, Aramaki, 2000</marker>
<rawString>Watanabe H., Kurohashi S., and Aramaki E. (2000). Finding Structural Correspondences from Bilingual Parsed Corpus for Corpus-based Translation. In Proceedings of the 18th International Conference on Computational Linguistics (COLING 2000), Luxembourg/Saarbruecken, Germany.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>A Zolkovski</author>
<author>T Mel&apos;cuk</author>
</authors>
<title>On a Possible Method an Instruments for Semantic Synthesis (of texts).</title>
<date>1965</date>
<journal>Scientific and Technological Information,</journal>
<volume>6</volume>
<pages>23--28</pages>
<contexts>
<context position="6116" citStr="Zolkovski &amp; Mel&apos;cuk (1965)" startWordPosition="873" endWordPosition="876">ojective (e.g. scrambling, cross serial dependencies, etc.). Hence, it is very much desired to define the correspondence in a way to be able to handle the non-standard cases (e.g. non-projective correspondence), see Figure 1. Towards this aim, a flexible annotation structure called Structured String-Tree Correspondence (SSTC) was introduced in Boitet &amp; Zaharin (1988) to record the string of terms, its associated representation structure and the mapping between the two, which is expressed by the sub-correspondences recorded as part of a SSTC. 1 The Meaning-Text Theory (MTT) was put forward in (Zolkovski &amp; Mel&apos;cuk (1965), in the framework of research in Machine translation. More presentations of MTT can be found in (Mel&apos;cuk, 1997) and (Mili&amp;evi6, 2001). 2.1 The SSTC Annotation Structure The SSTC is a general structure that can associate an arbitrary tree structure to string in a language as desired by the annotator to be the interpretation structure of the string, and more importantly is the facility to specify the correspondence between the string and the associated tree which can be nonprojective (Boitet &amp; Zaharin, 1988). These features are very much desired in the design of an annotation scheme, in particu</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Zolkovski, Mel&apos;cuk, 1965</marker>
<rawString>Zolkovski, A. and Mel&apos;cuk, T. (1965). On a Possible Method an Instruments for Semantic Synthesis (of texts). Scientific and Technological Information, 6: 23-28.</rawString>
</citation>
</citationList>
</algorithm>
</algorithms>